<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>mental-healthonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/mental-health/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinmental-health on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 14:11:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/mental-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Useful Overview of Neurodiversity</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/useful-overview-of-neurodiversity/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 14:11:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/useful-overview-of-neurodiversity/</guid>
  <description>Myk Bolkonstky’s Things Every Software Engineer Should Know About Neurodiversity:
A lot of the work in neurodiversity now seems to be suggesting that grouping traits together and circling that and calling it a thing isn’t the best way to reason about this. Insurance companies really love it.
Neurodiversity provides an alternate take on traits that are common to card/ADHD, autism, OCD, and others. Myk’s talk summarizes them better than I could, and better than resources I could find for linking.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>watch</category>  <category>mental-health</category>  <category>neurodiversity</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Myk Bolkonstky&rsquo;s <a href="https://egghead.io/lessons/egghead-things-every-software-engineer-should-know-about-neurodiversity">Things Every Software Engineer Should Know About Neurodiversity</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A lot of the work in neurodiversity now seems to be suggesting that grouping
traits together and circling that and calling it a thing isn’t the best way to
reason about this. Insurance companies really love it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Neurodiversity provides an alternate take on traits that are common to <a href="/card/adhd/">card/ADHD</a>, autism, OCD, and others. Myk’s talk summarizes them better than I could, and better than resources I could find for linking.</p>
<p>The talk lasts half an hour including questions. Some occasional audio issues thanks to everyone’s new remote life, but the transcript makes following easier.</p>
<p>Some new / clarified bits for me — aside from the above quote:</p>
<ul>
<li>many folks experience these traits, but their intensity for neurodivergent folks is such that we must plan our lives around them</li>
<li>useful medical information is not widely available</li>
<li>&ldquo;dead time&rdquo; oh god that thing where your brain won’t let you do something now because you’re planning to do something later</li>
<li>description of &ldquo;autistic burnout&rdquo; sounds like something I’m going through right now</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Open Sourcing Mental Illness</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/06/open-sourcing-mental-illness/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/06/open-sourcing-mental-illness/</guid>
  <description>Watching YAPCNA videos, and the most important to me today had nothing to do with card/Perl. I loved Ed Finkler’s talk about mental health among developers. His OSMI project - Open Sourcing Mental Illness - aims to improve workplace and community awareness and resources for mental health. Good stuff. Many domains and communities need this effort, and his chosen community is tech. Worth checking out.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>mental-health</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Ed Finkler's OSMI project</h2><p>Watching <a href="http://www.yapcna.org">YAPCNA</a> videos, and the most important to me today had nothing to do with <a href="/card/perl/">card/Perl</a>. I loved  <a href="https://funkatron.com">Ed Finkler</a>&rsquo;s talk about mental health among developers. His <a href="https://osmihelp.org">OSMI</a> project - Open Sourcing Mental Illness - aims to improve workplace and community awareness and resources for mental health. Good stuff. Many domains and communities need this effort,
and his chosen community is tech. Worth checking out.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bWqSuBg8AMo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
