<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>procreateonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/procreate/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinprocreate on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 23:15:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/procreate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Something new to color</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/12/something-new-to-color/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 23:15:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/12/something-new-to-color/</guid>
  <description> Roughly four hours of bedtime drawing over the last few days. The challenge of a brain that has to timeshare hobbies.
But hey, I remembered to leave the linework layer alone this time. You can color your own if you want!
2020-12-15-linework.jpg image/jpeg 1050 pixels wide, 1050 pixels high Licensed under Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0) </description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>symmetry</category>  <category>color-me</category>  <category>procreate</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-12-18.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-12-18.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Roughly four hours of bedtime drawing over the last few days. The challenge of a brain that has to timeshare hobbies.</p>
<p>But hey, I remembered to leave the linework layer alone this time. You can color your own if you want!</p>
<div class="image-link">
  <div class="image-link-preview">
    <a href="2020-12-15-linework.jpg">
      <img src="2020-12-15-linework-96x96.jpg" alt="thumbnail of linked image">
    </a>
  </div>
  <div class="image-link-details">
    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="2020-12-15-linework.jpg">
          <tt>2020-12-15-linework.jpg</tt>
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>image/jpeg</li>
      <li>1050 pixels wide, 1050 pixels high</li>
      <li>Licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</a></li>
    </ul>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Kistler Tree</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/kistler-tree/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 20:25:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/kistler-tree/</guid>
  <description>Found this in my image folder the other day. It’s from working through Mark Kistler’s book You can Draw in 30 Days last year. I like it. Sure I kinda already know I can draw. But it’s good to refresh yourself every so often.
Tree
Oh, and I used Max Ulichney’s MaxPack brush sets forProcreate. The Gouache pack for sure, and probably others.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>art-attack</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Found this in my image folder the other day. It’s from working through <a href="https://markkistler.com/">Mark Kistler</a>&rsquo;s book <em>You can Draw in 30 Days</em> last year. I like it. Sure I kinda already know I can draw. But it’s good to refresh yourself every so often.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-04-18.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-04-18.jpg"/></figure>
Tree</p>
<p>Oh, and I used <a href="https://maxulichney.com/">Max Ulichney</a>&rsquo;s <a href="https://gumroad.com/maxulichney">MaxPack</a> brush sets for<a href="https://procreate.art/">Procreate</a>. The Gouache pack for sure, and probably others.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Again with the manual symmetry</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/12/again-with-the-manual-symmetry/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2019 12:37:51 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/12/again-with-the-manual-symmetry/</guid>
  <description>I spent forty hours over the last month or so inbox/Drawing this.
Couldn’t decide which aspect I liked best. Line work? Color? Values? So I went with all three.
On another note, I kinda want to study more about image formats. JPEG clearly has some issues with the red. PNG is unacceptably large thanks to all the detail work.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>symmetry</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I spent forty hours over the last month or so <em>inbox/Drawing</em> this.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-12-15.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-12-15.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Couldn’t decide which aspect I liked best. Line work? Color? Values? So
I went with all three.</p>
<p>On another note, I kinda want to study more about image formats. JPEG
clearly has some issues with the red. PNG is unacceptably large thanks
to all the detail work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Teabagging a Monsto</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/05/teabagging-a-monsto/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/05/teabagging-a-monsto/</guid>
  <description>2022-11-20
This post made more sense before Twitter had new owners and I locked down my account. Oh well. It’s still a cute picture.
So there was a tweet exchange with a friend on Sunday about “teabagging a monsto.”
I didn’t think to ask for context. Context is generally unexpected on Twitter, and sometimes downright unwelcome. Presumably Rachel’s friend was interacting oddly with monsters in a game. Or maybe not.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Yeah I know. That's not what "teabagging" is.</h2><blockquote>
<p><strong>2022-11-20</strong></p>
<p>This post made more sense before Twitter had new owners and I locked down my account. Oh well. It&rsquo;s still a cute picture.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So there was a <a href="https://twitter.com/wholemilk/status/1124911645786959872">tweet exchange</a> with a friend on Sunday about &ldquo;teabagging a monsto.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I didn’t think to ask for context. Context is generally unexpected on Twitter, and sometimes downright unwelcome. Presumably Rachel’s friend was interacting oddly with monsters in a game. Or maybe not. I don’t judge.</p>
<p>I still replied, of course. Even without context. We follow each other.
We’re friends outside of Twitter. It <em>should</em> be okay.</p>
<p>Random note, since I’d still like this to be a useful post. Here are a
few guidelines for a happy life on Twitter.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you don’t hear your name, don’t come running.</li>
<li>If you thought you heard your name, don’t come running unless you
know each other.</li>
<li>Most important: save your dumb jokes for your friends, not the
random strangers who get retweeted into your timeline. That ticks
off the strangers.</li>
<li>Remember you might tick your friends off sometimes too. Just try to
be considerate.</li>
</ul>
<p>Anyways. Overnight my mind wandered, and by Sunday afternoon the
wandering had turned into a sketch. I mean I know what
<a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=teabagging">teabagging</a>
is. Be careful, that’s an Urban Dictionary link, and most definitely not
safe for work.</p>
<p>But what if &ldquo;teabagging&rdquo; meant something else? What if it merely
involved fetching a fresh bag of tea for your friendly monster guest?</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2019/sketch.jpg" alt="The sketch"/></figure></p>
<p>Being the sort of person I am, I had to embellish the script in
<a href="https://procreate.art">Procreate</a>. And then post it in the thread.</p>
<p>I’m not going to lie. I like this picture. Picked a small number of main
colors and adjusted saturation and brightness to build on those. The
horns are great. And that is a respectable teabag.</p>
<p>Perfect for teabagging the monstos.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Cake Batter</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/cake-batter/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/cake-batter/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting the doodle time in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Getting the doodle time in.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-10.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-10.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>The background — and likely a few of the lines, if I&rsquo;m being honest — were inspired by a recent viewing of the movie <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heavy_Metal_%28film%29">Heavy Metal</a>.</p>
<p>Posted a version of this to the social networks. <a href="https://shellybedsaul.com/">My mom</a> had some comments which resulted in both a name and a few color adjustments.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Three Circles</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/02/three-circles/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/02/three-circles/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;That &lt;a href=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/01/circular-grids-with-python-and-pillow/&#34;&gt;circle template&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned a couple weeks ago? Well, I made it so I could draw stuff like this!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>buy-me</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That <a href="/post/2019/01/circular-grids-with-python-and-pillow/">circle template</a> I mentioned a couple weeks ago? Well, I made it so I could draw stuff like this!</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-02-05.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-02-05.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Spent about a month on it, an hour or so at a time. Will I do it again? Of course! Will I do it regularly? Who knows? It took more patience than I&rsquo;m used to, and I still haven&rsquo;t decided how much I like it.</p>
<p>I enjoyed figuring out the templates with code and then building on them manually. I also have ideas for some Celtic style images.</p>
<p>But first I need to get back to preparing a work talk.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Satellite</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/satellite/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 11 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/satellite/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;This one took a while.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>sketchbook-mobile</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>buy-me</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This one took a while.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-11.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-11.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>I found a quick symmetry doodle in Sketchbook from a month or two ago, turned off symmetry, then spent about a week and a half reworking the lines and adding &ldquo;just one more bit.&rdquo; Switch over to Procreate for a couple hours of touchups, because I prefer the feel of Procreate&rsquo;s brushes.</p>
<p>Finally forced myself to stop and post this. It is too easy to keep going until you lose steam and end up with an overwhelmingly intricate but <em>unfinished</em> work.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Vegvisir</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/06/vegvisir/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/06/vegvisir/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to see my own take on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://norse-mythology.org/vegvisir/&#34;&gt;Vegvísir&lt;/a&gt;, an Icelandic symbol also called a “Nordic Compass”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>buy-me</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to see my own take on the <a href="https://norse-mythology.org/vegvisir/">Vegvísir</a>, an Icelandic symbol also called a &ldquo;Nordic Compass&rdquo;.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-06-13.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-06-13.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>After a <em>lot</em> of work my favorite part was the underlying rough line work. So I kept that and scrapped the rest.</p>
<p>I will probably make more attempts drawing this symbol. Read up on it studying mythology, folklore, and symbolism when I was a kid, then forgot about it until it started cropping up in my life recently. This will do for a start though.</p>
<p>All I know for sure about the Vegvísir is this description from the 19th Century <a href="https://www.academia.edu/13008560/Huld_Manuscript_of_Galdrastafir_Witchcraft_Magic_Symbols_and_Runes_-_English_Translation">Huld manuscript</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Carry this sign with you and you won&rsquo;t get lost in storms or bad weather, even though in unfamiliar surrounds.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Who wouldn&rsquo;t like that?</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Duotone Panel</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/12/duotone-panel/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/12/duotone-panel/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/../../../attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-19.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-19.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month I read an article about &lt;a href=&#34;https://muddycolors.blogspot.com/2012/08/duotone-illustrations.html&#34;&gt;duotone illustrations&lt;/a&gt; and decided to try
a version of the technique myself someday. Today was that day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>celtic</category>  <category>zentangle</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-19.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-19.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Last month I read an article about <a href="https://muddycolors.blogspot.com/2012/08/duotone-illustrations.html">duotone illustrations</a> and decided to try
a version of the technique myself someday. Today was that day.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duotone">Duotone</a> uses two colors — usually black and a color such as blue or red — to make an image. It was popular for a while in 20th Century illustration because it cost less than full color printing. Skilled duotone illustrators like <a href="https://americanillustration.org/project/mead-schaeffer/">Mead Schaeffer</a> produced visually arresting images.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/mead-schaeffer-red.jpg" alt="&ldquo;Red&rdquo; by Mead Schaeffer"/></figure></p>
<p><em>Illustration by Mead Schaeffer via <a href="https://muddycolors.blogspot.com/2012/08/duotone-illustrations.html">Muddy Colors</a></em></p>
<p>I wanted to manually create duotone images in sketch apps like Procreate. Time to describe what I came up with.</p>
<p>This post isn’t a tutorial, but the information may be useful to you. For that matter it may be useful to <em>me</em>. That’s really what this whole site is about, after all: making life easier for future me, and hopefully maybe you too.</p>
<p>I had a couple of self-imposed limitations while making this. I deliberately chose to only use flat color for this experiment — no shading to speak of. I also used a smaller canvas than usual. It wasn’t a technical limitation, but it did limit the detail I could put into the image.</p>
<p>In retrospect, that’s probably a good thing for this experiment. I ended up with about 50 layers the way I put things together, and this might have slowed my iPad down with a large image.</p>
<h2 id="linework">Linework</h2>
<p>The first finished step is a solid black and white image. It started out as a
knotwork panel demonstration, but somewhere along the way I decided the panel
needed extras. Most of those extras came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26311641-the-tangles-of-kells">Tangles of Kells</a>.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/duotone-panel-linework.png" alt="Linework"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="values">Values</h2>
<p>Then I put the values in, working from a grayscale palette. Nothing fancy going on here. The background is darker, the foreground is lighter, with a couple small variations along the way.</p>
<p>I set the drop shadow layers to &ldquo;Soft Light&rdquo; so they wouldn’t obscure whatever was beneath them.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/duotone-panel-values.png" alt="Values"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="color">Color</h2>
<p>For color, I created a new layer under the value layers, which I set to &ldquo;Multiply.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Here’s what that looked like, with everything else but linework cut out.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/duotone-panel-color.png" alt="Color"/></figure></p>
<p>I had an initial stage where all the shadows were hatched lines. Duotone didn’t occur to me until near the end of linework. I’ll try value-based shading for everything in some future sketches.</p>
<p>In order to have value mix nicely with color, I put each color layer beneath its value layer and set the value layer’s mode to &ldquo;Multiply.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="final">Final</h2>
<p>And that’s how I ended up with this.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-19.jpg" alt="Final image"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="what-now">What now?</h2>
<p>That was fun.</p>
<p>I want to explore duotone more, trying some specific ideas.</p>
<ul>
<li>Shading instead of value blocks.</li>
<li>Use higher contrasting values. This ended up just a tiny bit muddy to my eyes.</li>
<li>Multiple color layers — tritone?</li>
<li>Mixing grayscale values and color values in a style more similar to the  duotone illustrations I like so much.</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Knotwork Practice</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/12/knotwork-practice/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/12/knotwork-practice/</guid>
  <description>This started with practicing a knotwork pattern from Celtic Art: The Methods of Construction, and ended up as an exercise in how long I could add stuff before I got bored. Thirteen hours. Not bad.
Not in a row, of course.
Oh and I threw in a couple tangle elements from The Tangles of Kells.
I might be ready to try drawing things on purpose again. Usually it’s just that my hands get itchy when I see blank space.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>celtic</category>  <category>zentangle</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-15.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-12-15.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>This started with practicing a knotwork pattern from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/618205.Celtic_Art">Celtic Art: The Methods of Construction</a>, and ended up as an exercise in how long I could add stuff before I got bored. Thirteen hours. Not bad.</p>
<p>Not in a row, of course.</p>
<p>Oh and I threw in a couple tangle elements from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26311641-the-tangles-of-kells">The Tangles of Kells</a>.</p>
<p>I might be ready to try drawing things on purpose again. Usually it’s just that my hands get itchy when I see blank space.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
