<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>2012onRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2012/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentin2012 on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 14:33:48 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/post/2012/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Oh yeah, Ryan Davis is awesome</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2012/08/oh-yeah-ryan-davis-is-awesome/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2012 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2012/08/oh-yeah-ryan-davis-is-awesome/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Found out about a talk from Ryan Davis at Cascadia RubyConf because of an &lt;a href=&#34;http://gilesbowkett.blogspot.com/2012/08/ryan-davis-you-are-idiot-liar-or-fool.html&#34;&gt;incensed reaction&lt;/a&gt; to it from Giles Bowkett on &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; blog. Thing is, I like the talk. I even like the bits that Bowkett doesn’t. Of course, I wasn’t one of the folks specifically mentioned, and he was. So there’s going to be a different perspective there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>blogspot</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Found out about a talk from Ryan Davis at Cascadia RubyConf because of an <a href="http://gilesbowkett.blogspot.com/2012/08/ryan-davis-you-are-idiot-liar-or-fool.html">incensed reaction</a> to it from Giles Bowkett on <em>his</em> blog. Thing is, I like the talk. I even like the bits that Bowkett doesn&rsquo;t. Of course, I wasn&rsquo;t one of the folks specifically mentioned, and he was. So there&rsquo;s going to be a different perspective there.</p>
<p>But I could have been. Heck, I tried my hand at cute ranty posts a few years back, and one of them threw what I thought was a light hearted jab at Ryan.  But it really bugged him. He told me so the next time I logged into IRC, much later. I could see why it would when I looked back at the post and imagined it without context. The joke wasn&rsquo;t even that funny <em>with</em> context. Our posts on big or little blogs - or social networks, for that matter - have a reach far beyond what we might think when we&rsquo;re sitting at the keyboard. They can span the globe in a split second, and still be out there for years.</p>
<p>On revisiting the forgotten joke, I saw that it could be considered offensive if you weren&rsquo;t in the unique garden of my brain. I was really shaken by the fact that somebody I had such respect for (the guy is basically a genius in Ruby and other domains) had taken a lasting offense to something that I&rsquo;d long forgotten about. So I cleared the post and got into the habit of checking myself before wrecking myself.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t mind if someone somewhere thinks I&rsquo;m a jerk. I want it to be for a better reason than me pretending to be an insult comic, though.</p>
<p>So, yeah. The guidelines mentioned by Ryan Davis for tending to the community are great, but it wouldn&rsquo;t do any harm to use them as guidelines for tending yourself. You know: &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t be a dick!&rdquo;</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3fG4dDJAifo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
