<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>glovesonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/gloves/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentingloves on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/gloves/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Winter Hat and Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>The gloves use the same <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch">Son of Stitch &rsquo;n Bitch</a> pattern as the <a href="/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/">purple beer gloves</a> I knitted this summer. This pair turned out much better. Learning through repetition! However, that Loops &amp; Threads &ldquo;Impeccable&rdquo; yarn is far too stiff for gloves. I would prefer a sportweight blend to this worsted weight acrylic for things that need to move with my hands.</p>
<p>I lost the label for the hat yarn but it&rsquo;s probably Patons North America Classic Wool Worsted. So soft and cozy on my head. I accidentally changed tension once I picked up speed, resulting in an interesting gauge effect along the bottom ribbing, but that is already becoming less pronounced with wear. You can also see twisted stiches where I recovered a row but mounted those stitches incorrectly. This happened plenty of times in the past, but I wanted to remember these little mistakes for future projects.</p>
<p>This isn&rsquo;t me being overly fussy. It&rsquo;s just me moving past the beginner mode of &ldquo;Yay I finished something!&rdquo; to hopefully more intermediate habits that ask &ldquo;how will I do better next time?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The hat pattern came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter&rsquo;s Handy Book of Patterns</a> by Ann Budd. As I get more comfortable with knitting, my interests move from specific patterns to templates and techniques. This book seems a good step in that direction so far. Quite a few tables and charts, which calls out to old memories of gaming books. The tables are just math helpers though. I can see not needing them after a certain point. That&rsquo;s the day I&rsquo;ll be able to knit custom fit stuff from memory. Something to look forward to!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Beer Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I knitted a pair of the fingerless Beer Gloves from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch&#34;&gt;Son of Stitch ’n Bitch&lt;/a&gt;. This involved a couple new techniques and several new mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I knitted a pair of the fingerless Beer Gloves from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch">Son of Stitch &rsquo;n Bitch</a>. This involved a couple new techniques and several new mistakes.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-04.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-04.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>These gloves have a nice cable along the back. A seed stitch patch near the palm supposedly helps with opening bottles. I have not tested them for opening bottles yet, but the texture feels nice and gives a bit more grip than the reverse stockinette alone.</p>
<p>The pattern called for double-pointed needles. I tried something new instead, and knit this using the <a href="https://www.craftsy.com/knitting/article/demystifying-the-magic-loop/">magic loop</a> method with a single circular needle. It worked well until the thumbs and fingers. It&rsquo;s kind of easy to get yourself going in the wrong direction if you aren&rsquo;t careful. I accidentally knit one thumb pointing almost straight out, instead of the slight angle of its mate.</p>
<p>Since my purl gauge tends to be loose, the reverse stockinette that dominates this pattern produced a bulkier glove than I would have liked. If I make these again with the same <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/yarns/library/loops--threads-impeccable-solids">Impeccable Solids</a> yarn, I should use slightly smaller needle than the pattern calls for. And I probably won&rsquo;t use magic loop, either.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://knitfreedom.com/invisible-ribbed-bind-off/">invisible ribbed bind off</a> took me a few tries to get right. Fortunately, I had ten opportunities to learn. Even more fortunately, the recipient of these gloves finds the loose yarn loops of failure to be charming.</p>
<p>Enough nitpicking! These are good gloves. They keep their wearer warm while keeping fingers free for fine motor skills. The cable is gorgeous. These are destined for a friend, who already loves them and will wear them enthusiastically once the weather gets cold enough.</p>
<h2 id="what-next">What next?</h2>
<p>I enjoyed making these, but I want to learn more about glove construction in general instead of haphazardly implementing cool-looking patterns. I have several simple mitten and glove ideas planned!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Nicole&#39;s Fingerless Gauntlets</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/02/nicoles-fingerless-gauntlets/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/02/nicoles-fingerless-gauntlets/</guid>
  <description>Still catching up with the backlog of finished knitting. Finished these a couple weeks ago.
Like post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves, these started from a fingerless gauntlet pattern in Sally Melville’s [The Knitting Experience Book 2: The Purl Stitch] I stayed closer to the original pattern this time, only adding a couple of stripes.
Impressively, I also managed to stay close to the recommended gauge. How? Went a size up on the needles. I tend to knit tight when working in the round.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Still catching up with the backlog of finished knitting. Finished these a couple weeks ago.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-02-02.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-02-02.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Like <a href="/post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves/">post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves</a>, these started from a fingerless gauntlet pattern in Sally Melville&rsquo;s [The Knitting Experience Book 2: The Purl Stitch]<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24691.The_Knitting_Experience"></a> I stayed closer to the original pattern this time, only adding a couple of stripes.</p>
<p>Impressively, I also managed to stay close to the recommended gauge. How? Went a size up on the needles. I tend to knit tight when working in the round. I used that tendency to my advantage in the next project, which I&rsquo;ll post about shortly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Rainy&#39;s Mish-Mash Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;By special request, some fingerless gloves using a bit of every sock yarn I own.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>By special request, some fingerless gloves using a bit of every sock yarn I own.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-03-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-03-20.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>When I offered to make a pair, my friend pointed out a pair she had seen on Etsy. I started from a straightforward pattern in Sally Melville&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24691.The_Knitting_Experience">The Knitting Experience Book 2: The Purl Stitch</a>.</p>
<p>Yes I&rsquo;ll try to find that pair on Etsy again at some point, because it&rsquo;s a great design and people should buy that designer&rsquo;s stuff.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
