<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>snapshotonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/snapshot/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinsnapshot on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/snapshot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: 2024-01-21 Snapshot</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-21-snapshot/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-21-snapshot/</guid>
  <description>Mostly working on the brain-blog hybrid.
Jots Almost done with my brain-blog hybrid project, merging My Public Brain with Random Geekery. Made some forward progress on the current Job Search. Nothing concrete yet, but people want to talk to me. That feels nice. Plan shift the live site from blog to brain-blog ever forward with job search Bookmarks A fair bit of Obsidian stuff got my attention this week as I worked out ways to publish the vault within my own very particular workflow.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
  
   <category>snapshot</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mostly working on the brain-blog hybrid.</p>
<h2 id="jots">Jots</h2>
<ul>
<li>Almost done with my brain-blog hybrid project, merging <a href="/card/my-public-brain/">My Public Brain</a> with <a href="/card/random-geekery/">Random Geekery</a>.</li>
<li>Made some forward progress on the current <a href="/card/job-search/">Job Search</a>. Nothing concrete yet, but people want to talk to me. That feels nice.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="plan">Plan</h2>
<ul>
<li>shift the live site from blog to brain-blog</li>
<li>ever forward with job search</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="bookmarks">Bookmarks</h2>
<p>A fair bit of <a href="/card/obsidian/">Obsidian</a> stuff got my attention this week as I worked out ways to publish the vault within my own very particular workflow. BTW I&rsquo;d just use Obsidian Publish if I wasn&rsquo;t me.</p>
<dl>
<dt><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/rehype-obsidian-callout">rehype-obsidian-callout - npm</a></dt>
<dd>support callouts (notes, warnings, etc) in remark-based SSGs</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/remark-obsidian">remark-obsidian - npm</a></dt>
<dd>converts most of Obsidian&rsquo;s markup, though right now it strips out path information when slugifying links (<code>/card/ADHD</code> becomes <code>/cardadhd</code>)</dd>
<dt><a href="https://github.com/zoni/obsidian-export">GitHub - zoni/obsidian-export: Rust library and CLI to export an Obsidian vault to regular Markdown</a></dt>
<dd>handy for exporting Obsidian vaults; does not yet handle callouts or YouTube embeds; I ended up settling on <a href="/card/obsidian-export/">obsidian-export</a> + some post-processing for my current publishing workflow</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cNbWmjGNZD8">Can You See The Red Flags Of A Toxic Tech Company? - YouTube</a></dt>
<dd>this will always be relevant; some good general indicators, but the vaguest-sounding one to &ldquo;trust your gut&rdquo; is the one I&rsquo;ve regretted ignoring over the years</dd>
</dl>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: 2024-01-14 Snapshot</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-14-snapshot/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-14-snapshot/</guid>
  <description>Conversion of blog to vault in progress
Jots What’s up?
job hunting; check out my LinkedIn Profile if you’re looking for a remote or hybrid mostly backend senior dev based near Seattle building Kotlin and Kubernetes familiarity for some specific job prospects; I could see enjoying Kotlin, and I’m starting to understand how and when Kubernetes is useful; I remain a fan of small tools when reasonable, though working towards a new public brain by creating an Obsidian vault from this site and pulling recurring concepts into topic cards Plan What’s coming up next week?</description>
   <category>post</category> 
  
   <category>snapshot</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Two weeks in a row? Wow!</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/Pasted%20image%2020240114095144.png" alt="attachments/Pasted image 20240114095144.png"/></figure>
Conversion of blog to vault in progress</p>
<h2 id="jots">Jots</h2>
<p>What&rsquo;s up?</p>
<ul>
<li>job hunting; check out my <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brianwisti/">LinkedIn Profile</a> if you&rsquo;re looking for a remote or hybrid mostly backend senior dev based near Seattle</li>
<li>building <a href="/card/kotlin/">Kotlin</a> and <em>Kubernetes</em> familiarity for some specific job prospects; I could see enjoying Kotlin, and I&rsquo;m starting to understand how and when Kubernetes is useful; I remain a fan of small tools when reasonable, though</li>
<li>working towards a new public brain by creating an <a href="/card/obsidian/">Obsidian</a> vault from this site and pulling recurring concepts into topic cards</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="plan">Plan</h2>
<p>What&rsquo;s coming up next week?</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/card/job-search/">Job Search</a> is the priority, won&rsquo;t bother you with the search / submit / follow-up task list</li>
<li>plan out how to build a new version of the site that would include posts and public cards, including pre-processing for posts that are integrated with Obsidian&rsquo;s Markdown extras and automated testing of the results</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="bookmarks">Bookmarks</h2>
<p>Kind of a theme this week. One might even call it a mood.</p>
<dl>
<dt><a href="https://blog.cassidoo.co/post/human-curation/">I miss human curation</a></dt>
<dd>Cassidy&rsquo;s correct that the human-curated Web is still here — I mean hello it me — and also correct that it&rsquo;s a lot harder to find thanks to algorithm-driven social networks and search engines; guess we&rsquo;ll have to go back to old-fashioned ways like blogrolls, webrings, bookmark pages, and variations like this weekly review</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.niemanlab.org/2023/12/the-robots-will-make-us-more-human/">The robots will make us more human » Nieman Journalism Lab</a></dt>
<dd>predicting that more LLM spam and the &ldquo;AI&rdquo; boom in general will result in more people splitting off from the old big social networks and platforms, being more creative to differentiate between the plausible mediocrity generated by automated systems; I would love for it to be true</dd>
<dt><a href="https://thenewstack.io/7-guiding-principles-for-working-with-llms/">7 Guiding Principles for Working with LLMs - The New Stack</a></dt>
<dd>TL;DR: Think out loud; Never trust, always verify; Use a team of assistants; Ask for choral explanations; Outsource pattern recognition; Automate transformations; Learn by doing</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/ethical-web-principles/">W3C TAG Ethical Web Principles</a></dt>
<dd>&ldquo;The web should be a platform that helps people and provides a positive social benefit&rdquo; says it all really; A W3C spec draft on building the Web we want to be in</dd>
</dl>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: 2024-01-07 Snapshot</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-07-snapshot/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2024/01/2024-01-07-snapshot/</guid>
  <description>Output of a ComfyUI Stable Diffusion experiment
Shared notes. Not too much. Mostly links.
I want to call them “weekly notes.” I lack confidence in my time awareness, so let’s go with “snapshot.” But hey. I fill up my notes every day. Why not share some of the interesting items here from time to time?
Bookmarks All Things Considered - The Mark Kistler Interview - YouTube Been a fan of Mark Kistler since before I was a fan of computers.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
  
   <category>snapshot</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/2024-01-07-snapshot-cover.jpg" alt="attachments/2024-01-07-snapshot-cover.jpg"/></figure>
Output of a ComfyUI Stable Diffusion experiment</p>
<p>Shared notes. Not too much. Mostly links.</p>
<p>I want to call them &ldquo;weekly notes.&rdquo; I lack confidence in my time awareness, so let&rsquo;s go with &ldquo;snapshot.&rdquo; But hey. I fill up my notes every day. Why not share some of the interesting items here from time to time?</p>
<h2 id="bookmarks">Bookmarks</h2>
<dl>
<dt><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WP4cSfrJUuE">All Things Considered - The Mark Kistler Interview - YouTube</a></dt>
<dd>Been a fan of Mark Kistler since before I was a fan of computers. I&rsquo;ve shared one Kistler-inspired work — <a href="/post/2020/04/kistler-tree/">post/2020/04/kistler-tree</a> — and have multiple sketchbooks full of similar. Of course I listened to this interview.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://buildexcellentwebsit.es/">Be the browser’s mentor, not its micromanager. - Build Excellent Websites</a></dt>
<dd>Exposed to <em>Build Excellent Websites</em> thanks to the <a href="https://github.com/madrilene/eleventy-excellent">Eleventy Excellent</a> starter. Good guidelines and good tools for Web design.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.freepascal.org/">Free Pascal - Advanced open source Pascal compiler for Pascal and Object Pascal</a></dt>
<dd>Niklaus Wirth died this week. The Pascal programming language was only one of his contributions, but it&rsquo;s the one I kind of know.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://stable-diffusion-art.com/comfyui/">Beginner&rsquo;s Guide to ComfyUI - Stable Diffusion Art</a></dt>
<dd>A workflow-based GUI for <a href="https://stablediffusionxl.com">Stable Diffusion</a> as I learn the different technologies under the buzzword blanket of <em>*Artificial Intelligence*</em>.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://github.com/ebullient/markdown-it-obsidian-callouts">ebullient/markdown-it-obsidian-callouts: Markdown extensions for obsidian</a></dt>
<dd><a href="https://obsidian.md">Obsidian</a> has some fairly specific syntax for callouts. This extension could help with that for publishing a second brain with <a href="https://11ty.dev">Eleventy</a>. Now I just need to switch to Eleventy. And stick with Obsidian.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://www.customink.com/fundraising/hackerstown-noto-peninsula-earthquake-relief-1747">Hackers.town Noto Peninsula Earthquake Relief Custom Ink Fundraising</a></dt>
<dd>Cool T-shirts for good causes, by the good folks at <a href="https://hackers.town">Hackers.town</a>, my preferred Fediverse instance.</dd>
<dt><a href="https://americandialect.org/2023-word-of-the-year-is-enshittification/">2023 Word of the Year is “enshittification” – American Dialect Society</a></dt>
<dd>Because honestly what other word could describe 2023 so well? <a href="https://pluralistic.net">Cory Doctorow</a> came up with it, and used it to great effect when <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/tiktok-platforms-cory-doctorow/">describing TikTok and others</a>.</dd>
</dl>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
