<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>exploringonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/exploring/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinexploring on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/exploring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Cougar Mountain</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</guid>
  <description>The park sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.
Be careful Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Last weekend I wandered the trails of Cougar Mountain Regional Wildland Park
</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/09/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg"/></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.kingcounty.gov/services/parks-recreation/parks/parks-and-natural-lands/popular-parks/cougar.aspx">park</a> sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.</p>
<h2 id="be-careful">Be careful</h2>
<p>Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently. Warning signs remind you about the area’s long history as a coal mine. Collapsed mines could collapse further with just a little weight on them. A decades-old underground fire presents ongoing <a href="https://www.heraldnet.com/news/cougar-mountain-mines-still-a-danger/">danger</a> from heat and toxic fumes.</p>
<p>Basically: if a sign tells me to stay back, I stay back.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/warning-sign.jpg" title="Pay attention to the warning signs" alt="sign warning of ground collapse or fatal gases"/></p>
<p>The trails are well-labeled, perhaps partly due to those hazards. I still managed to get myself turned around, because there were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cougar_Mountain_Regional_Wildland_Park#Official_Trails">so many trails</a>. Somewhere along the way I lost my paper map, but had enough signal to get the Washington Trails Association <a href="https://www.wta.org/our-work/about/trailblazer-mobile-app">Trailblazer</a> app installed on my phone and follow the links to a PDF map.</p>
<h2 id="look-at-the-trees">Look at the trees</h2>
<p>I think I focused a little too much on the hazards. Those are really in specific sections of the park, and are all clearly indicated. The park itself is lovely, green, and very Pacific Northwest.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/mossy.jpg" alt="Mossy"/></p>
<p>We have some lovely woods around here. I started taking that for granted over the years. My assorted <a href="/tags/sauntering">sauntering</a> trips have done a great job reminding me to not do that.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/tall-stump.jpg" alt="Tall stump"/></p>
<p>The trees on Cougar Mountain are young. When the mines started winding down, logging picked up. I saw several thick old stumps near the trail, giving me a hint of what the older growth must have looked like.</p>
<p>Some of those stumps had sprouts on them, while a few had full grown trees.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/old-stump.jpg" alt="Old stump with stump sprouts"/></p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/stump-tree.jpg" alt="Tree growing from stump"/></p>
<p>We got some rain recently. Everything that could be green was very green indeed. Even the rocks. I walked a little out of my way to see Fantastic Erratic, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glacial_erratic">glacial erratic</a> boulder left here by glacier action in some past ice age.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/fantastic-erratic.jpg" title="Fantastic Erratic" alt="Large mossy rock"/></p>
<p>My image shows the scale poorly. That single rock is roughly fifteen feet high. I took a rest break sitting on top of it, with room to stretch.</p>
<h2 id="anyways">Anyways</h2>
<p>I spent three hours walking about ten miles of trails around Cougar Mountain, enjoying the scenery and history. It didn’t feel as epic as <a href="/post/2018/09/mount-si/">walking up a mountain</a>, but I want to avoid chasing that &ldquo;epic&rdquo; feeling. I’m not racking up accomplishments. I’m getting out and appreciating more of the world around me. That includes epic moments, little details, and everything in between.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/fungi.jpg" title="Look! Fungus!" alt="clamshell-looking fungi on a tree trunk"/></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Mount Si</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</guid>
  <description>A rather rocky trail through the trees
Mount Si If Mount Si looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show Twin Peaks. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I sauntered up the main trail of Mount Si this weekend.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/09/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg"/>
A rather rocky trail through the trees</p>
<h2 id="mount-si">Mount Si</h2>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/mt-si.jpg" alt="Mount Si as seen from North Bend"/></p>
<p>If <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/mount-si">Mount Si</a> looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_Peaks">Twin Peaks</a>. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s. It was officially labeled a Natural Resources Conservation Area in 1987.</p>
<p>The Olympic and Cascade mountains defined my landscape growing up in the Puget Sound area, but I never went up any of them. I attribute that to my habit of mentally associating &ldquo;mountain climbing&rdquo; with the major challenge of Mount Rainier. I never thought of smaller mountains such as Mount Si. They challenge desk-bound people like myself but can still be done as a single day trip.</p>
<p>Oh, you pronounce &ldquo;Si&rdquo; as &ldquo;sigh&rdquo; — not &ldquo;see.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="getting-there">Getting there</h2>
<p>The trail is a short drive from Seattle, but Google Maps gave me a hard time. I ask for directions to Mount Si. It sends me to the base of the mountain, in somebody’s driveway and nowhere near a trail. Then I ask for directions to the Mount Si <em>Trail</em> and it tries to put me on a private road. This happens often enough that the owner put up a sign indicating there was no trail access on their property.</p>
<p>I abandoned Google Maps and found the trail proper a little further up the (public) road. You want to keep your eyes peeled. The sign for the trail is easy to miss if you don’t know the area.</p>
<p>Don’t forget about your <a href="http://discoverpass.wa.gov/">Discover Pass</a>! You need one to use the official parking spots, and there’s no public parking anywhere near the trail.</p>
<p>I admit it. I forgot about the pass. Fortunately, you can purchase one at the Ace Hardware in North Bend.</p>
<h2 id="the-trail">The trail</h2>
<p>The thing about sauntering up a mountain is that the trail occupies most of your attention. You might miss interesting stuff as you spend a few hours wondering how much trail you have left. Thankfully, the trail itself is pretty interesting. Some spots soft and flat, some spots packed with rocks, and sometimes both!</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/trail.jpg" alt="a trail section with packed rocks and dirt"/></p>
<p>The trail climbs around 3,000 feet over roughly four miles. A walk like that is easy enough for the experienced, but by the time I was halfway up I needed to rest every few minutes. Thank goodness nobody accompanied me! I bet a veteran walker would have been at best amused, and at worst annoyed, by my pace.</p>
<p>Nobody accompanied me, but I wasn’t alone. This trail gets loads of traffic, and has its own traffic rules.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you bring a dog, keep it on a leash, and clean up after it</li>
<li>People going up get right of way, so people going down need to make   room for them.</li>
<li>Be nice</li>
<li>Stay tidy — don’t be dropping garbage along the way!</li>
</ul>
<p>Everybody I encountered stuck with the rules, which were posted on an information board at the trail head. Well, I met a few off-leash dogs, but they were friendly.</p>
<p>My frequent breaks meant that I saw most sights while leaning or sitting on something, and waiting for my pulse to recover.</p>
<p>For example: my new, attractive, and very comfortable friend Stumpy the Stump.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/stumpy.jpg" alt="Check out this gnarled tree stump"/></p>
<p>I encountered impressive rocks all over the place. That’s not unusual in the Pacific Northwest, but you rarely see anything so <em>large</em> in Seattle.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/rock.jpg" alt="Rock!"/></p>
<p>Of course I looked up the details when I got home. These are <a href="https://www.usgs.gov/faqs/what-are-metamorphic-rocks-0">metamorphic</a> rocks, transformed by intense pressure. Apparently in the distant geological past, there was an oceanic plate volcano. Now, millions of years later, we walk around on it and call it Mount Si.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/more-rock.jpg" alt="These rocks used to be under an ocean?"/></p>
<p>I can’t help but feel very small and brief when I try wrapping my brain around a geological time scale.</p>
<h2 id="lunch">Lunch</h2>
<p>Eventually I ran out of mountain. I paused to have lunch and enjoy the view with half a dozen other like-minded folks.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/lunch.jpg" alt="Eating lunch and looking over Snoqualmie"/></p>
<p>I encountered few local critters on the way up. That’s probably because the ones that tolerate people knew to stick around up here where folks brought out food. Gray jays, chipmunks, and a wandering raven kept us company.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/grayjay.jpg" title="A photogenic gray jay posing — right before stealing my cracker!" alt="gray jay bird"/></p>
<p>Keep a tight grip on your meal! One jay grabbed a cracker right out of my hand when a hiker distracted me.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/jay-rocks.jpg" alt="Gray jay against rocks"/></p>
<p>I suppose a bird has to make a living. I can’t be mad when they’re so fearless and just so <em>pretty</em>.</p>
<h2 id="wandering-a-little-further">Wandering a little further</h2>
<p>So many folks came up, ate their lunch, and headed right back down. That confused me, because I was nowhere near done enjoying Mount Si. Maybe this is just a routine weekend thing for them. Me? Even if this becomes routine I’ll find excuses to stick around longer. Maybe I can bring my knitting.</p>
<p>I had read that the trail extended beyond my lunch spot, so I looked around until I saw the Haystack, an additional 200 feet of rock that marks the proper peak of Mount Si.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/haystack.jpg" title="The Haystack, Si&#39;s true summit" alt="rocky peak"/></p>
<p>I decided against climbing the Haystack this time. Almost halfway, I realized going down would be harder than going up. My body still felt the strain from walking up the mountain in the first place. Next trip.</p>
<p>Got some nice shots before I started back down, though.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/lovely.jpg" title="Sure the trees will break my fall eventually" alt="treetops seen from above"/></p>
<p>I spent the next hour or so lounging in the overlook between the Haystack and the gray jay crime haven, looking at flowers and appreciating the view.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/flowers.jpg" alt="Flower!"/></p>
<p>Surely the view impresses even more on clear days, but clouds are familiar to me. A clear sky would have disoriented me.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/overlook.jpg" alt="View from the overlook"/></p>
<p>A memorial marker placed at the overlook caught my eye.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/brett-marker.jpg" title="Memorial marker for Brett Hall 1962-1981" alt="memorial marker"/></p>
<p>Later I looked up the name on the marker, and found this nwhikers forum<a href="http://www.nwhikers.net/forums/viewtopic.php?p=202011&amp;sid=1b5ffb6683037d9488f2bbb5e5f4218b#202011">comment</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Brett Hall was from Lynnwood. His family used to live next door to mine. He disappeared on an intended dayhike on Mt Si with, I think, a group of friends. They searched at the time but didn’t find him; the assumption was that he took a tumble down a hill, or got disoriented, sat down and died of hypothermia. I’m not sure about the January 25th, 1981 date&ndash; or why they were hiking in the winter. (I was away at college at the time, so my info was secondhand.) If I recall, his body was found a year or so later after the snow melted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, yeah. Caution is smart even on small, popular mountains close to urban centers.</p>
<h2 id="heading-back">Heading back</h2>
<p>Once I rested enough — and my phone started running low on charge after so many pics — I headed back down the trail. Going down took less time than going up. Even so I took care, because those rocks in the path feel ever so solid when your feet are landing on them from above.</p>
<p>The sun came out when I was near the bottom of the mountain, and it was so gorgeous I felt the temptation to climb back up.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/sunshine.jpg" alt="Afternoon sun through trees and undergrowth"/></p>
<p>My feet would have hated me. Besides, because of my timing, I got back to Seattle at exactly the right moment to get waved at on West Seattle Bridge by a trolley bus full of furries having their own special day! That was an awesome &ldquo;welcome home!&rdquo; moment.</p>
<h2 id="the-aftermath">The aftermath</h2>
<p>I wore better shoes than at <a href="/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/">Island Center Forest</a>, so my feet feel fine today. My knees got more work than usual, but at least I can walk without major discomfort.</p>
<p>One thing is for sure: next time I go walking up a mountain, I bring my
<em>inbox/Knitting</em>!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Island Center Forest</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/</guid>
  <description>Island Center Forest contains roughly ten miles of trails. I walked about six of them yesterday. Today my feet hurt.
Getting There Island Center Forest is a 363 acre wooded nature preserve in the middle of Vashon Island, which is a short ferry ride from West Seattle. I skipped the car for this trip, looking to save money on ferry fares.
I regretted that plan a little when I reached the island and noticed that route 118 only runs every hour and a half on Saturdays.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/island-center-forest">Island Center Forest</a> contains roughly ten miles of trails. I walked about six of them yesterday. Today my feet hurt.</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-19.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-19.jpg"/></p>
<h2 id="getting-there">Getting There</h2>
<p>Island Center Forest is a 363 acre wooded nature preserve in the middle of <a href="http://www.vashonchamber.com/">Vashon Island</a>, which is a short ferry ride from West Seattle. I skipped the car for this trip, looking to save money on ferry fares.</p>
<p>I regretted that plan a <em>little</em> when I reached the island and noticed that <a href="https://www.kingcounty.gov/depts/transportation/metro/schedules-maps/118-119.aspx">route 118</a> only runs every hour and a half on Saturdays. No problem. I decided to walk until I reached something interesting. Lovely roads to drive on. Walking, maybe not so much. There was no sidewalk until I reached downtown Vashon about an hour after leaving the ferry terminal. Fortunately drivers were considerate as I negotiated the road shoulder on foot.</p>
<p>Found a grocery store in downtown Vashon and recharged with a snack while enjoying local art.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/art-cart.jpg" alt="Cool sketch on a cart. I missed the &lsquo;Trump/Putin 2016&rsquo; stickers until just now"/></p>
<p>The park itself was only about five minutes&rsquo; walk from the store.</p>
<h2 id="my-path">My Path</h2>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/map.jpg" title="The trails I covered, more or less" alt="map"/></p>
<p>The trails have names, but there were fewer signs than I would have liked. Given the large number of trails to choose from, I set my plan as &ldquo;when in doubt, turn right.&rdquo; That kept me on the outer edge of the park. About halfway through I had a better feel for the park layout, and made more deliberate choices about my path.</p>
<h2 id="the-park-itself">The Park Itself</h2>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/mossy-trees.jpg" alt="Mossy trees and undergrowth"/></p>
<p>This is a second-growth forest, moving from single-species tree plantations to a more diverse selection that provides better homes for wildlife and native growth. Trees provide pleasant shade throughout most of the park, which is good news for some of my friends who are sensitive to heat and sunlight.</p>
<p>Watch your step, though. You share these trails with horse riders, and droppings are a minor hazard underfoot.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/mukai-pond.jpg" alt="The southern bit of Mukai Pond"/></p>
<p>I visited in the tail end of summer. As lovely as Mukai and Meadowlake ponds were, you could tell they were ready for rain. Still — there was something in Mukai Pond big enough to make a splash when I got too close.</p>
<p>Folks sometimes accuse me of getting lost in the weeds, getting so wrapped up in details that I miss the big picture. They have a point. I could stand to step back and look at the forest occasionally instead of the trees.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/fungus.jpg" alt="Look! Fungus!"/></p>
<p>That said, these woods offered a wealth of details to keep my attention.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/cobwebs.jpg" alt="A spider neighborhood"/></p>
<p>I picked Meadowlake Pond as the end of my circuit, enjoying the view and the strange calls of the local ravens that were having a grand time in the wetlands. Maybe the calls weren’t strange for ravens. I’m accustomed to crows. These corvids definitely had a range of noises to make, from a &ldquo;Mwa!&rdquo; that sounded like a strange cat to vaguely simian noises to a water drop sound.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/attachments/img/2018/meadowlake-pond.jpg" alt="Meadowlake Pond"/></p>
<h2 id="the-aftermath">The Aftermath</h2>
<p>I timed my return from downtown Vashon a little more carefully, catching the 118 bus to the ferry terminal. Much better.</p>
<p>I put my Fitbit back on for the day — I’ve been taking a little vacation from it the last week or so to minimize distractions — and managed to get myself some new badges:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Trail Shoe&rdquo; for 30,000 steps in a day</li>
<li>&ldquo;Hiking Boot&rdquo; for 35,000 steps in a day</li>
<li>&ldquo;Skyscraper&rdquo; for 100 floors in a day</li>
</ul>
<p>16,000 or so of those steps were in the park itself, and pretty much all of those &ldquo;floors.&rdquo; It’s hardly mountain climbing, but there plenty of hills to cover. Anyways, back to my Fitbit vacation. My feet hurt and I won’t walk more than I must for the next couple days.</p>
<p>I enjoyed Island Center Forest, and particularly enjoyed getting out of Seattle for a day. I’m already deciding which park to make a day trip out of next time I feel the need to go sauntering.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Fauntleroy Park</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/fauntleroy-park/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/fauntleroy-park/</guid>
  <description>Today I explored Fauntleroy Park, a 28 acre park in West Seattle with some nice trails.
Years ago, I had a regular habit of exploring local parks and trails. Not hiking, mind you. Ugh. That sounds too purposeful for a person like me. No, sauntering. I just wanted to wander around, seeing what interests me, and enjoying the little differences each park offered.
You know what? It’s past time to start that habit back up.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>sauntering</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I explored <a href="http://fauntleroywatershed.org/">Fauntleroy Park</a>, a 28 acre park in West Seattle with some nice trails.</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><img src="/post/2018/07/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-08.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-08.jpg"/></p>
<p>Years ago, I had a regular habit of exploring local parks and trails. Not <em>hiking</em>, mind you. Ugh. That sounds too purposeful for a person like me. No, <a href="/tags/sauntering">sauntering</a>. I just wanted to wander around, seeing what interests me, and enjoying the little differences each park offered.</p>
<p>You know what? It’s past time to start that habit back up.</p>
<p>Fauntleroy Park is smaller than nearby <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/lincoln-park">Lincoln Park</a>, but I wanted someplace new to me.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/07/attachments/img/2018/stairs.jpg" alt="stairs leading uphill"/></p>
<p>I enjoyed following the park’s trails. Green, lush, and very local. <a href="http://www.nwplants.com/business/catalog/pol_mun.html">Sword ferns</a> everywhere! It left me feeling a bit nostalgic for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_belt">green belts</a> that have been steadily disappearing from the Pacific Northwest as we make room for more people.</p>
<p>The city is unavoidable. I could hear traffic at every point in the park. I found myself accidentally outside the park a few times in my brief visit. If you’re not careful some of the smaller trails will lead you to someone’s back yard. That makes me even more impressed by how much work has gone into maintaining the watershed in the middle of a busy city’s residential neighborhoods. Volunteers and students maintain the space, keeping it safe for salmon spawning, barred owls, and other critters.</p>
<p>And if you give nature half a chance, things start growing absolutely any place they can.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/07/attachments/img/2018/tree-roots.jpg" alt="trees growing from a decaying collapsed tree trunk"/></p>
<p>Still – I think next time I may want to venture a little further out. Seattle has many parks and trails, but I have visited the longer trails within the city many times over the years. The <a href="https://www.wta.org/">Washington Trails Association</a> provides resources for the aspiring saunterer, including an <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-outside/map">interactive map</a> of trails across Washington State.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Living in Seattle</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2003/07/living-in-seattle/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2003 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2003/07/living-in-seattle/</guid>
  <description>Seattle is a city. It may not be as big as Los Angeles or New York, but it is still a city. You do not have an excuse to be bored, even if you are flat broke. My wife and I have lived in Seattle since 1999, and it still feels like we are scraping the surface of what this area has to offer after ten years.
This page exists to guide folks around Seattle, with pointers to some trivia and favorite locations in town.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>babblings</category>  <category>seattle</category>  <category>exploring</category>  <category>coolnamehere</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>circa 2003, at least.</h2><p>Seattle is a city. It may not be as big as Los Angeles or New York, but it is still a city. You do not have an excuse to be bored, even if you are flat broke. My wife and I have lived in Seattle since 1999, and it still feels like we are scraping the surface of what this area has to
offer after ten years.</p>
<p>This page exists to guide folks around Seattle, with pointers to some trivia and favorite locations in town. You may find something new or forgotten in these pages. You might not agree with my opinions. That is okay. Go ahead and tell me all about it. Many ways to contact me are on the top of this page.</p>
<h2 id="seattle-neighborhoods">Seattle Neighborhoods</h2>
<p>Not all of them, obviously. Just a few that I’m more familiar with.</p>
<h3 id="skid-row">Skid Row</h3>
<p>You ever hear the term &ldquo;Skid Row&rdquo;? I’m told that phrase came from Seattle. Loggers used to skid logs down Yesler Way into the sawmill down near the waterfront. The street became sort of infamous for being where the worst of the city lived. 3rd and Yesler is still sort of the hairy armpit of the city, but there has been a lot of work to polish the street up. <a href="http://www.pioneersquare.org">Pioneer Square</a> is at the downtown end of Yesler. You won’t believe the amount of great food and music you can find around here. I’m trying to lose weight, so I avoid this neighborhood like the plague these days.</p>
<h3 id="fremont">Fremont</h3>
<p>Here’s a bit of trivia that will resolve a point of confusion for my dad when talking about Fremont. The neighborhood was named by its founders after the Nebraska town that they came from. These days, it’s a rapidly gentrifying — but still very active and artistic — spot in the northern part of Seattle. The people are nice, but maybe a little full of themselves sometimes. The shops are bright and fun to wander in. There’s no pressure to buy anything, but you’ll find good prices if you do feel like spending. Be smart about crossing the street, though. There have been more than a few accidents as people try to rush across against the crosswalk lights while some car is trying to rush through the yellow light. Don’t be paranoid, just be smart. That’s all I’m saying. And pay your respects to Lenin’s statue while you are in the neighborhood.</p>
<h3 id="phinney-ridge">Phinney Ridge</h3>
<p>Let me be honest. The only reason I know <em>anything</em> about Phinney Ridge is because we lived there for nearly four years. It is a gorgeous neighborhood at the very top of one of Seattle’s many hills. There are many expensive condos and older houses being remodeled by ambitious young families, but not much else.</p>
<p>Ha! Did you actually believe that? There’s not many shops here, but there’s still the <a href="http://www.zoo.org/">Woodland Park Zoo</a>! The sound of monkey loving late at night makes Phinney one of the most unusual city spots to live in. If you live in Seattle, you would be a fool not to get a membership to the zoo. It’s big. It’s beautiful. Membership is dirt cheap. You don’t even have to be big on animals. It’s nice to just come in and kick back for a relaxing bit of time on the grass.</p>
<p>As long as you’re in the neighborhood, you might as well walk up to Sully’s Snow Goose Tavern for a good pint of beer and a tasty veggie hot dog. I recommend their veggie dogs even if that is not normally your thing. They do have &ldquo;real&rdquo; hot dogs if you absolutely must have meat, but try the veggie version sometime. It’s good and tasty and leaves you wanting to ask if they’re <em>sure</em> that was the vegetarian version.</p>
<h3 id="central-district">Central District</h3>
<p>We have only explored the Central District a little, so I really only have one thing to tell you about: <a href="http://www.ezellschicken.com/">Ezell’s</a>. It’s the best danged fried chicken I have ever had. I’m getting hungry just thinking about it. Have you noticed that a lot of my neighborhood summaries mention food? Yeah, that’s how I’ve gone from being bone-skinny to needing to lose weight. Food in Seattle is really good and plentiful. You’ve been warned. Even <a href="http://www.oprah.com/index.html">Oprah Winfrey</a> has to be careful. Back in the day, she loved Ezell’s, gushed about it on TV, and the story claims that she even had their chicken specially delivered to Chicago. Yeah, I’d say it’s about that good. Be aware, though, the quality is a little inconsistent. It’s usually the best fried chicken ever, but occasionally they throw a dud so bad you wish you’d gone for grocery store deli chicken instead.</p>
<h3 id="international-district--chinatown">International District / Chinatown</h3>
<p>There is a minor identity crisis in this neighborhood. Some folks call it Chinatown, but it shows up on the map as the International District. Wander around a bit here. It’s nice. There are some great dim sum places, and <a href="http://www.uwajimaya.com/">Uwajimaya</a> is a fun store with lots and lots of great food for local families — and curious pasty white folk like me. I’m a big fan of the Kinokuniya book store, even though I can only read about a third of the titles. Someday I <em>will</em> learn Japanese, I swear!</p>
<h3 id="green-lake">Green Lake</h3>
<p>Joggers. That’s the first thing you notice when you visit this neighborhood. Bicyclists are probably the second. The last thing you notice will be either a jogger or a bicyclist, depending on who runs you down when you aren’t looking. You might notice a few things in between, though. The lake itself is pretty and well-maintained, with ducks and geese and an assortment of other urban wildlife varieties. There are a few good places to eat here, and at least one <a href="http://thecoffeerevolution.com/">great coffee shop</a>.</p>
<p>Most of the businesses in this neighborhood cater to the health-conscious sort of person: running supplies, bicycle shops, stuff like that. This obviously means that I haven’t been to half of the stores around me. As soon as they open a good shop for lazy computer geeks who like to knit, I’ll be there.</p>
<h2 id="so-long">So Long</h2>
<p>That’s it for the moment. Whenever I think of something else, I’ll add to this page. There is so much more that I would like to tell you about, but my typing fingers are already getting sore.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
