<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>craftonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/craft/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentincraft on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/craft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Hard symmetry soft colors</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/03/hard-symmetry-soft-colors/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/03/hard-symmetry-soft-colors/</guid>
  <description>intricate patterns drawn in the middle of the night is my jam
I don’t even know how many hours I spent on this. An hour or two a night — but not every night — since November or so?
I like it, however long I spent drawing the dang thing.
Linea takes a very constrained approach to tools. No automatic symmetry. No blend modes. Only five layers. Makes it feel like a paper sketch book, but with bonuses.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>color-me</category>  <category>linea-sketch</category>  <category>symmetry</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Linea needs a time tracker</h2><p><img src="/post/2021/03/../../../attachments/img/2021/2021-03-06.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/2021-03-06.png"/>
intricate patterns drawn in the middle of the night is my jam</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t even know how many hours I spent on this.  An hour or two a night — but not every night — since November or so?</p>
<p>I like it, however long I spent drawing the dang thing.</p>
<p><a href="https://linea-app.com/">Linea</a> takes a very constrained approach to tools.  No automatic symmetry.  No blend modes.  Only five layers.  Makes it feel like a paper sketch book, but with bonuses.  Their approach to color palettes is one of those bonuses.  I used their predefined &ldquo;Art Deco&rdquo; palette for this.</p>
<p>You can grab the line work yourself if you want something to color.</p>
<div class="image-link"><div class="image-link-preview">
  <a href="/post/2021/03/hard-symmetry-soft-colors/2021-03-06-linework.jpg">
    <img src="/post/2021/03/hard-symmetry-soft-colors/2021-03-06-linework-96x96.jpg" alt="thumbnail of linked image">
  </a>
</div>
<div class="image-link-details">
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="/post/2021/03/hard-symmetry-soft-colors/2021-03-06-linework.jpg">
        <tt>2021-03-06-linework.jpg</tt>
      </a>
    </li>
    <li>image/jpeg</li>
    <li>2047 pixels wide, 2047 pixels high</li>
    <li>Licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0)</a></li>
  </ul>
</div></div>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Deidre&#39;s Double Moss Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</guid>
  <description>blocked and ready to wear
Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!
The pattern Using Sensational Knitted Socks by Charlene Schurch, as usual. Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe moss stitch fallback.
The yarn brand Think Bamboo style B917 color 992 composition 45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon site https://thinkbamboo.com; doesn’t work for me at the moment The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I'm just glad I finished them</h2><p><img src="/post/2021/01/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg"/>
blocked and ready to wear</p>
<p>Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!</p>
<h2 id="the-pattern">The pattern</h2>
<p>Using <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/399836.Sensational_Knitted_Socks">Sensational Knitted Socks</a> by Charlene Schurch, as usual.
Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe <a href="https://www.gathered.how/knitting-and-crochet/knitting/moss-stitch/">moss
stitch</a> fallback.</p>
<h2 id="the-yarn">The yarn</h2>
<dl>
<dt>brand</dt>
<dd>Think Bamboo</dd>
<dt>style</dt>
<dd>B917</dd>
<dt>color</dt>
<dd>992</dd>
<dt>composition</dt>
<dd>45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon</dd>
<dt>site</dt>
<dd><a href="https://thinkbamboo.com">https://thinkbamboo.com</a>; doesn&rsquo;t work for me at the moment</dd>
</dl>
<p>The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.  It is beyond a hassle
to wind up, though.</p>
<h2 id="the-review">The review</h2>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Omg my beautiful handmade socks are so soft and a thing of BEAUTY <a href="https://t.co/cXmYHyI1CC">pic.twitter.com/cXmYHyI1CC</a></p>&mdash; Deidre Wisti (@IamMrsGeek) <a href="https://twitter.com/IamMrsGeek/status/1341594975629283328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Chaotic Symmetry</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/08/chaotic-symmetry/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/08/chaotic-symmetry/</guid>
  <description>I wish I drew this one larger. Then again, I thought it was going to be a quick bedtime sketch. Ended up spending probably around 40 hours on it.
I particularly enjoyed enabling and disabling symmetry at different stages. Made for what feels to me like a more organic image. If I were to go back and change anything, it might be to make foreground and background a little easier to differentiate.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>infinite-painter</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>In which I spend a month on a fifteen minute doodle</h2><p>I wish I drew this one larger. Then again, I thought it was going to be a quick bedtime sketch. Ended up spending probably around 40 hours on it.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/08/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-08-22.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-08-22.jpg"/></p>
<p>I particularly enjoyed enabling and disabling symmetry at different stages. Made for what feels to me like a more organic image. If I were to go back and change anything, it might be to make foreground and background a little easier to differentiate. Use different brushes, maybe.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Teabagging a Monsto</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/05/teabagging-a-monsto/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/05/teabagging-a-monsto/</guid>
  <description>2022-11-20
This post made more sense before Twitter had new owners and I locked down my account. Oh well. It’s still a cute picture.
So there was a tweet exchange with a friend on Sunday about “teabagging a monsto.”
I didn’t think to ask for context. Context is generally unexpected on Twitter, and sometimes downright unwelcome. Presumably Rachel’s friend was interacting oddly with monsters in a game. Or maybe not.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Yeah I know. That's not what "teabagging" is.</h2><blockquote>
<p><strong>2022-11-20</strong></p>
<p>This post made more sense before Twitter had new owners and I locked down my account. Oh well. It&rsquo;s still a cute picture.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So there was a <a href="https://twitter.com/wholemilk/status/1124911645786959872">tweet exchange</a> with a friend on Sunday about &ldquo;teabagging a monsto.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I didn’t think to ask for context. Context is generally unexpected on Twitter, and sometimes downright unwelcome. Presumably Rachel’s friend was interacting oddly with monsters in a game. Or maybe not. I don’t judge.</p>
<p>I still replied, of course. Even without context. We follow each other.
We’re friends outside of Twitter. It <em>should</em> be okay.</p>
<p>Random note, since I’d still like this to be a useful post. Here are a
few guidelines for a happy life on Twitter.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you don’t hear your name, don’t come running.</li>
<li>If you thought you heard your name, don’t come running unless you
know each other.</li>
<li>Most important: save your dumb jokes for your friends, not the
random strangers who get retweeted into your timeline. That ticks
off the strangers.</li>
<li>Remember you might tick your friends off sometimes too. Just try to
be considerate.</li>
</ul>
<p>Anyways. Overnight my mind wandered, and by Sunday afternoon the
wandering had turned into a sketch. I mean I know what
<a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=teabagging">teabagging</a>
is. Be careful, that’s an Urban Dictionary link, and most definitely not
safe for work.</p>
<p>But what if &ldquo;teabagging&rdquo; meant something else? What if it merely
involved fetching a fresh bag of tea for your friendly monster guest?</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/05/attachments/img/2019/sketch.jpg" alt="The sketch"/></p>
<p>Being the sort of person I am, I had to embellish the script in
<a href="https://procreate.art">Procreate</a>. And then post it in the thread.</p>
<p>I’m not going to lie. I like this picture. Picked a small number of main
colors and adjusted saturation and brightness to build on those. The
horns are great. And that is a respectable teabag.</p>
<p>Perfect for teabagging the monstos.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Psychedelic Playing Card</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/psychedelic-playing-card/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/psychedelic-playing-card/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;That cover image is kinda fuzzy. Better click on the original link image to see it properly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>infinite-painter</category>  <category>symmetry</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That cover image is kinda fuzzy. Better click on the original link image to see it properly.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/04/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-14.png" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-14.png"/></p>
<p>The result of a couple weeks of bedtime doodling.</p>
<p>Sometimes drawing constraints are fun: one layer. Two colors. One brush. Undo okay, changing brush size okay.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Cake Batter</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/cake-batter/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/cake-batter/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting the doodle time in.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Getting the doodle time in.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/04/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-10.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-04-10.jpg"/></p>
<p>The background — and likely a few of the lines, if I&rsquo;m being honest — were inspired by a recent viewing of the movie <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heavy_Metal_%28film%29">Heavy Metal</a>.</p>
<p>Posted a version of this to the social networks. <a href="https://shellybedsaul.com/">My mom</a> had some comments which resulted in both a name and a few color adjustments.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Garden Mandala</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/03/garden-mandala/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/03/garden-mandala/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;A Samsung Note 9 means my phone drawing has been upgraded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>infinite-painter</category>  <category>buy-me</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A Samsung Note 9 means my phone drawing has been upgraded.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/03/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-03-19.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-03-19.jpg"/></p>
<p>I feel like I neglected the blog this year. That&rsquo;s probably because of the half dozen draft posts I still need to finish. Also, I&rsquo;ve been busy working, drawing, learning, and even — <em>gasp</em> — socializing!</p>
<p>One of the big moments for me? Well, aside from dancing in public, which I hadn&rsquo;t done in well over a decade? The purchase of a Samsung Galaxy Note 9. Refurbished, because if I can save a few bucks I will. Drawing on it is a delight, pretty much. Not <em>quite</em> as smooth as iPad + Pencil, but far better than using a capacitive stylus on other phones. Overall, the Note takes me back to the days of having a small sketchbook with me at all times.</p>
<p>The Note is Android, which means I could install <a href="https://syncthing.net/">Syncthing</a> on it and grab a <a href="/post/2019/01/circular-grids-with-python-and-pillow/">circle template</a> from my desktop. My first serious sketch with the Note was of course another manual symmetry doodle.</p>
<p>The Note&rsquo;s specs meant that I could have many layers for relatively large images (this one is 4084x4084 pixels) and still get a smooth drawing experience. I like the end result, too.</p>
<p>I kind of want to take a break from the super detailed symmetry drawings,  though. Seems like that&rsquo;s all I&rsquo;ve been doing lately! Maybe practice some cartoon style doodles. Pull out the Mark Kistler books if I have to.</p>
<p>Oh, and I should finish those draft posts at some point.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Three Circles</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/02/three-circles/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/02/three-circles/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;That &lt;a href=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/01/circular-grids-with-python-and-pillow/&#34;&gt;circle template&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned a couple weeks ago? Well, I made it so I could draw stuff like this!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>drawing</category>  <category>procreate</category>  <category>buy-me</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That <a href="/post/2019/01/circular-grids-with-python-and-pillow/">circle template</a> I mentioned a couple weeks ago? Well, I made it so I could draw stuff like this!</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/02/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-02-05.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-02-05.jpg"/></p>
<p>Spent about a month on it, an hour or so at a time. Will I do it again? Of course! Will I do it regularly? Who knows? It took more patience than I&rsquo;m used to, and I still haven&rsquo;t decided how much I like it.</p>
<p>I enjoyed figuring out the templates with code and then building on them manually. I also have ideas for some Celtic style images.</p>
<p>But first I need to get back to preparing a work talk.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Picot Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</guid>
  <description>This hat is another round of the “basic hat” from Ann Budd’s The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from last time.
The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from A Treasury of Knitting Patterns. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I continue building my hat knitting knowledge!</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg"/></p>
<p>This hat is another round of the &ldquo;basic hat&rdquo; from Ann Budd’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a>. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from <a href="/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/">last time</a>.</p>
<p>The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129506.A_Treasury_of_Knitting_Patterns">A Treasury of Knitting Patterns</a>. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat. I adapted them for knitting in the round.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Rows 1-4</dt>
<dd><code>K</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 5</dt>
<dd><code>K1,P1</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 6</dt>
<dd><code>P1,K1</code> to end</dd>
</dl>
<p>I wasn’t done with new stuff, though. I decided it was time for my first pom pom. Wandered off to YouTube to see the process in action.</p>
<p>I needed to see someone making a pom pom.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8ilFeg7dPIU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Finally, I realized I also needed to see someone attach a pom pom to a hat. The hat in the video is crochet, but the principle is the same.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aiRQb5JkjzE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>After all that, the hat came out quite nice. It fit my head comfortably. The pom pom stays securely attached. The Roman Stitch feels nice when I rub my hands on the hat.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/modeling.jpg" alt="A much better fit"/></p>
<p>So naturally I’m taking the hat down to the post office tomorrow to ship off for a friend. Their head has the same circumference as mine. At this point, I worry less about the fate of my projects. I can make more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Hemmed Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</guid>
  <description>Ann Budd’s book The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her “Basic hat” template. The black wool hat I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.
What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a ribbed edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I made another hat! This time I learned how to make a hemmed edge.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg"/></p>
<p>Ann Budd’s book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a> continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her &ldquo;Basic hat&rdquo; template. The black <a href="/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/">wool hat</a> I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.</p>
<p>What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a <a href="https://www.dummies.com/crafts/knitting/knitting-stitches/how-to-rib-stitch/">ribbed</a> edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</p>
<p>This hat uses a <a href="http://www.vogueknitting.com/pattern_help/how-to/beyond_the_basics/hems">hemmed</a> edge. Stockinette rows get folded over and stitched into the body of the hat. I like the smooth look a hemmed edge produces. The extra volume of the hem provides the snugness needed to keep your hat on your head.</p>
<p>Oh! This was also the first time I used my copy of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13167139-the-handknitter-s-yarn-guide">The Handknitter’s Yarn Guide</a>! See, I had this mystery yarn in my stash. It was thick and self-striping, but that’s all I knew. No idea about the material, or what size needles I should be using. And let’s be honest, &ldquo;thick yarn&rdquo; is more than a little subjective. Some people <a href="https://youtu.be/FKw-pjwaXz8">knit with rope</a>, after all.</p>
<p>The Yarn Guide provides a reference of yarn textures and varieties, focused on details that are important for hand knitters. Machine knitters track somewhat different details. It includes nifty details like how a particular yarn material feels, or how it should burn — wool burns slow, acrylic goes up quick. It also describes <a href="https://www.craftyarncouncil.com/standards/how-measure-wraps-inch-wpi">wraps per inch</a> for establishing the weight of your yarn. &ldquo;Weight&rdquo; here is not about mass and gravity, but about expected gauge and needle size.</p>
<p>My 200 gram chunk of mystery self-striping yarn yielded eight and a half wraps per inch. A snip burned <em>quick</em>. This suggested I had a bulky acrylic, and should use size 13-15 (9-10mm) knitting needles.</p>
<p>Except I misread those numbers — three cheers for minor cognitive issues! — and ended up using size 9 (5.5mm) needles. Combine that with the fact that my flat knitting — such as what I used for the gauge swatch — produces a wildly different gauge from my knitting in the round, and. Well.</p>
<p>I made a <em>lovely</em> hat. A hat that was maybe a little too snug for a comfortable fit on my head.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/wearing-hat.jpg" title="The hat looks nice, but after a minute starts pinching my forehead" alt="me wearing the hat"/></p>
<p>That’s okay though. The hat fits a friend perfectly, and it’s heading home with them as I type.</p>
<p>For future projects, I will make my flat stockinette stitch match my round knitting gauge more closely. The main difference is in my purl stitch, which is looser than my knit stitch unless I pay close attention. When you knit in the round, purl stitches occur less often than when flat. That’s why those projects have a tighter gauge and tighter fit.</p>
<p>So far the hat I am knitting now has only a somewhat tighter gauge than the flat swatch. I <em>could</em> — maybe &ldquo;should?&rdquo; — also knit my gauge swatch in the round, but I’m not entirely confident that a gauge tube is what I need. We’ll see. But so far the current hat is the size I expected. That’s good enough for me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
