<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>os-xonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/os-x/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinos-x on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/os-x/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Taking OS X Screenshots</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/05/taking-os-x-screenshots/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/05/taking-os-x-screenshots/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Notes on saving screenshots in OS X, so I don’t have to look it up again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>os-x</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Notes on saving screenshots in OS X, so I don’t have to look it up again.</p>
<p>This started as a search to find how I can set the OS screenshot save location. <a href="http://osxdaily.com/">OS X Daily</a> provided that information and much more. I suggest you check it out for your OS X tips.</p>
<h2 id="the-shortcuts-i-use">The Shortcuts I Use</h2>
<p>My fingers pretty much have these memorized, but it would be nice if my brain knew them too.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Keys</th>
<th>Action</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>⌘ + ⇧ + 3</code></td>
<td>Save full screen to file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>⌘ + ⇧ + 4</code> + select area</td>
<td>Save selected area to file</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>⌘ + ⇧ + 4</code> + spacebar + click</td>
<td>Save selected window to file</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>There are <a href="http://osxdaily.com/2010/06/09/screen-capture-in-mac-os-x/">several more</a> that I do not use. I&rsquo;m already trying to learn Emacs shortcuts. I don&rsquo;t feel like cluttering my brain with additional OS X shortcuts I won&rsquo;t use.</p>
<h2 id="setting-the-save-location">Setting The Save Location</h2>
<p>OS X saves these files to <code>~/Desktop</code> by default, which results in much visual clutter on my screen desktop. Eventually I tired of the periodic cleanups and learned how to save in a different folder.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ mkdir ~/Pictures/Screenshots
$ defaults write com.apple.screencapture location ~/Pictures/Screenshots/</code></pre>
</figure><p>OS X Daily <a href="http://osxdaily.com/2011/01/26/change-the-screenshot-save-file-location-in-mac-os-x/">suggested</a> changing the setting and running <code>killall SystemUIServer</code>. Somewhere in the years since that post was published, restarting SystemUIServer became unnecessary.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: OS X Updates</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2007/12/os-x-updates/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2007 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2007/12/os-x-updates/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Had to reinstall OS X late last night because something left our trusty iMac in an unbootable state and a simple Repair from the install disc wouldn’t do the trick. This happened after running a system update, but I’m not sure I can blame Apple for this one. I also happened to interrupt a syncing iPod during that session. It’s possible that either of those things could have whacked the filesystem tree. Of course, I would expect the iPod sync to whack the iPod. Still, I’m not exactly an expert on these matters.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>os-x</category>  <category>macos</category>  <category>blogspot</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Had to reinstall OS X late last night because something left our trusty iMac in an unbootable state and a simple Repair from the install disc wouldn&rsquo;t do the trick. This happened after running a system update, but I&rsquo;m not sure I can blame Apple for this one. I also happened to interrupt a syncing iPod during that session. It&rsquo;s possible that either of those things could have whacked the filesystem tree. Of course, I would expect the iPod sync to whack the iPod. Still, I&rsquo;m not exactly an expert on these matters.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s not important, though. The file tree was only lightly whacked, and I was able to copy all of our important files to an external hard drive using the Terminal utility from the install disc. That process took a very long time. My guess is around 4 or 5 hours. The OS install was much quicker.</p>
<p>So now our iMac is nice and happy, and I can take the opportunity to review which apps I really want installed. I started with beta 2 of Firefox  3, which is <span style="font-style: italic;">significantly</span> snappier than 2.0 was. It&rsquo;s actually a useful browser again! Then it&rsquo;s time for fresh Python and Perl installs. I went the lazy way and grabbed ActiveState versions. Hey, ActivePerl 5.10 final is already out! That was uncharacteristically fast. I wonder if the other kids in the playground were making fun of them for being slow or something.</p>
<p>I also grabbed the freshest copy I could find of REBOL/Core and REBOL/View. View is much more polished than the last time I looked at it under OS X. See, I don&rsquo;t stay caught up on my OS X software much, since most of my time on the Mac is connecting over an ssh session. Little crises like this end up being a great chance for housecleaning.</p>
<p>Still some more stuff I want to do - fresh screen, vim, and Ruby for example. But we got the basics.</p>
<p>And all this was done with a nasty cold.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: I&#39;m too cheap to buy a radio alarm</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2007/06/im-too-cheap-to-buy-a-radio-alarm/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2007 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2007/06/im-too-cheap-to-buy-a-radio-alarm/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I have trouble waking up on time. That’s probably because I have trouble getting to bed on time. You can tell I have trouble getting to bed on time, because it’s 1:40 in the morning right now and I’m writing a little blog post instead of going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>applescript</category>  <category>os-x</category>  <category>unix</category>  <category>blogspot</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I have trouble waking up on time. That&rsquo;s probably because I have trouble getting to bed on time. You can tell I have trouble getting to bed on time, because it&rsquo;s 1:40 in the morning right now and I&rsquo;m writing a little blog post instead of going to bed.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m working on getting to sleep earlier. Hey, I might even be to bed by 2, instead of 3 or 3:30. Waking up takes a few tricks. Say, for example: an alarm clock that&rsquo;s too big for me to pick it up and stuff under my pillow like a gift for the tooth fairy. A loud annoying beeping gift. How about getting a bigger alarm and putting across the room? Well you would expect that to work, but apparently I can get up, walk over to the alarm, hit the snooze, pick up the alarm, bring it back to bed, and stuff the alarm under the bed for the tooth fairy again, all without actually waking up.</p>
<p>Yes, one issue is that the alarm clocks are battery powered. We live in a small, old apartment, and there just aren&rsquo;t enough outlets to go around. I had to unplug the lamp so that I could plug the computer in and type this.</p>
<p>But I have found a solution, or at least something which is not so easily circumvented. I&rsquo;ve turned our beautiful iMac G4 into a glorified radio alarm. Turns out that it was actually quite simple. First I needed an application that plays music. Right, that would be iTunes. Next, I need a radio station that both of us like. Why not just use a playlist? I don&rsquo;t know, I guess I actually wanted this to be a <span style="font-style: italic;">radio</span> alarm. I&rsquo;m odd. I do crazy things. I stash timepieces under my pillow, and blog in the middle of the night. Really, a radio station feed is not the strangest idea I&rsquo;ve had.</p>
<p>Should I use our local <a href="http://npr.org/">NPR</a>affiliate? No, I don&rsquo;t think so. Light jazz mixed with news and traffic reports are <em>not</em> going to make us jump out of bed all energized. I decided to use my favorite college station, <a href="/card/kexp/">card/KEXP</a>. The morning DJ is good, and
the morning selection is fantastic unless it&rsquo;s Winter and his <a href="http://www.sada.org.uk/">SAD</a>has kicked in.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve got my app, I&rsquo;ve got my radio station feed. Now a little AppleScript to automate the process of firing up and playing the station. I haven&rsquo;t experimented much with AppleScript, but there&rsquo;s no time like the present for putting a simple script together:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-applescript" data-lang="applescript"><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="c">-- PlayKEXP.applescript</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="c">--  Play the KEXP live stream</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">tell</span> <span class="nb">application</span> <span class="s2">&#34;iTunes&#34;</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">  <span class="k">set</span> <span class="na">sound</span> <span class="na">volume</span> <span class="k">to</span> <span class="mi">60</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">  <span class="nb">play</span> <span class="nv">user</span> <span class="nv">playlist</span> <span class="s2">&#34;KEXP Live&#34;</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">end</span> <span class="k">tell</span></span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>I test it with <code>osascript PlayKEXP.applescript</code>. It works like a charm.</p>
<p>Now to set this alarm so it goes off at a set time every day. This is the part where I really love the UNIXy goodness of OS X. I can just use crontab. So here&rsquo;s my new crontab file:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      ># minute/hour/mday/month/wday/command
30  6   *   *   *   osascript /Users/brian/iTunesScripts/PlayKEXP.applescript</code></pre>
</figure><p>Then I make sure that crontab knows about the task:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ crontab mycrontab</code></pre>
</figure><p>This was my first time using crontab for a personal task as well. It&rsquo;s awesome. Every morning at 6:30 iTunes will set the volume and start playing the KEXP broadcast.</p>
<p>So there you have it. It&rsquo;s simple and it works. I&rsquo;m going to bed now.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
