<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>statamiconRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/statamic/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinstatamic on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/statamic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: So here&#39;s my first Statamic tip: don&#39;t forget xml_handler in your RSS template</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/05/statamic-xml-handler-rss/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/05/statamic-xml-handler-rss/</guid>
  <description>@brianwisti what&#39;s the proper way to subscribe to https://t.co/6QUV8FCUgL now? Not finding an RSS.
— Captain Macho Pirate Mick Rackam (@tw2113) May 8, 2021 Yeah, the link was at /index.xml, but card/Statamic wasn’t outputting valid XML until I replaced my raw &lt;?xml with the xml_handler tag:
{{ xml_handler }} Should be all better now. Or at least better than it was.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>statamic</category>  <category>i-fixed-it</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://twitter.com/brianwisti?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@brianwisti</a> what&#39;s the proper way to subscribe to <a href="https://t.co/6QUV8FCUgL">https://t.co/6QUV8FCUgL</a> now? Not finding an RSS.</p>&mdash; Captain Macho Pirate Mick Rackam (@tw2113) <a href="https://twitter.com/tw2113/status/1390887717261561857?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">May 8, 2021</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Yeah, the link was at <code>/index.xml</code>, but <a href="/card/statamic/">card/Statamic</a> wasn&rsquo;t outputting valid XML until I replaced my raw <code>&lt;?xml</code> with the <code>xml_handler</code> tag:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >{{ xml_handler }}</code></pre>
</figure><p>Should be all better now. Or at least better than it was.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Officially Using Statamic For The Site</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/05/officially-using-statamic-for-the-site/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/05/officially-using-statamic-for-the-site/</guid>
  <description>Hey look it’s a Web page, but with Statamic!
Got the Webmention pingbacks up. Got the Plausible token in place. Got server configuration and deployment working.
Got — server configuration? Well yeah. The card/Statamic CMS runs on card/PHP. I could generate and push a static site with it, but I want to try some card/Laravel stuff. Been watching Laracasts even.
What’s different? The visual style, obviously. But I cycle through those routinely.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>statamic</category>  <category>cause-it-s-there</category>  <category>my-brand</category>  <category>oooh-a-sparkly</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Hugo's fine but I needed to try something new</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-05-07.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-05-07.png"/></figure>
Hey look it&rsquo;s a Web page, but with Statamic!</p>
<p>Got the <a href="https://webmention.io">Webmention</a> pingbacks up.  Got the <a href="https://plausible.io">Plausible</a> token in place.  Got server configuration and deployment working.</p>
<p>Got — server configuration?  Well yeah.  The <a href="/card/statamic/">card/Statamic</a> CMS runs on <a href="/card/php/">card/PHP</a>.  I <em>could</em> generate and push a static site with it, but I want to try some <a href="/card/laravel/">card/Laravel</a> stuff.  Been watching <a href="https://laracasts.com/">Laracasts</a> even.</p>
<h2 id="whats-different">What’s different?</h2>
<p>The visual style, obviously.  But I cycle through those routinely.  This one’s <a href="https://www.getpapercss.com/">PaperCSS</a> with a few tweaks.</p>
<p>I added a new section for my art — specifically for the art you can buy somewhere.  That’s been on my task list for a long time.  Feels nice to get it out of the way.  I have a sizable backlog of stuff I wanted to put on my <a href="https://www.designbyhumans.com/shop/randomgeek/">store</a>.  That art section will remind me to get through that backlog a bit more quickly.</p>
<p>You can search! Just by title or tag for now, but I’ll add more as I figure out how to fine tune it. And because you can search, I’m not <em>as</em> worried about how pagination is handled. I’m sure I’ll add something later.</p>
<p>And also because you can search, I haven’t gotten to the page aliases yet. Lots of broken inbound links, I expect. If this were some kind of professional site, I would’ve waited until I had those in place. But it’s not. So I don’t.</p>
<h2 id="anything-else">Anything else?</h2>
<p>From your perspective, that’s about it.  It’s pretty much the same site.</p>
<p>From my perspective, so much!  I get an awesome control panel to manage and edit content.  All my pages are still in flat text files, so I can edit them in my favorite text editor with no fuss.</p>
<p>Okay that’s not new for the site.  It’s new compared to when I tried this with WordPress though.</p>
<h2 id="whats-different-from-stock-statamic-solo">What’s different from stock Statamic Solo?</h2>
<p>The styling is set up with <a href="https://sass-lang.com/">SASS</a> instead of the starter’s default of <a href="https://tailwindcss.com/">Tailwind</a>.  Probably shift back once I figure out an approach to content styling that I prefer to Tailwind Prose.</p>
<p>I don’t entirely trust server-side for a blog.  Nothing to do with Statamic or PHP mind you.  It’s just too easy to miss important details when you’re running a solo project.</p>
<p>With that in mind, I added <a href="https://statamic.com/addons/jrc9designstudio/2fa">2FA</a> for two factor authentication and <a href="https://statamic.com/addons/simonhamp/gitamic">Gitamic</a> for Git integration.  Both are paid add-ons.  Much as I love open source software, I love knowing that good developers get a good dinner even more.  Sponsorship and patronage only go so far — on my monthly budget, at least.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>
<p>There’s still some basic deployment stuff to figure out.  Metadata for sharing, or what the boring kids call &ldquo;SEO.&rdquo; Ugh.  I ain’t optimizing <em>nothin’</em>, least of all some search engine’s job.</p>
<p>Anyways.  Then comes automating the non-RSS syndication: posting toots and tweets when I hit &ldquo;Publish.&rdquo; Until I get that code in it’s manual, so I’ll probably skip those for my notes.</p>
<p>After that?  Watch Laracasts.  Learn Laravel.  Learn Statamic.  Have fun.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: I&#39;ll deploy eventually.</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/i-ll-deploy-eventually/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/i-ll-deploy-eventually/</guid>
  <description>I mean sure. There’s my usual puttering with every little corner. But also I need to make sure everything is as close to seamless as possible for when I go live. And I’ve decided I will go live with this. card/Statamic is too much fun.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>statamic</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I mean sure. There&rsquo;s my usual puttering with every little corner. But also I need to make sure everything is as close to seamless as possible for when I go live. And I&rsquo;ve decided I <em>will</em> go live with this. <a href="/card/statamic/">card/Statamic</a> is too much fun.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: I&#39;m trying a &#34;notes&#34; collection</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/i-m-trying-a-notes-collection/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/i-m-trying-a-notes-collection/</guid>
  <description>Using card/Statamic for the site this split second. Titles are mandatory in Statamic, but I’ll figure something out. Could always treat “title” like a lead paragraph. That’s the direction I was headed in with the Hugo site.
Course, I already changed my blueprint layout from the screenshot.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>statamic</category>  <category>shouldn-t-you-be-working</category>  <category>it-s-sunday</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-04-18.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-04-18.png"/></figure></p>
<p>Using <a href="/card/statamic/">card/Statamic</a> for the site this split second. Titles are mandatory in Statamic, but I&rsquo;ll figure something out. Could always treat &ldquo;title&rdquo; like a lead paragraph. That&rsquo;s the direction I was headed in with the Hugo site.</p>
<p>Course, I already changed my blueprint layout from the screenshot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
