<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>personalonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/personal/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinpersonal on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 21:15:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Patronize Me on Liberapay</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/patronize-me-on-liberapay/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2020 21:15:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/04/patronize-me-on-liberapay/</guid>
  <description>Been skimming through ethical.net resources recently. Liberapay looks interesting: a patronage system like Patreon, but without reward tiers. More of a “keep doing — whatever the hell it is that you’re doing — it’s great” approach. So I joined of course. Give me money and I’ll keep doing exactly what I’ve been doing. Such a deal!</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>site</category>  <category>money</category>  <category>filthy-lucre</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-04-26.png" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-04-26.png"/></figure></p>
<p>Been skimming through <a href="https://ethical.net">ethical.net</a> resources recently. <a href="https://en.liberapay.com/">Liberapay</a> looks interesting: a patronage system like Patreon, but without reward tiers. More of a &ldquo;keep doing — whatever the hell it is that you’re doing — it’s great&rdquo; approach. So I <a href="https://en.liberapay.com/randomgeek/">joined</a> of course. Give me money and I’ll keep doing exactly what I’ve been doing. Such a deal!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Got Married Yesterday</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/got-married-yesterday/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:00:21 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/got-married-yesterday/</guid>
  <description>NOTE
I mentioned it on hackers.town / Twitter. Even updated my relationship status on Facebook. I’ll probably leave LinkedIn alone for the moment. But worth remembering here as well.
Seattle, 2020.
COVID-19 has shut down pretty much everything in the city and beyond. Large gatherings are forbidden, or at least strongly discouraged.
Thank goodness.
No not for the disease. Sheesh. For the new social rules. They gave us an acceptable excuse to keep our wedding a small affair.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>life</category>  <category>with-my-sweetheart</category>  <category>marginalia</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Can't let our dystopian sci-fi setting stop us</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-03-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-03-20.jpg"/></figure></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong></p>
<p>I mentioned it on <a href="https://hackers.town/@randomgeek/103853335008640787">hackers.town</a> / <a href="https://twitter.com/brianwisti/status/1240848019077111814">Twitter</a>. Even updated my relationship status on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/brianwisti/posts/10158601243074665">Facebook</a>. I’ll probably leave LinkedIn alone for the moment. But worth remembering here as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://crosscut.com/2020/03/coronavirus-turns-seattle-americas-laboratory">Seattle</a>, 2020.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2020/03/biography-new-coronavirus/608338/">COVID-19</a> has shut down pretty much <a href="https://publichealthinsider.com/2020/03/17/events-eating-out-and-retail-whats-allowed-and-whats-not/">everything</a> in the city and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/coronavirus-comes-spring-break-locals-close-florida-beaches-after-governor-n1163741">beyond</a>. Large gatherings are forbidden, or at least strongly discouraged.</p>
<p>Thank goodness.</p>
<p>No not for the disease. Sheesh. For the new social rules. They gave us an  acceptable excuse to keep our wedding a small affair.</p>
<p>A <em>very</em> small affair. Five of us and four — her <a href="https://twitter.com/qlitterbang">eldest daughter</a>, <a href="https://www.shellybedsaul.com">my mom</a> (subliminal message: BUY THEIR ART) plus a couple friends who couldn’t be there because quarantine — watching on Facebook group video chat. Might have added more, but the technical issues were complicated enough as it was.</p>
<p>One of our friends got ordained so she could officiate. We wouldn’t have to worry about the courthouses closing! The same friend was sort of an anti-chaperone at an early event. She made sure we were dancing close enough and that our hands were outside the Respectful First Dance Zone.</p>
<p>And yesterday she made sure we would be able to get married. It’s the circle of life. Or something. It’s very sweet is what it is.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2020/thumbs-up.jpg" title="You want a serious event, talk to someone else" alt="Newlyweds and friend grinning with thumbs up"/><figcaption>You want a serious event, talk to someone else</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>So yeah I’m happy. And the honeymoon will be nice — whenever the world opens back up again so we can have one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: that thing</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/01/that-thing/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2020 10:44:15 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/01/that-thing/</guid>
  <description>That thing where you’re doing a thing but need to look up something and get an idea and start a thing but need a thing and you notice a thing and get an idea and start a thing and you notice a thing…
Is that an card/ADHD thing? That sounds like an ADHD thing.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>time-is-an-illusion</category>  <category>so-many-browser-tabs</category>  <category>yeah-i-know</category>  <category>oh-no-the-dishes</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>That thing where you’re doing a thing but need to look up something and get an idea and start a thing but need a thing and you notice a thing and get an idea and start a thing and you notice a thing…</p>
<p>Is that an <a href="/card/adhd/">card/ADHD</a> thing? That sounds like an ADHD thing.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Hopepunk for 2019</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Lots of copying and pasting in this, since getting the words in full is important to me.</p>
<p>Tonight on Facebook, a friend shared a <a href="http://heartlessharless.tumblr.com/post/133490414240/alycs-being-unconditionally-polite-kind-and">Tumblr post</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Being unconditionally polite, kind, and compassionate in a society that values and finds “deeper meaning” in aloofness and cynicism is subversive and thus punk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>hufflepunk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has been my own general philosophy. Best to make it explicit. Values fade if kept in the shadows.</p>
<p>Anyways, &ldquo;hufflepunk&rdquo; sounds an awful lot like <a href="https://ariaste.tumblr.com/post/163500138919/ariaste-the-opposite-of-grimdark-is-hopepunk">hopepunk</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The opposite of grimdark is hopepunk. Pass it on.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>#this is a good post #also I need an example of hopepunk #bc the name #resonates with me #and I need it
#please #if you don’t mind (via @-lavender-starling)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So the essence of grimdark is that everyone’s inherently sort of a bad person and does bad things, and that’s awful and disheartening and cynical. It’s looking at human nature and going, “The glass is half empty.”</p>
<p>Hopepunk says, “No, I don’t accept that. Go fuck yourself: The glass is half-full.”  YEAH, we’re all a messy mix of good and bad, flaws and virtues. We’ve all been mean and petty and cruel, but (and here’s the important part) we’ve also been soft and forgiving and KIND. Hopepunk says that kindness and softness doesn’t equal weakness, and that in this world of brutal cynicism and nihilism, being kind is a <em>political act</em>. An act of <em>rebellion.</em></p>
<p>Hopepunk says that <em>genuinely and sincerely</em> caring about something, anything, requires bravery and strength. Hopepunk isn’t ever about submission or acceptance: It’s about standing up and fighting for what you believe in. It’s about standing up for other people. It’s about DEMANDING a better, kinder world, and truly believing that we can get there if we care about each other as hard as we possibly can, with every drop of power in our little hearts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There&rsquo;s more, but I don&rsquo;t need to paste the <em>entire</em> post.</p>
<p>Looking up Hopepunk led me to <a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/12/27/18137571/what-is-hopepunk-noblebright-grimdark">this Vox article</a>, which does a fine job breaking it down so I don&rsquo;t have to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Through this framing, the idea of choosing hope becomes both an existential act that affirms your humanity, and a form of resistance against cynical worldviews that dismiss hope as a powerful force for change.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see, what other examples can I think of? Oh, I know: <a href="http://www.pbs.org/parents/rogers">Mister Rogers</a>. You could throw a dart at a wall of Fred Rogers quotes and anything it hit would be appropriate for hopepunk. The man fully understood the world he was speaking to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some days, doing &ldquo;the best we can&rdquo; may still fall short of what we would like to be able to do, but life isn&rsquo;t perfect on any front — and doing what we can with what we have is the most we should expect of ourselves or
anyone else. — <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/895495">Fred Rogers</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The thing about all of these is that you don&rsquo;t expect the world to magically become a better place through your efforts. You do them because that&rsquo;s how things should be, and if we see someone stubbornly refusing to submit to cynicism, it might give us a little strength for our own efforts. If nothing else, we can sleep a little more easily with ourselves at night.</p>
<p>So I intend to be more explicitly this in 2019.</p>
<p>And — you know. If you don&rsquo;t like it, fuck off. I love you anyways.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: On Modesty And Imposter Syndrome</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</guid>
  <description>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It’s a rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It’s something I’ll need to read again.
It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I’m glad.
Don’t get in your own way Imposter Syndrome is a thing, yes.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It&rsquo;s a  rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ll need to read again.</p>
<p>It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I&rsquo;m glad.</p>
<h2 id="dont-get-in-your-own-way">Don&rsquo;t get in your own way</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.quickanddirtytips.com/health-fitness/medical-conditions/what-is-impostor-syndrome">Imposter Syndrome</a> is a thing, yes.</p>
<p>Anyone who pays attention and is honest with themselves knows there are things they do not know, and that other people know some of those things.</p>
<p>Some folks who see how much they don&rsquo;t know assume it means they know nothing of value. Massive oversimplification, but work with me here.</p>
<p>This assumes you value knowledge or competence, of course. If you don&rsquo;t, then we won&rsquo;t have much to talk about.</p>
<p>Modesty is good, in moderation. Pretending you know more than you do is at best tasteless, and can be dangerous.</p>
<p>But don&rsquo;t get in your own way.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been programming professionally for twenty years. I&rsquo;ve been knitting for well over ten years. I&rsquo;ve been sketching close to thirty years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m better than most folks at each of these. Granted, I&rsquo;m better partly because most folks don&rsquo;t do any of those things. BUT STILL.</p>
<p>I put in time. I learned things. I know things other practitioners know, and things not every practitioner knows.</p>
<p>I learn new things all the time. I just learned how to look up the spelling of a word with <a href="http://aspell.net/">GNU aspell</a>:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ <span class="nb">echo</span> practicioner <span class="p">|</span> aspell -a
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">@<span class="o">(</span><span class="c1">#) International Ispell Version 3.1.20 (but really Aspell 0.60.7-20110707)</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="p">&amp;</span> practicioner <span class="m">6</span> 0: practitioner, practicing, practice, practiced, practices, practice<span class="err">&#39;</span>s</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>In every one of those domains I&rsquo;m <strong>convinced</strong> I&rsquo;m a raw beginner.</p>
<p>Because there are plenty of things I don&rsquo;t know, and because sometimes I get brain lock.</p>
<h2 id="brain-lock">Brain lock</h2>
<p>I usually only get brain lock when knowing the thing is important to me.</p>
<p>I <em>should</em> know the thing. I should know <em>something</em>. I knew lots of things a second ago. But suddenly I don&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know the answer. I don&rsquo;t know the question. I don&rsquo;t know how to brain. All I know is to be furious at myself.</p>
<p>Is the brain lock just me getting into emotional overload because I didn&rsquo;t <em>immediately</em> have an acceptable answer?</p>
<p>Is that one of those &ldquo;gifted child grows up&rdquo; kind of problems? Yeesh what a depressing thought.</p>
<p>Whatever it is, that brain lock gets in the way.</p>
<p>It gets in the way at work. It gets in the way in relationships. Oh goodness does it get in the way in relationships.</p>
<p>So I think I&rsquo;m a beginner because I&rsquo;m still mad at myself for not knowing everything immediately? Maybe.</p>
<p>Regardless of why I feel this way, I need to get over it.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<h2 id="stack-building">Stack building</h2>
<p>Started focusing on the crisis moments there, when the original thought was about modesty and Imposter Syndrome.</p>
<p>But that&rsquo;s part of the point, isn&rsquo;t it? Taking a specific moment, generalizing it, and then judging yourself based on the generalization?</p>
<p>And then deciding what you are and are not capable of based on that judgment?</p>
<p>And then not doing the thing because you already decided you wouldn&rsquo;t be good at it?</p>
<p>Hey look at me I built a stack of cognitive distortions!</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s pop the stack. How would I look at these if it was someone else?</p>
<p>Avoiding action out of fear is its own entire stack of issues. Let&rsquo;s just set that one to the side for today.</p>
<p>A person&rsquo;s capabilities change. They may do better or even worse than you expected, but there is always the possibility of improvement.</p>
<p>Judging someone based on a general pattern of behavior is generally good but limited. They could surprise you given a new context.</p>
<p>Taking a particular moment and imagining this is how the person will behave in every moment is almost always a bad idea.</p>
<p>Some folks I feel perfectly content building a stack like this, but not many.</p>
<p>Certainly nobody I ever felt close to. I know I&rsquo;ve been fortunate in that regard.</p>
<p>I feel pretty close to myself.</p>
<h2 id="a-better-stack">A better stack</h2>
<p>So. Yeah. Sometimes I get brain lock. That sucks, and it&rsquo;s a thing I can work on.</p>
<p>Most of the time my brain is pretty good.</p>
<p>I know things, and I know how to learn more things.</p>
<p>If anything, my general pattern is wanting to learn more and do better.</p>
<p>You can always do better, but usually you&rsquo;re further along than the last time you tried this.</p>
<p>If it doesn&rsquo;t feel that way, you&rsquo;re in the frustrating part of getting better. But you&rsquo;re still getting better.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pattern I&rsquo;ve applied successfully throughout my life. Programming, knitting, sketching, juggling, being a decent human being.</p>
<p>Heck yeah being a decent human being takes wanting to learn more and do better. I&rsquo;m working on it <em>right now</em>.</p>
<p>There we go. I built a better cognitive stack. I&rsquo;ll keep revisiting it of course.</p>
<p>Getting rid of the old one takes more than just seeing it.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been with me my whole life, so tearing it down will be the work of a lifetime.</p>
<p>But look at how much I&rsquo;ve done even with that stack in place!</p>
<p>I can still be realistically modest. I can also take pride in what I <em>have</em> accomplished, and what I&rsquo;m continuing to accomplish.</p>
<p>Not entirely sure it&rsquo;s still about modesty or Imposter Syndrome, but I&rsquo;ll leave the title. And I&rsquo;ll fight the urge to just stash this file away somewhere, because posting makes it more concrete. I have an easier time holding myself accountable with a post. After all, this isn&rsquo;t the first time I&rsquo;ve seen and worked on bits of my cognitive stack.</p>
<p>Now go knit or something.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<p>PS. Still not smoking. It&rsquo;ll be five months on Saturday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Two Weeks Without Cigarettes</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/06/two-weeks-without-cigarettes/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/06/two-weeks-without-cigarettes/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I stopped smoking cigarettes two weeks ago. For now I &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/vape&#34;&gt;vape&lt;/a&gt; instead. Time to put down some notes about what other habits I had to adjust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I stopped smoking cigarettes two weeks ago. For now I <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/vape">vape</a> instead. Time to put down some notes about what other habits I had to adjust.</p>
<h2 id="drink-plenty-of-water">Drink plenty of water</h2>
<p>This one&rsquo;s pretty much a <a href="https://spinfuel.com/vaping-dehydration/">universal caution</a> with the cigarette -&gt; vape transition. Propylene Glycol, a common ingredient in vape juice, is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hygroscopy">hygroscopic</a>. It holds onto water, keeping your body from absorbing as much.</p>
<p>For folks that aren&rsquo;t vaping, just about anything will avoid <a href="https://www.webmd.com/a-to-z-guides/dehydration-adults#1">dehydration</a>: coffee, tea, sugary drinks, maybe a little alcohol. A healthy body can compensate for their diuretic or hygroscopic properties in moderation. It has to be water for me thanks to Propylene Glycol. I can have the others if I want, but I better keep it light and should still keep plain old water handy.</p>
<h2 id="careful-with-the-caffeine">Careful with the caffeine</h2>
<p>While I&rsquo;m on the subject of drinking: I drink lots of coffee. I accompanied my first cup of the day with the heaviest smoking. All that caffeine affects me more now that I consume less nicotine.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/14186462_The_impact_of_caffeine_use_on_tobacco_cessation_and_withdrawal">The impact of caffeine use on tobacco cessation and withdrawal</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Continuous caffeine consumption with smoking cessation has been associated with more than doubled caffeine plasma levels. Such concentrations may be sufficient to produce caffeine toxicity symptoms in smoking abstinence conditions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A few cups of good coffee and I&rsquo;m just about grinding my teeth now. So maybe I&rsquo;ll cut down on the bean.</p>
<h2 id="careful-with-the-alcohol">Careful with the alcohol</h2>
<p>If you&rsquo;re vaping, maybe don&rsquo;t leave the vape pen at home in a fit of overconfidence when you go out for drinks. Turns out there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2013/02/130213100726.htm">correlation between drinking and smoking urges</a>. So you&rsquo;ll be sitting there staring out the window at all those happy drunks with a smoke in their hands, with you feeling and possibly behaving ever so unpleasantly.</p>
<p>I was, anyways.</p>
<p>My new rule is to never leave home without my pen, until I&rsquo;m ready to drop the vape habit as well.</p>
<p>Add the hydration issue from alcohol or sugary drinks or sugary alcohol drinks? Yeesh. All the rules for healthy people about consuming in moderation apply even more strictly right now.</p>
<h2 id="careful-with-the-social-media">Careful with the social media</h2>
<p>My smoke break routine involved checking Twitter, Facebook, etc for the day&rsquo;s good memes and bad news. Initially I carried this habit over to vaping to maintain my rituals. It occurs to me that withdrawal, chemical interactions, and breaking old habits has me anxious enough. Maybe it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> important to find out what horrible things happened to the world in the last hour or so.</p>
<p>For now I&rsquo;m keeping with a ritual of reading, but starting today I choose books instead. I like it so far. <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17204679-man-s-search-for-meaning">Man&rsquo;s Search for Meaning</a> isn&rsquo;t exactly light and perky, but it&rsquo;s more helpful than the news.</p>
<h2 id="careful-with-the-timeline-assumptions">Careful with the timeline assumptions</h2>
<p>Last night was pretty rough. All the anxiety and disorientation that happened in the first few days of previous attempts to quit smashed into me after a couple deceptively mild weeks. I still have a chunk of that anxiety and disorientation now, twelve hours later.</p>
<p>I dug around on the Web and found the occasional <a href="https://www.e-cigarette-forum.com/threads/tobacco-withdrawal-symptoms-when-using-e-cig.409890/page-2#post-9355216">forum post</a> suggesting that the surprise crash a few weeks in is pretty common, even for folks who switch from cigarette to ecig.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>About 3 weeks in these symptoms hit me pretty hard.It felt like I was in a haze and just couldnt concentrate. I&rsquo;m no doctor but my guess is it&rsquo;s the 3999 other chemicals in cigarettes leaving our bodies for good. In 25 years of smoking, I wouldnt be surprised if I had bult up quite an excess of them.</p>
<p>The good news it that it passed after a week or two and I feel better than ever at 6 months. I just finished my first ever  5k&hellip;ended up walking most of it&hellip;but 10 years I wouldnt have been able to finish so it&rsquo;s still a victory.</p>
<p>Hang in there man, youve made it this far and after this bump in the road it will get easier.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That&rsquo;s why I&rsquo;m writing this post: it&rsquo;s a collection of things I learned while trying to figure out what the heck happened last night. Recognizing the situational prompts helped. Nicotine interacts with the body and what you consume in ways I didn&rsquo;t think about, so breaking that habit can have unexpected challenges even if
you keep a <a href="https://vapingdaily.com/quitting-effects/nicotine-withdrawal-symptoms-timeline/">nicotine withdrawal infographic</a> in easy reach.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll take the words of Vaping Master zapped to heart and hang in there. A little better informed now, though.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Geekish Update</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/03/geekish-update/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/03/geekish-update/</guid>
  <description>I set up a space for myself in the basement. This is now where I keep my desktop — running Ubuntu at the moment. Easy enough to get at from the laptop upstairs. Maybe keep Irssi running in a Tmux session or something.
Oh, and just in case you want to know how the basement looked when we moved in, here’s a picture.
I like it better now.
What have I been coding in this workspace that looks a bit less like a horror movie scene than it did a few weeks ago?</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>site</category>  <category>marginalia</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-03-28.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2017/cover-2017-03-28.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>I set up a space for myself in the basement. This is now where I keep my desktop — running <a href="https://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</a> at the moment. Easy enough to get at from the laptop upstairs. Maybe keep <a href="https://irssi.org/">Irssi</a> running in a <a href="https://tmux.github.io/">Tmux</a> session or something.</p>
<p>Oh, and just in case you want to know how the basement looked when we moved in, here’s a picture.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2017/basement-original.jpg" alt="The original basement"/></figure></p>
<p>I like it better now.</p>
<p>What have I been coding in this workspace that looks a bit less like a horror movie scene than it did a few weeks ago?</p>
<p>I’m working on a <code>test</code> rule for this site. Mainly I use it to check for bad links in an attempt to deal with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_rot">link rot</a>. The link checker is <a href="https://www.python.org/">Python</a> with <a href="http://docs.python-requests.org/en/master/">Requests</a>, and seeing if <a href="https://scrapy.org/">Scrapy</a> can be useful in this context. Scrapy seems like overkill at first glance, but it has middleware for respecting <a href="http://www.robotstxt.org/"><code>robots.txt</code></a>. I care about being a good Internet citizen.</p>
<p>I plan to write about that soon, since I enjoy the task so far.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Maybe Ration My Time In Hot Take Land</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/03/maybe-ration-my-time-in-hot-take-land/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2017/03/maybe-ration-my-time-in-hot-take-land/</guid>
  <description>I dunno, folks. Over the years I have seen so much outrage – sincere or feigned – on social media. Then there’s the echo chamber problem. Yeah. Nice thing about an RSS feed is that I’m guaranteed to see everything I subscribe to, but there’s no personal insult in unsubscribing.
I think maybe I could spend less time on Twitter and Facebook. Not give them up. They remain a source of great conversation.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I dunno, folks. Over the years I have seen so much <a href="http://www.geekwire.com/2017/trump-supporters-voice-real-outrage-fake-resistanceradio-promoting-amazon-tv-series/">outrage</a> &ndash; sincere or feigned &ndash; on social media. Then there’s the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2017/03/the-social-media-echo-chamber-is-real/">echo chamber</a> problem. Yeah. Nice thing about an RSS feed is that I’m guaranteed to see everything I subscribe to, but there’s no personal insult in unsubscribing.</p>
<p>I think maybe I could spend less time on Twitter and Facebook. Not give them up. They remain a source of great conversation. But this nonsense takes up brain that I just can’t spare. Some of my online friends cut themselves out completely, and <a href="https://seeknuance.com/2017/03/07/im-happier-and-more-productive-without-twitter/">they like it</a>. Perhaps I should follow their example. Besides, each of them that moves on means one less bit of signal in the noise.</p>
<p>There is so much noise.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong></p>
<p>I noticed that the Disqus sections for all post content in 2017 are tied to <a href="/post/2017/01/cinnamon-screenshot-shortcuts/">my screenshot post</a>, which also happens to be the first post content of 2017. Made some adjustments and had Disqus recrawl the site.</p>
<p>Then I decided that maybe I can do without comments for a while.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Starting The Coursera Programming Languages Course</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2014/10/starting-the-coursera-programming-languages-course/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2014/10/starting-the-coursera-programming-languages-course/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I signed up for the Coursera &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/course/proglang&#34;&gt;Programming Languages&lt;/a&gt; course. I may even complete it. See, I signed up for a Scala course earlier this year, but did not get past the first video. That made me sad. Scala is one of those things that I would like to learn.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>A quick confession about learning how to learn</h2><p>I signed up for the Coursera <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/proglang">Programming Languages</a> course. I may even complete it. See, I signed up for a Scala course earlier this year, but did not get past the first video. That made me sad. Scala is one of those things that I would like to learn.</p>
<p><em>Many</em> topics appeal to me. This causes problems. I will never stop finding things that I want to learn: languages, idioms, platforms, databases, security, and so on. The list becomes almost frightening when you add non-computery things that I want to get better at: drawing, knitting, cooking, writing, etcetera.</p>
<p>I keep trying to learn new things. I know that I will never have enough time to learn most of it, but I keep trying.</p>
<p>Preparation makes more things possible. You are supposed to set time aside that is just for focused learning. The early morning and early evening work best for me, since there are fewer distractions.</p>
<p>Some of my preparation involves watching videos with the express purpose of learning. <a href="http://about.avdi.org/">Avdi Grimm</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.rubytapas.com/">Ruby Tapas</a> episodes help with that goal. They are short. They are educational. They are fun.</p>
<p>The Coursera videos have a greater length than Ruby Tapas, of course. At least my brain is warmed up for the task of focused learning. A few stretching exercises have been done.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m nervous. My habits are getting better, but my ratio of Things Started to Things Finished embarrasses me. I will not make &ldquo;Finish This Course&rdquo; a requirement. Too nervous. But I will have a certain amount of pride if I can make it through, do the assignments, and maybe even - <em>gasp</em> - turn them in.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s hoping.</p>
<p>related:: <a href="/card/tech-career-skill-development/">card/Tech Career Skill Development</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
