<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>and-other-delusionsonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/and-other-delusions/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinand-other-delusions on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/and-other-delusions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Maybe lock chat-gpt3 out of your blog</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/01/maybe-lock-chat-gpt3-out-of-your-blog/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/01/maybe-lock-chat-gpt3-out-of-your-blog/</guid>
  <description>Random post crossed into my field of view today.
When one day someone asks Chat-gpt3 - ‘how is chat-gpt3 like a Wasp Spider’, chat-gpt3 will quote my article (because who else would make such ridiculous analogies) without attribution.
But what it won’t do is offer the user a link to the source of the information and it will never result in a user visiting the OnePub blog.
— OnePub, The threat that chat-gpt3 poses to bloggers “I made this” is one of the oldest frustrations of the Internet, to the point of being immortalized in comic form at least once.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>the-internet</category>  <category>and-other-delusions</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Random post crossed into my field of view today.</p>
<figure class="border-primary border-left pl-9 container-9 centered">
  <blockquote
    cite="#ZgotmplZ">
<p>When one day someone asks Chat-gpt3 - &lsquo;how is chat-gpt3 like a Wasp Spider&rsquo;, chat-gpt3 will quote my article (because who else would make such ridiculous analogies) without attribution.</p>
<p>But what it won&rsquo;t do is offer the user a link to the source of the information and it will never result in a user visiting the OnePub blog.</p>
  </blockquote><figcaption class="align-right">
    &mdash;
    OnePub, <a href="#ZgotmplZ">The threat that chat-gpt3 poses to bloggers</a>
  </figcaption></figure>
<p>&ldquo;I made this&rdquo; is one of the oldest frustrations of the Internet, to the point of being immortalized in comic form at least <a href="https://nedroidcomics.tumblr.com/post/41879001445/the-internet">once</a>. Heck it&rsquo;s part of why I set my site content to a Creative Commons license. Why fight it? But yeah. Any possible external value has been extracted and claimed. Let&rsquo;s assume it&rsquo;s too late for my ancient blog.</p>
<p>Your newer site, with words and images you care deeply about? You may want to put some locks on those doors.</p>
<p>The only caveat about the advice from the article — aside from the fact that it&rsquo;s probably kinda satirical what with getting its answers <em>from</em> chat-GPT3:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>robots.txt</code> is usually ignored &mdash; but it&rsquo;s still a nice gesture to the few who acknowledge it</li>
<li>User-agent restrictions can be worked around with minimal effort &mdash; but will work against the large number of folks who can&rsquo;t be bothered with minimal effort</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Great workflow you got there</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/12/great-workflow-you-got-there/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 15:18:34 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/12/great-workflow-you-got-there/</guid>
  <description>Thirty seconds to add a bookmark link. Three hours to tweak a bunch of minor layout issues.
I’m like a machine. A machine held together by duct tape and glitter glue.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>efficiency</category>  <category>productivity</category>  <category>and-other-delusions</category>  <category>still-feels-good</category>  <category>site</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thirty seconds to add a bookmark link. Three hours to tweak a bunch of minor layout issues.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m like a machine. A machine held together by duct tape and glitter glue.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
