<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>podcastonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/podcast/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinpodcast on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 17:46:19 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/podcast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: I still love when people say nice things about Perl</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/08/i-still-love-when-people-say-nice-things-about-perl/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 17:46:19 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/08/i-still-love-when-people-say-nice-things-about-perl/</guid>
  <description>John Siracusa, on the Diving for Perl episode of the Command Line Heroes podcast:
My hope for Perl 5 is that people don’t dismiss it, because despite all the other more popular languages, there are still problems today to which Perl 5 is the best solution. Very often those are sort of glue type problems. If you find yourself ever writing a shell script, and you’re like, “Well, I’m not going to use my ‘real programming language’ for this.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>perl</category>  <category>podcast</category>  <category>glue-languages-stick-with-you</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://hypercritical.co/">John Siracusa</a>, on the <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/command-line-heroes/season-3/diving-for-perl">Diving for Perl</a> episode of the <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/command-line-heroes">Command Line Heroes</a> podcast:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My hope for Perl 5 is that people don&rsquo;t dismiss it, because despite all the other more popular languages, there are still problems today to which Perl 5 is the best solution. Very often those are sort of glue type problems. If you find yourself ever writing a shell script, and you&rsquo;re like, &ldquo;Well, I&rsquo;m not going to use my &lsquo;real programming language&rsquo; for this.&rdquo; Whether it&rsquo;s Python, or Ruby, or whatever. But a shell script can let me connect together a bunch of stuff. Perl is a better tool for that job. It is easier to write a correct Perl script than it is to write a correct shell script.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Having written a few glue tasks with <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/coreutils.html">GNU Coreutils</a> and some shell scripts, I agree with that point. Even just glueing together Coreutils can be easier with <a href="/card/perl/">card/Perl</a>.</p>
<p>And <a href="/card/raku/">card/Raku</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That&rsquo;s the great thing about open source, and programming languages. No one&rsquo;s going to make you stop. You can just keep working on Perl 6 the same way you have been.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I won&rsquo;t say whether I installed a fresh build of <a href="https://rakudo.org">Rakudo</a> and played around with Raku after listening to the podcast, but — I installed a fresh build of Rakudo and played around with Perl 6 after listening to this episode.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
