<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>community-supportonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/community-support/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentincommunity-support on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 12:41:46 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/community-support/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: [2022-07-17 Sun 12:41] Better than a gist</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/07/better-than-a-gist/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 12:41:46 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/07/better-than-a-gist/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t sure about the new 988 suicide prevention hotline, here are some other numbers you can call in the US, via Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>community-support</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you aren&rsquo;t sure about the new 988 suicide prevention hotline, here are some other numbers you can call in the US, via Twitter.</p>
<p>I wanted to share a tweet with alternate national hotlines, but there was no alt text for screenreaders — and the text from the image has a bit too much text for a tweet. So here&rsquo;s the list, reformatted and with links added by me.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://translifeline.org">Trans Lifeline</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="tel:8775658860">(877) 565-8860</a></li>
<li>24/7</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://thrivelifeline.org">THRIVE</a>
<ul>
<li>text message line at <a href="sms:3136628209&amp;body=THRIVE">(313) 662-8209</a></li>
<li>24/7</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://promiseresourcenetwork.org">Promise Resource Network</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="tel:8333907728">(833) 390-7728</a></li>
<li>24/7</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://prpsn.org/home-peer-support-network.html">Project Return Peer Support Network</a>
<ul>
<li>English &amp; Spanish Language: <a href="tel:8884489777">(888) 448-9777</a></li>
<li>hours are Monday through Friday 2:30 PM to 10:00 PM and Saturday and Sunday 10:00 AM to 6:00 PM</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://wildfloweralliance.org">Wildflower Alliance Peer Support Line</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="tel:8884074515">(888) 407-4515</a></li>
<li>hours are 7pm to 9pm Monday through Thursday and 7pm-10pm Friday</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The tweet I wanted to quote:</p>
<p>{{&lt; twitter user=&ldquo;jiminspinkypal&rdquo; id=&ldquo;1548717117683503106&rdquo; &gt;}}</p>
<p>The image accompanying the tweet lists alternative numbers to call, which I already listed above because that&rsquo;s the important bit.</p>
<p>According to the tweet, there are privacy violations along with risk of police involvement and involuntary hospitalization if you call 988. Later in the thread they added a link to <a href="https://www.madinamerica.com/2022/01/roll-988-threatens-anonymity-crisis-hotlines/">Roll-out of 988 Threatens Anonymity of Crisis Hotlines</a>. That article links out to additional resources, none of which I am informed enough to verify.</p>
<p>So I looked for the official responses in the <a href="https://www.samhsa.gov/find-help/988/faqs">SAMHSA 988 FAQ</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>If I contact the Lifeline for help, will I be hospitalized?</strong></p>
<p>All Lifeline crisis centers adhere to the Lifeline’s Imminent Risk Policy,
which means that crisis center staff work through active engagement to
provide support and assistance for people at risk in the least restrictive
setting possible. In fact, most contacts with the Lifeline are resolved by
the Lifeline itself, by chat or phone, in a manner that does not require
additional immediate intervention.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The attentive reader will note that this answer is not a &ldquo;no.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The other concern relates to privacy concerns for callers.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Will geolocation services be enacted?</strong></p>
<p>Currently, the Lifeline automatically routes calls by area code to the
nearest crisis center (unlike 911, which uses geolocation). As part of the
2020 Designation Act, the Federal Communications Commission submitted a
report examining the feasibility and cost of including an automatic
dispatchable location that would be conveyed with a 988 call. Within that
report, the FCC recommended that Congress require that a multi-stakeholder
group be convened to further examine the key issues and collaborate on
potential next steps. The FCC held a 988 Geolocation Forum in May 2022 and
the agency is actively analyzing the information gathered during that forum.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And this sounds a lot to me like &ldquo;not yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So yeah, keep the alternate numbers handy if you have reason to be concerned. If nothing else, folks staffing a specialized hotline may be more understanding of your context and better able to talk you through your specific crisis.</p>
<p>Oh, and friends: please put alt text on your tweet images.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
