<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>knittingonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/knitting/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinknitting on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/knitting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: A Knitted Washcloth</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/04/a-knitted-washcloth/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/04/a-knitted-washcloth/</guid>
  <description>it may not be much but I made it
A washcloth on its own is no big deal, but it’s been a while since I finished any knitting.
This particular washcloth pattern came printed inside the wrapper of some Lily Sugar’n Cream yarn, of the “Fruit Punch” color variety. Fairly straightforward pattern but even so I think I did more yarn-overs than on any project that comes to mind.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>it-s-been-84-years</category>  <category>okay-maybe-two</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2023/04/../../../attachments/img/2023/cover-2023-04-23.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2023/cover-2023-04-23.jpg"/>
it may not be much but I made it</p>
<p>A washcloth on its own is no big deal, but it&rsquo;s been a <em>while</em> since I finished any knitting.</p>
<p>This particular washcloth pattern came printed inside the wrapper of some Lily <a href="https://www.yarnspirations.com/lily-sugarn-cream-ombres-yarn/102002.html">Sugar&rsquo;n Cream</a> yarn, of the &ldquo;Fruit Punch&rdquo; color variety. Fairly straightforward pattern but even so I think I did more yarn-overs than on any project that comes to mind.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Deidre&#39;s Double Moss Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</guid>
  <description>blocked and ready to wear
Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!
The pattern Using Sensational Knitted Socks by Charlene Schurch, as usual. Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe moss stitch fallback.
The yarn brand Think Bamboo style B917 color 992 composition 45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon site https://thinkbamboo.com; doesn’t work for me at the moment The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I'm just glad I finished them</h2><p><img src="/post/2021/01/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg"/>
blocked and ready to wear</p>
<p>Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!</p>
<h2 id="the-pattern">The pattern</h2>
<p>Using <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/399836.Sensational_Knitted_Socks">Sensational Knitted Socks</a> by Charlene Schurch, as usual.
Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe <a href="https://www.gathered.how/knitting-and-crochet/knitting/moss-stitch/">moss
stitch</a> fallback.</p>
<h2 id="the-yarn">The yarn</h2>
<dl>
<dt>brand</dt>
<dd>Think Bamboo</dd>
<dt>style</dt>
<dd>B917</dd>
<dt>color</dt>
<dd>992</dd>
<dt>composition</dt>
<dd>45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon</dd>
<dt>site</dt>
<dd><a href="https://thinkbamboo.com">https://thinkbamboo.com</a>; doesn&rsquo;t work for me at the moment</dd>
</dl>
<p>The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.  It is beyond a hassle
to wind up, though.</p>
<h2 id="the-review">The review</h2>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Omg my beautiful handmade socks are so soft and a thing of BEAUTY <a href="https://t.co/cXmYHyI1CC">pic.twitter.com/cXmYHyI1CC</a></p>&mdash; Deidre Wisti (@IamMrsGeek) <a href="https://twitter.com/IamMrsGeek/status/1341594975629283328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Deidre&#39;s Juneuary Hat</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/06/deidres-juneuary-hat/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 15:02:53 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/06/deidres-juneuary-hat/</guid>
  <description>Finished knitting a nice winter hat for the Missus. Right in time for summer. But at least she got a couple days where it was cool enough to wear the hat without sweating to death.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2020/06/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-06-24.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-06-24.jpg"/></p>
<p>Finished knitting a nice winter hat for the Missus. Right in time for summer. But at least she got a couple days where it was cool enough to wear the hat without sweating to death.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Picot Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</guid>
  <description>This hat is another round of the “basic hat” from Ann Budd’s The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from last time.
The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from A Treasury of Knitting Patterns. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I continue building my hat knitting knowledge!</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg"/></p>
<p>This hat is another round of the &ldquo;basic hat&rdquo; from Ann Budd’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a>. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from <a href="/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/">last time</a>.</p>
<p>The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129506.A_Treasury_of_Knitting_Patterns">A Treasury of Knitting Patterns</a>. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat. I adapted them for knitting in the round.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Rows 1-4</dt>
<dd><code>K</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 5</dt>
<dd><code>K1,P1</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 6</dt>
<dd><code>P1,K1</code> to end</dd>
</dl>
<p>I wasn’t done with new stuff, though. I decided it was time for my first pom pom. Wandered off to YouTube to see the process in action.</p>
<p>I needed to see someone making a pom pom.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8ilFeg7dPIU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Finally, I realized I also needed to see someone attach a pom pom to a hat. The hat in the video is crochet, but the principle is the same.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aiRQb5JkjzE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>After all that, the hat came out quite nice. It fit my head comfortably. The pom pom stays securely attached. The Roman Stitch feels nice when I rub my hands on the hat.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/modeling.jpg" alt="A much better fit"/></p>
<p>So naturally I’m taking the hat down to the post office tomorrow to ship off for a friend. Their head has the same circumference as mine. At this point, I worry less about the fate of my projects. I can make more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Hemmed Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</guid>
  <description>Ann Budd’s book The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her “Basic hat” template. The black wool hat I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.
What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a ribbed edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I made another hat! This time I learned how to make a hemmed edge.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg"/></p>
<p>Ann Budd’s book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a> continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her &ldquo;Basic hat&rdquo; template. The black <a href="/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/">wool hat</a> I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.</p>
<p>What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a <a href="https://www.dummies.com/crafts/knitting/knitting-stitches/how-to-rib-stitch/">ribbed</a> edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</p>
<p>This hat uses a <a href="http://www.vogueknitting.com/pattern_help/how-to/beyond_the_basics/hems">hemmed</a> edge. Stockinette rows get folded over and stitched into the body of the hat. I like the smooth look a hemmed edge produces. The extra volume of the hem provides the snugness needed to keep your hat on your head.</p>
<p>Oh! This was also the first time I used my copy of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13167139-the-handknitter-s-yarn-guide">The Handknitter’s Yarn Guide</a>! See, I had this mystery yarn in my stash. It was thick and self-striping, but that’s all I knew. No idea about the material, or what size needles I should be using. And let’s be honest, &ldquo;thick yarn&rdquo; is more than a little subjective. Some people <a href="https://youtu.be/FKw-pjwaXz8">knit with rope</a>, after all.</p>
<p>The Yarn Guide provides a reference of yarn textures and varieties, focused on details that are important for hand knitters. Machine knitters track somewhat different details. It includes nifty details like how a particular yarn material feels, or how it should burn — wool burns slow, acrylic goes up quick. It also describes <a href="https://www.craftyarncouncil.com/standards/how-measure-wraps-inch-wpi">wraps per inch</a> for establishing the weight of your yarn. &ldquo;Weight&rdquo; here is not about mass and gravity, but about expected gauge and needle size.</p>
<p>My 200 gram chunk of mystery self-striping yarn yielded eight and a half wraps per inch. A snip burned <em>quick</em>. This suggested I had a bulky acrylic, and should use size 13-15 (9-10mm) knitting needles.</p>
<p>Except I misread those numbers — three cheers for minor cognitive issues! — and ended up using size 9 (5.5mm) needles. Combine that with the fact that my flat knitting — such as what I used for the gauge swatch — produces a wildly different gauge from my knitting in the round, and. Well.</p>
<p>I made a <em>lovely</em> hat. A hat that was maybe a little too snug for a comfortable fit on my head.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/wearing-hat.jpg" title="The hat looks nice, but after a minute starts pinching my forehead" alt="me wearing the hat"/></p>
<p>That’s okay though. The hat fits a friend perfectly, and it’s heading home with them as I type.</p>
<p>For future projects, I will make my flat stockinette stitch match my round knitting gauge more closely. The main difference is in my purl stitch, which is looser than my knit stitch unless I pay close attention. When you knit in the round, purl stitches occur less often than when flat. That’s why those projects have a tighter gauge and tighter fit.</p>
<p>So far the hat I am knitting now has only a somewhat tighter gauge than the flat swatch. I <em>could</em> — maybe &ldquo;should?&rdquo; — also knit my gauge swatch in the round, but I’m not entirely confident that a gauge tube is what I need. We’ll see. But so far the current hat is the size I expected. That’s good enough for me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Winter Hat and Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg"/></p>
<p>The gloves use the same <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch">Son of Stitch &rsquo;n Bitch</a> pattern as the <a href="/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/">purple beer gloves</a> I knitted this summer. This pair turned out much better. Learning through repetition! However, that Loops &amp; Threads &ldquo;Impeccable&rdquo; yarn is far too stiff for gloves. I would prefer a sportweight blend to this worsted weight acrylic for things that need to move with my hands.</p>
<p>I lost the label for the hat yarn but it&rsquo;s probably Patons North America Classic Wool Worsted. So soft and cozy on my head. I accidentally changed tension once I picked up speed, resulting in an interesting gauge effect along the bottom ribbing, but that is already becoming less pronounced with wear. You can also see twisted stiches where I recovered a row but mounted those stitches incorrectly. This happened plenty of times in the past, but I wanted to remember these little mistakes for future projects.</p>
<p>This isn&rsquo;t me being overly fussy. It&rsquo;s just me moving past the beginner mode of &ldquo;Yay I finished something!&rdquo; to hopefully more intermediate habits that ask &ldquo;how will I do better next time?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The hat pattern came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter&rsquo;s Handy Book of Patterns</a> by Ann Budd. As I get more comfortable with knitting, my interests move from specific patterns to templates and techniques. This book seems a good step in that direction so far. Quite a few tables and charts, which calls out to old memories of gaming books. The tables are just math helpers though. I can see not needing them after a certain point. That&rsquo;s the day I&rsquo;ll be able to knit custom fit stuff from memory. Something to look forward to!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Beer Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I knitted a pair of the fingerless Beer Gloves from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch&#34;&gt;Son of Stitch ’n Bitch&lt;/a&gt;. This involved a couple new techniques and several new mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I knitted a pair of the fingerless Beer Gloves from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch">Son of Stitch &rsquo;n Bitch</a>. This involved a couple new techniques and several new mistakes.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/08/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-04.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-04.jpg"/></p>
<p>These gloves have a nice cable along the back. A seed stitch patch near the palm supposedly helps with opening bottles. I have not tested them for opening bottles yet, but the texture feels nice and gives a bit more grip than the reverse stockinette alone.</p>
<p>The pattern called for double-pointed needles. I tried something new instead, and knit this using the <a href="https://www.craftsy.com/knitting/article/demystifying-the-magic-loop/">magic loop</a> method with a single circular needle. It worked well until the thumbs and fingers. It&rsquo;s kind of easy to get yourself going in the wrong direction if you aren&rsquo;t careful. I accidentally knit one thumb pointing almost straight out, instead of the slight angle of its mate.</p>
<p>Since my purl gauge tends to be loose, the reverse stockinette that dominates this pattern produced a bulkier glove than I would have liked. If I make these again with the same <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/yarns/library/loops--threads-impeccable-solids">Impeccable Solids</a> yarn, I should use slightly smaller needle than the pattern calls for. And I probably won&rsquo;t use magic loop, either.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://knitfreedom.com/invisible-ribbed-bind-off/">invisible ribbed bind off</a> took me a few tries to get right. Fortunately, I had ten opportunities to learn. Even more fortunately, the recipient of these gloves finds the loose yarn loops of failure to be charming.</p>
<p>Enough nitpicking! These are good gloves. They keep their wearer warm while keeping fingers free for fine motor skills. The cable is gorgeous. These are destined for a friend, who already loves them and will wear them enthusiastically once the weather gets cold enough.</p>
<h2 id="what-next">What next?</h2>
<p>I enjoyed making these, but I want to learn more about glove construction in general instead of haphazardly implementing cool-looking patterns. I have several simple mitten and glove ideas planned!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: My First F Bomb</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/my-first-f-bomb/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/my-first-f-bomb/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Took a break this weekend &lt;em&gt;inbox/Knitting&lt;/em&gt; a quick yarn project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>crochet</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Took a break this weekend <em>inbox/Knitting</em> a quick yarn project.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/07/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-01.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-01.jpg"/></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/the-f-bomb">original pattern</a> uses <a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Knit-the-Duplicate-Stitch">duplicate stitch knitting</a> for the letter, but after a couple frustrated hours I gave up on that and crocheted the letter on. I expect to make more of these. The lettering should improve.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Stocking Cap</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/04/stocking-cap/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/04/stocking-cap/</guid>
  <description>
To get a comfortable fit, I cast on 84 instead of the original pattern’s 78. To produce a slightly shorter hat, I decreased every 15 stitches instead of every 20. </description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I knitted myself a slightly silly stocking cap which I quite enjoy.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/04/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-04-27.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-04-27.jpg"/></p>
<ul>
<li>To get a comfortable fit, I cast on 84 instead of the <a href="http://www.knittingonthenet.com/patterns/hatlongstockingcap.htm">original</a> pattern’s 78.</li>
<li>To produce a slightly shorter hat, I decreased every 15 stitches instead of every 20.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/post/2018/04/attachments/img/2018/me.jpg" alt="Me wearing the stocking cap"/></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: My Sloppy Floppy Fingerless Mitten</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/02/my-sloppy-floppy-fingerless-mitten/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/02/my-sloppy-floppy-fingerless-mitten/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I knit a fingerless mitten. Mistakes were made. I also figured out some stuff about Hugo Page Bundles and image processing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>glove</category>  <category>hugo</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I knit a fingerless mitten. Mistakes were made. I also figured out some stuff about Hugo Page Bundles and image processing.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/02/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-02-17.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-02-17.jpg"/></p>
<p>I modified a mitten pattern from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns?from_search=true">Knitter&rsquo;s Handy Book of Patterns</a>. The book&rsquo;s template approach works for me. I adjusted the pattern for fingerless mittens — my preference.</p>
<p>I will knit the mittens again, making additional adjustments.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cast on fewer stitches. I prefer less ease in my gloves.</li>
<li>Stop an inch shorter on the upper part of the hand. Cover the knuckles, and no more.</li>
<li>Knock at least four stitches off the thumb gusset.</li>
</ul>
<p>It isn&rsquo;t all negative. I kept consistent gauge, and the <a href="https://www.thespruce.com/stretchy-bind-off-stich-knitting-tutorial-2115677">stretchy bind off</a> stayed stretchy.</p>
<h2 id="hugo">Hugo?</h2>
<p>I wrote this post to learn <a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/image-processing/">image processing</a> in <a href="/card/hugo/">card/Hugo</a> 0.36. My suggestion: follow the documentation, especially where it says to name your content file <code>index.md</code>.</p>
<p>Maybe I can say a little more about that. I&rsquo;ll just focus on the bits relevant to <a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/page-resources/">Page Resources</a>, since the rest of it is specific to the details of my site.</p>
<p>Up until today my site images relied on a Python script to generate post cover images and thumbnails from master images in <code>static/</code>. Hugo 0.36 can now create those images itself, but you have to organize your content and its images correctly.</p>
<h3 id="post-organization">Post organization</h3>
<p>Instead of a single file, your post becomes a directory, with <code>index.md</code> for the content itself.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >content
&#43;-&gt; craft
  &#43;-&gt; 2018
    &#43;-&gt; my-sloppy-floppy-fingerless-mitten
      &#43;-&gt; index.md
      &#43;-&gt; cover.jpg</code></pre>
</figure><h3 id="templates">Templates</h3>
<p>Posts might have a primary images, which Hugo displays at the top of the post itself, and as a thumbnail in summary pages. I named the image <code>cover.jpg</code>.</p>
<h4 id="cover-image">Cover Image</h4>
<p>If I have a cover image, Hugo&rsquo;s image processing creates a version of the image 800 pixels wide. Display this image, along with a link to the original.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >{{- $description := .Title -}}
{{- $coverImage := .Page.Resources.GetMatch &#34;cover*&#34; -}}
{{- if $coverImage -}}
  {{- $image := $coverImage.Resize &#34;800x&#34; -}}
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;{{ $image.RelPermalink }}&#34; alt=&#34;{{ $description }}&#34;
         height=&#34;{{ $image.Height }}&#34; width=&#34;{{ $image.Width }}&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      {{ $description }}&lt;br&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;{{ $coverImage.RelPermalink }}&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;
        (see full size in new window)
      &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
{{- else -}}
  legacy cover image handling
{{- end -}}</code></pre>
</figure><h4 id="thumbnail">Thumbnail</h4>
<p>If I have a cover image, I create 128 pixel square <a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/image-processing/#smart-cropping-of-images">smart crop</a> — a thumbnail which should show the original&rsquo;s most interesting part. The thumbnail is presented along with a link to the post itself.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >{{ $title := .Title }}
{{- $coverImage := .Page.Resources.GetMatch &#34;cover*&#34; -}}
{{- if $coverImage -}}
  {{- $thumbnail := $coverImage.Fill &#34;128x128&#34; -}}
  &lt;a href=&#34;{{ .Permalink }}&#34; title=&#34;{{ $title }}&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img class=&#34;summary-thumbnail&#34;
         src=&#34;{{ $thumbnail.RelPermalink }}&#34;
         alt=&#34;{{ $title }}&#34;
         height=&#34;{{ $thumbnail.Height }}&#34;
         width=&#34;{{ $thumbnail.Width }}&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
{{- else -}}
  legacy thumbnail handling
{{- end -}}</code></pre>
</figure><h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>This flow replaces my Python image script and a fair amount of templating logic. Once I remove the legacy templating logic, I&rsquo;ll put the cover image and thumbnail dimensions in site config, making it easier to redesign page layout later.</p>
<p>I better get to it.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
