<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ssgonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/ssg/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinssg on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/ssg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Elf Sternberg on how SSG is not a reaction</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/elf-sternberg-on-how-ssg-is-not-a-reaction/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/elf-sternberg-on-how-ssg-is-not-a-reaction/</guid>
  <description>{% quote( cite=&#34;https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/&#34; from=“Elf Sternberg” title=“Static site generation is not a ‘reaction’ to client-site rendering” ) %} It was literally the first thing we did. {% end %}
Strong agree. I’ve heard variations on static site generators being something invented after SPAs turned out to be a less than universal solution. Sounds like Elf’s start was with Muse — an Emacs tool that I heard of but never played with.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>quotes</category>  <category>ssg</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>{% quote(
cite=&quot;<a href="https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/">https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/</a>&quot;
from=&ldquo;Elf Sternberg&rdquo;
title=&ldquo;Static site generation is not a &lsquo;reaction&rsquo; to client-site rendering&rdquo;
) %}
It was literally the first thing we did.
{% end %}</p>
<p>Strong agree. I&rsquo;ve heard variations on static site generators being something invented after SPAs turned out to be a less than universal solution. Sounds like Elf&rsquo;s start was with <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs-muse/index.html">Muse</a> — an Emacs tool that I heard of but never played with.</p>
<p>I showed up onto the Internet a few years later, so I had a few site-generating frameworks to choose from. <a href="http://webmake.taint.org">WebMake</a> built my site for a couple years. What was that other one? Oh that&rsquo;s right! Engelschall&rsquo;s <a href="https://thewml.github.io/about/">WML</a>! That was fun too.</p>
<p>Oh, and my first interesting project was converting Vim&rsquo;s text documentation to usable HTML. I had a better version at some point, but <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020422015833/http://www.coolnamehere.com/vim/vimdoc/help.html">this</a> was what I found with the Wayback Machine.</p>
<p>Anyways, there&rsquo;s also some good points in there about &ldquo;the eternal amnesia.&rdquo; That&rsquo;s one name for — basically, when folks have no foundational context. They think they&rsquo;re the first ones to think about some issue that was addressed in 1999, or 1968, or ~260 BCE.</p>
<p>{% quote() %}
The Eternal Amnesia is a consequence of how programming works&hellip; it encourages programmers to fill their brains with the sort of intellectual puzzle solving that used to be left to the rare professional mathematician, but without giving us the time to write it all down and explain how it works to other people.
{% end %}</p>
<p>No time to write it and not much time to read it, either. The kind of thoughtful effort it takes to build your context runs counter to the whole &ldquo;if you got time to lean, you got time to clean&rdquo; rut we call a work ethic.</p>
<p>Except we don&rsquo;t really clean either. You know — technical debt? That tag for 90% of the items in your ticket backlog? The backlog that&rsquo;ll last longer than your job?</p>
<p>Anyways. Yeah. Static site generation has been around for a bit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: I Talked About My Site on Test &amp; Code in Python</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/07/i-talked-about-my-site-on-test-code-in-python/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 15:04:02 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/07/i-talked-about-my-site-on-test-code-in-python/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;In the latest &lt;a href=&#34;https://testandcode.com/191&#34;&gt;episode&lt;/a&gt; of the Test &amp; Code podcast, Brian Okken — host and author of the excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://pragprog.com/titles/bopytest2/python-testing-with-pytest-second-edition/&#34;&gt;Python Testing with pytest&lt;/a&gt; — and I talked about the little joys of running your own Web site.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>listen</category>  <category>blogging</category>  <category>ssg</category>  <category>my-brand</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the latest <a href="https://testandcode.com/191">episode</a> of the Test &amp; Code podcast, Brian Okken — host and author of the excellent <a href="https://pragprog.com/titles/bopytest2/python-testing-with-pytest-second-edition/">Python Testing with pytest</a> — and I talked about the little joys of running your own Web site.</p>
<p><a href="https://podcast.pythontest.com/episodes/191-running-your-own-site-for-fun-and-absolutely-no-profit-whatsoever-brian-wisti">Python Test | Running your own site for fun and absolutely no profit whatsoever - Brian Wisti</a></p>
<p>Of course, it just reminded me how much I have been neglecting this here site. Fixed, a little.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Starting 2022 With Eleventy</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/01/starting-2022-with-eleventy/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 21:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/01/starting-2022-with-eleventy/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/01/../../../attachments/img/2022/cover-2022-01-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;attachments/img/2022/cover-2022-01-01.jpg&#34;/&gt;
A baby possum!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally ported enough of my site to &lt;a href=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/card/eleventy/&#34;&gt;card/Eleventy&lt;/a&gt; that I feel like making it live. It’s only been two and a half years since I started &lt;a href=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/04/eleventy/&#34;&gt;thinking&lt;/a&gt; about this. Why rush into things, right?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>eleventy</category>  <category>ssg</category>  <category>site</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>It's not done, but it's done enough</h2><p><img src="/post/2022/01/../../../attachments/img/2022/cover-2022-01-01.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2022/cover-2022-01-01.jpg"/>
A baby possum!</p>
<p>Finally ported enough of my site to <a href="/card/eleventy/">card/Eleventy</a> that I feel like making it live. It&rsquo;s only been two and a half years since I started <a href="/post/2019/04/eleventy/">thinking</a> about this. Why rush into things, right?</p>
<h2 id="but-why">But why?</h2>
<p>Well, Eleventy&rsquo;s got <a href="https://mozilla.github.io/nunjucks/">Nunjucks</a> support, for starters. For the Pythonistas out there, Nunjucks is basically <a href="https://jinja2docs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">Jinja</a> for Node.js.</p>
<p>Beyond that, the Node.js ecosystem is pretty lively, with plenty to keep the dedicated <a href="/post/2020/09/ssg-is-for-putterers/">putterer</a> occupied for a bit. Eleventy can hook into enough of that without going overboard on the <a href="https://jamstack.com">Jamstack</a> application side of things. A gentle transition.</p>
<h2 id="this-isnt-even-my-final-form">This isn&rsquo;t even my final form</h2>
<p>Nowhere near what I&rsquo;d call &ldquo;done.&rdquo; There&rsquo;s still things to touch up with the Eleventy site. Layout, workflow, architecture.</p>
<p>And naturally I&rsquo;m already casting glances at other SSGs like <a href="https://lumeland.github.io">Lume</a>. I haven&rsquo;t abandoned the <a href="/card/astro/">card/Astro</a> experiment either. I&rsquo;m just waiting for Astro to be a little quicker at assembling a site like mine.</p>
<p>I just really really wanted to stop complaining about <a href="/card/hugo/">card/Hugo</a>. It&rsquo;s great. It really is. It just hasn&rsquo;t felt like a good fit for my particular flow in the last couple years.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: I got Astro working!</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/12/i-got-astro-working/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/12/i-got-astro-working/</guid>
  <description>this time you get a screenshot
card/Astro is great once you get started. A bit funky if you have twenty years of legacy content.
Rather than do my usual — a screenshot and maybe a “lesson learned” post — this time around I made a public repo and live instance of this in-progress experiment available for your entertainment and edification.
Oh and lesson learned: components are fussy, and the errors don’t always happen where you expect.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>astro-dot-build</category>  <category>ssg</category>  <category>site</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2021/12/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-12-23.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-12-23.png"/>
this time you get a screenshot</p>
<p><a href="/card/astro/">card/Astro</a> is great once you get started. A bit funky if you have twenty years of legacy content.</p>
<p>Rather than do my usual — a screenshot and <em>maybe</em> a &ldquo;lesson learned&rdquo; post — this time around I made a public <a href="https://github.com/brianwisti/rgb-astro">repo</a> and <a href="https://quirky-wozniak-e4e36f.netlify.app">live instance</a> of this in-progress experiment available for your entertainment and edification.</p>
<p>Oh and lesson learned: components are <em>fussy</em>, and the errors don&rsquo;t always happen where you expect. Treat all your imported HTML as XHTML, and look for stray <code>{</code> characters. You might need to convert those to <code>&amp;#123;</code>.</p>
<p>Took me months to figure that out. Hopefully it saves you a few hours of confusion.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: pared down to the base blog</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/08/pared-down-to-the-base-blog/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/08/pared-down-to-the-base-blog/</guid>
  <description>My rst.txt files become HTML before the SSG sees, so I may leave them
No more content shortcodes. No more — or at least not many — exotic content formats. Embedded video or tweet? Copy and paste the embed code from the host site. Need some fancy HTML for notes? Use raw HTML.
I need a base blog, with minimal dependencies on card/Hugo or any other card/Static Site Generator, so I can get serious with some of those others.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>ssg</category>  <category>site</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2021/08/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-08-21.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-08-21.png"/>
My <code>rst.txt</code> files become HTML before the SSG sees, so I may leave them</p>
<p>No more content shortcodes. No more — or at least not many — exotic content formats. Embedded video or tweet? Copy and paste the embed code from the host site. Need some fancy HTML for notes? Use raw HTML.</p>
<p>I need a base blog, with minimal dependencies on <a href="/card/hugo/">card/Hugo</a> or any other <a href="/card/static-site-generator/">card/Static Site Generator</a>, so I can get serious with some of those others. &ldquo;I&rsquo;d need to port all my shortcodes&rdquo; has blocked me from switching for the last year and a half (you accumulate a lot of cruft using the same site builder for six years). Now it won&rsquo;t be such a blocker.</p>
<p>Plus, I can try the fancy stuff in <a href="/card/astro/">card/Astro</a> or <a href="/card/lektor/">card/Lektor</a> or whatever and still have the base blog to fall back on. Heck, I could port the base blog to <a href="/card/eleventy/">card/Eleventy</a> or <a href="/card/zola/">card/Zola</a> or …</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: oh no there is a shiny new SSG</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/07/oh-no-there-is-a-shiny-new-ssg/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/07/oh-no-there-is-a-shiny-new-ssg/</guid>
  <description>Saw card/Astro mentioned in my Twitter feed today. Tempting.
Been looking for a gateway SSG into JavaScript. Something with a little more built-in than card/Eleventy, but maybe a bit less than card/Gatsby. I think I’ll play with Astro — see if it keeps my attention.
Will it keep my attention long enough to replace the Hugo version? Precedent says “no.” But it should be fun just the same.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>ssg</category>  <category>astro</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saw <a href="/card/astro/">card/Astro</a> mentioned in my Twitter feed today. Tempting.</p>
<p>Been looking for a gateway SSG into JavaScript. Something with a little more built-in than <a href="/card/eleventy/">card/Eleventy</a>, but maybe a bit less than <a href="/card/gatsby/">card/Gatsby</a>. I think I&rsquo;ll play with Astro — see if it keeps my attention.</p>
<p>Will it keep my attention long enough to replace the Hugo version? Precedent says &ldquo;no.&rdquo; But it should be fun just the same.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Still pondering new site approaches</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/still-pondering-new-site-approaches/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 23:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/04/still-pondering-new-site-approaches/</guid>
  <description>I haven’t exactly loved card/Hugo since they stuck me with Go templates as the only option. But Hugo doesn’t need me to love it, and it works well enough for me. Still. You look around and try stuff out with different builders.
card/Lektor looks nice — darn good control panel and API for a static site generator. Course I know about card/Gatsby, card/Eleventy, and card/Zola. Eh, nice enough but none really grabbed me and held on.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>hugo</category>  <category>ssg</category>  <category>but-what-else-is-there</category>  <category>site</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Just name-dropping site generators</h2><p>I haven’t exactly <em>loved</em> <a href="/card/hugo/">card/Hugo</a> since they stuck me with Go templates as
the only option.  But Hugo doesn’t need me to love it, and it works well enough for me.  Still.  You look around and try stuff out with different builders.</p>
<p><a href="/card/lektor/">card/Lektor</a> looks nice — darn good control panel and API for a static site generator.  Course I know about <a href="/card/gatsby/">card/Gatsby</a>, <a href="/card/eleventy/">card/Eleventy</a>, and <a href="/card/zola/">card/Zola</a>.  Eh, nice enough but none really grabbed me and held on. <a href="/card/nanoc/">card/Nanoc</a>?  Possibly.  Been having trouble with Ruby dependencies lately. No idea why — something something FFI — but it’s putting me off the Ruby site builders for the moment.</p>
<p>But maybe I don’t want static.  Maybe something like <a href="/card/statamic/">card/Statamic</a>, which feels like &ldquo;what if somebody wrote <a href="https://wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> today, with <a href="/card/laravel/">card/Laravel</a>?&rdquo; It <em>would</em> be nice to have something which let me be more impulsive with notes and pics.</p>
<p>Porting this site more or less intact would be a headache and a half.  Whatever I use better have good redirects and maybe even search.</p>
<p>Anyways that’s how I’ve been spending what spare time I get.  Hope things are okay for you in Pandemic Year Two.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: SSG is for putterers</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/09/ssg-is-for-putterers/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 10:29:56 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/09/ssg-is-for-putterers/</guid>
  <description>Kev Quirk on static site generators — WordPress Creator Vs The Jamstack (2020-05-20)
SSGs are really cool and super fun to play with – I’m really enjoying it on my side project; but I wish a lot of devs would stop touting about how amazingly simple they are, as it’s just not the case.
I often see “such and such card/Static Site Generator is simple!” tweets, and wonder what exactly they’re comparing it to.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>ssg</category>  <category>blogging</category>  <category>puttering</category>  <category>indieweb</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Kev Quirk on static site generators</strong> — <a href="https://kevq.uk/wordpress-creator-vs-the-jamstack/">WordPress Creator Vs The Jamstack</a> (2020-05-20)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>SSGs are really cool and super fun to play with – I’m really enjoying it on
my side project; but I wish a lot of devs would stop touting about how
amazingly simple they are, as it’s just not the case.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I often see &ldquo;such and such <a href="/card/static-site-generator/">card/Static Site Generator</a> is simple!&rdquo; tweets, and wonder what exactly they&rsquo;re comparing it to. DIY dentistry perhaps?</p>
<p>As much as I love puttering with static site generators, &ldquo;puttering&rdquo; is the main charm of an SSG. The hooks to customize are right there on the surface. Heck <a href="/card/eleventy/">Eleventy</a> is nothing <em>but</em> hooks. And having everything in a git repository is just a developer-focused version of a smart backup plan.</p>
<p>For the <a href="https://jamstack.org/">Jamstack</a> side of things, I&rsquo;m not sure I see the advantage of relying on a load of external services over oh say for example having a database and an internal comment system. You know, like Wordpress. Something I&rsquo;ve been thinking about a lot in relation to my own site leaning so much on <a href="https://webmention.io/">webmention.io</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
