<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>sublime-textonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/sublime-text/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinsublime-text on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 08:55:27 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/sublime-text/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Looks like Sublime Text is shifting to a subscription plan</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/looks-like-sublime-text-is-shifting-to-a-subscription-plan/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 08:55:27 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/looks-like-sublime-text-is-shifting-to-a-subscription-plan/</guid>
  <description>Yesterday’s dev build plus A File Icon
Terence Martin posted a couple helpful videos explaining version licensing and the impending changes to the Sublime Text text editor, along with some tips on getting started with “version 4.” So nice I watched them twice.
A real subscription, where you get to keep the builds you paid for. I like this.
Okay, sure. Sublime Text isn’t open source. Version releases are few and far between.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>editors</category>  <category>sublime-text</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Found via my quarterly "Sublime Text 4" web search</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-30.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-30.png"/></figure>
Yesterday&rsquo;s dev build plus <a href="https://packagecontrol.io/packages/A%20File%20Icon">A File Icon</a></p>
<p><a href="https://odatnurd.net">Terence Martin</a> posted a couple helpful videos <a href="https://youtu.be/P52ZBQvAAsU">explaining</a> version licensing and the impending changes to the <a href="https://www.sublimetext.com">Sublime Text</a> text editor, along with some tips on <a href="https://youtu.be/_HoltQwvF2o">getting started</a> with &ldquo;version 4.&rdquo; So nice I watched them twice.</p>
<p>A real subscription, where you get to keep the builds you paid for.  I like this.</p>
<p>Okay, sure.  Sublime Text isn’t open source.  Version releases are few and far between. But it’s <em>good</em> — the only graphical text editor I’ve used that feels as responsive as <a href="/card/vim/">card/Vim</a>.</p>
<p>I love supporting independent development when I can.  A subscription approach is more sustainable for developers and more satisfying for users than the (extremely) intermittent bursts of version-based licensing.  There’s nothing official, so I don’t know what’s really happening.  The <a href="https://discord.gg/HcmwdVK">Sublime Discord</a> &ldquo;announcements&rdquo; channel holds the details.</p>
<p>Python 3.8.6. Good stuff!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
