<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>the-internetonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/the-internet/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinthe-internet on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/the-internet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Save those links</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/07/save-those-links/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/07/save-those-links/</guid>
  <description>Saw this post today:
{% quote from=&#34;@n4@freeradical.zone&#34; cite=“https://freeradical.zone/@n4/110636140651779144&#34; %}
My greatest advice to those concerned: Start archiving. If you come across something you believe is valuable: make a copy.
If you follow a guide on how to install and configure software and you found it helpful: make a copy.
If you come across a video you really enjoy and find yourself coming back to again and again: make a copy.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>the-internet</category>  <category>second-brain</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saw this post today:</p>
<p>{% quote
from=&quot;@n4@freeradical.zone&quot;
cite=&ldquo;<a href="https://freeradical.zone/@n4/110636140651779144%22">https://freeradical.zone/@n4/110636140651779144"</a>
%}</p>
<p>My greatest advice to those concerned: Start archiving. If you come across something you believe is valuable: make a copy.</p>
<p>If you follow a guide on how to install and configure software and you found it helpful: make a copy.</p>
<p>If you come across a video you really enjoy and find yourself coming back to again and again: make a copy.</p>
<p>If it means anything to you: make a copy, or you’ll wish you did.
{% /quote %}</p>
<p>That prompted me to quote-share with my own suggestions:</p>
<p>{% quote
from=&quot;@randomgeek@ack.cringe.cafe&rdquo;
%}
Plain old link rot prompted my PKM habits. Twitter, Reddit, etc. are now putting Hanlon’s razor to the test, so it’s a good time to try it yourself.</p>
<p><a href="https://capacities.io">Capacities</a> provides excellent link archiving capabilities, but you gotta trust the online-only aspect.</p>
<p>Browser extensions such as <a href="https://github.com/deathau/markdownload">MarkDownload</a> can grab page content to paste into Markdown-friendly note tools like ObsidianMD and Logseq. If you prefer CLI, <a href="https://xwmx.github.io/nb/">nb</a> archives every link you bookmark with it.</p>
<p>Course, in all cases process those notes to the useful bits. Otherwise you’re just data hoarding. Understandable in this Digital Depression, but not helpful.
{% /quote %}</p>
<p>And then it occurred to me. Between budget and attention span constraints, my <a href="https://akkoma.social">Akkoma</a> instance — the one I posted that from — could die at any minute. Maybe I should follow my advice and put that note somewhere more persistent. First my notes, and then this blog.</p>
<p>So there’s my productivity quota for the day more or less complete.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>2023-10-25</strong></p>
<p>Sure enough I had to take down my Akkoma instance recently for budget prioritization.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Maybe lock chat-gpt3 out of your blog</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/01/maybe-lock-chat-gpt3-out-of-your-blog/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/01/maybe-lock-chat-gpt3-out-of-your-blog/</guid>
  <description>Random post crossed into my field of view today.
{% quote( from=“OnePub” title=“The threat that chat-gpt3 poses to bloggers” cite=&#34;https://onepub.dev/Blog?id=jxbxpsdavu&amp;utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=post&amp;utm_campaign=blog&#34; ) %}
When one day someone asks Chat-gpt3 - ‘how is chat-gpt3 like a Wasp Spider’, chat-gpt3 will quote my article (because who else would make such ridiculous analogies) without attribution.
But what it won’t do is offer the user a link to the source of the information and it will never result in a user visiting the OnePub blog.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>the-internet</category>  <category>and-other-delusions</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Random post crossed into my field of view today.</p>
<p>{% quote(
from=&ldquo;OnePub&rdquo;
title=&ldquo;The threat that chat-gpt3 poses to bloggers&rdquo;
cite=&quot;<a href="https://onepub.dev/Blog?id=jxbxpsdavu&amp;utm_source=reddit&amp;utm_medium=post&amp;utm_campaign=blog">https://onepub.dev/Blog?id=jxbxpsdavu&utm_source=reddit&utm_medium=post&utm_campaign=blog</a>&quot;
) %}</p>
<p>When one day someone asks Chat-gpt3 - &lsquo;how is chat-gpt3 like a Wasp Spider&rsquo;, chat-gpt3 will quote my article (because who else would make such ridiculous analogies) without attribution.</p>
<p>But what it won&rsquo;t do is offer the user a link to the source of the information and it will never result in a user visiting the OnePub blog.
{% end %}</p>
<p>&ldquo;I made this&rdquo; is one of the oldest frustrations of the Internet, to the point of being immortalized in comic form at least <a href="https://nedroidcomics.tumblr.com/post/41879001445/the-internet">once</a>. Heck it&rsquo;s part of why I set my site content to a Creative Commons license. Why fight it? But yeah. Any possible external value has been extracted and claimed. Let&rsquo;s assume it&rsquo;s too late for my ancient blog.</p>
<p>Your newer site, with words and images you care deeply about? You may want to put some locks on those doors.</p>
<p>The only caveat about the advice from the article — aside from the fact that it&rsquo;s probably kinda satirical what with getting its answers <em>from</em> chat-GPT3:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>robots.txt</code> is usually ignored &mdash; but it&rsquo;s still a nice gesture to the few who acknowledge it</li>
<li>User-agent restrictions can be worked around with minimal effort &mdash; but will work against the large number of folks who can&rsquo;t be bothered with minimal effort</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
