<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>marginaliaonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/marginalia/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinmarginalia on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:00:21 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/marginalia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Got Married Yesterday</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/got-married-yesterday/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 11:00:21 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/got-married-yesterday/</guid>
  <description>NOTE
I mentioned it on hackers.town / Twitter. Even updated my relationship status on Facebook. I’ll probably leave LinkedIn alone for the moment. But worth remembering here as well.
Seattle, 2020.
COVID-19 has shut down pretty much everything in the city and beyond. Large gatherings are forbidden, or at least strongly discouraged.
Thank goodness.
No not for the disease. Sheesh. For the new social rules. They gave us an acceptable excuse to keep our wedding a small affair.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>life</category>  <category>with-my-sweetheart</category>  <category>marginalia</category>  <category>now</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Can't let our dystopian sci-fi setting stop us</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-03-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-03-20.jpg"/></figure></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong></p>
<p>I mentioned it on <a href="https://hackers.town/@randomgeek/103853335008640787">hackers.town</a> / <a href="https://twitter.com/brianwisti/status/1240848019077111814">Twitter</a>. Even updated my relationship status on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/brianwisti/posts/10158601243074665">Facebook</a>. I’ll probably leave LinkedIn alone for the moment. But worth remembering here as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://crosscut.com/2020/03/coronavirus-turns-seattle-americas-laboratory">Seattle</a>, 2020.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2020/03/biography-new-coronavirus/608338/">COVID-19</a> has shut down pretty much <a href="https://publichealthinsider.com/2020/03/17/events-eating-out-and-retail-whats-allowed-and-whats-not/">everything</a> in the city and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/coronavirus-comes-spring-break-locals-close-florida-beaches-after-governor-n1163741">beyond</a>. Large gatherings are forbidden, or at least strongly discouraged.</p>
<p>Thank goodness.</p>
<p>No not for the disease. Sheesh. For the new social rules. They gave us an  acceptable excuse to keep our wedding a small affair.</p>
<p>A <em>very</em> small affair. Five of us and four — her <a href="https://twitter.com/qlitterbang">eldest daughter</a>, <a href="https://www.shellybedsaul.com">my mom</a> (subliminal message: BUY THEIR ART) plus a couple friends who couldn’t be there because quarantine — watching on Facebook group video chat. Might have added more, but the technical issues were complicated enough as it was.</p>
<p>One of our friends got ordained so she could officiate. We wouldn’t have to worry about the courthouses closing! The same friend was sort of an anti-chaperone at an early event. She made sure we were dancing close enough and that our hands were outside the Respectful First Dance Zone.</p>
<p>And yesterday she made sure we would be able to get married. It’s the circle of life. Or something. It’s very sweet is what it is.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2020/thumbs-up.jpg" title="You want a serious event, talk to someone else" alt="Newlyweds and friend grinning with thumbs up"/><figcaption>You want a serious event, talk to someone else</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>So yeah I’m happy. And the honeymoon will be nice — whenever the world opens back up again so we can have one.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic DIY Sea Salt Spray</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/10/basic-diy-sea-salt-spray/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/10/basic-diy-sea-salt-spray/</guid>
  <description>Sea salt, argan oil, and a spray bottle. You need water too.
tl;dr:
Heat a cup of water. Mix in 2 teaspoons argan oil, 1 tablespoon sea salt, and a few drops of something pretty. Let it cool. Shake before each use.
The recipe Get ingredients at your favorite local market or evil online megacorporation!
Ingredients Sea salt 1 Argan oil 2 Spray bottle 3 Funnel Maybe a whisk Kettle or other means of making cold water hot Extras That’s pretty much all you need.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>diy</category>  <category>recipe</category>  <category>grooming</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>In which I write a hair spray recipe and *then* share the story</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-10-21.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-10-21.jpg"/></figure>
Sea salt, argan oil, and a spray bottle. You need water too.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>tl;dr:</strong></p>
<p>Heat a cup of water. Mix in 2 teaspoons argan oil, 1 tablespoon sea salt, and a few drops of something pretty. Let it cool. Shake before each use.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="the-recipe">The recipe</h2>
<p>Get ingredients at your favorite local market or evil online megacorporation!</p>
<h3 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h3>
<ul>
<li>Sea salt <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></li>
<li>Argan oil <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></li>
<li>Spray bottle <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup></li>
<li>Funnel</li>
<li>Maybe a whisk</li>
<li>Kettle or other means of making cold water hot</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="extras">Extras</h3>
<p>That’s pretty much all you <em>need</em>. You’re free to add more!</p>
<ul>
<li>tea tree, sandalwood, or some other essential oil with a smell that pleases you</li>
<li>hair gel or coconut oil — for additional hold</li>
<li>epsom salt — for magnesium, I guess?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="instructions">Instructions</h3>
<ol>
<li>Heat some water in the kettle. If it boils, let it cool a moment. You don’t want your first hairspray story to involve burn treatment.</li>
<li>Measure out one cup (roughly 250 ml) of hot water</li>
<li>Whisk in 2 teaspoons of oil. You can vary this a bit more or less depending on how dry your hair gets.</li>
<li>Whisk in a tablespoon of sea salt. A little more gives more hold, but careful to avoid crusty hair!</li>
<li>If you want your hair to smell nice, whisk in a few drops of essential oil.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></li>
<li>Pour your mix into the spray bottle with a funnel, unless you have very steady hands!</li>
<li>Let it cool to room temperature or at least until there’s no risk of burns.</li>
<li>Shake vigorously before each use!</li>
</ol>
<p>One batch lasts me over a month of daily use, but I intentionally go for a lighter hold. Out of my face and roughly pointed in the right direction is all I care about.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2019/me.jpg" alt="Still roughly pointed in the right direction halfway through the day"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="the-story">The story</h2>
<p>Now that the recipe is out of the way — I thought cookbooks were bad about forcing you to read a long story before giving you their instructions. Cookbooks are nothing. Those self-care blogs are <em>awful</em>. An evening searching and I couldn’t find the source for the basic recipe I’ve been using over the last year or so because I couldn’t get through all the <em>stories</em>.</p>
<p>I had this big story in mind about how I was watching a beard care video one night and they said &ldquo;use sea salt spray! It’s good on your hair!&rdquo; and I said &ldquo;okay!&rdquo; and they said &ldquo;use <em>our</em> sea salt spray!&rdquo; and I said &ldquo;at that price? H*ck no!&rdquo; I was even going to work in some <a href="/card/perl/">card/Perl</a> references. Talk about how making your own hair spray is another application of <a href="http://threevirtues.com/">The Three Virtues</a>.</p>
<p>But I got bored just writing the outline for that particular story. Now it’s a year later, and I’m writing down the recipe somewhere permanent to avoid losing it again.</p>
<p>Look around for ideas from other recipes, but take what you read with a grain of sea salt. We’re here for mad science and saving money, not Clean Living or Purity Of Essence.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iyj_D2ivwS4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>This recipe is what I came up with last night after giving up on my search. You can find many recipes with varying ingredients and proportions. Experiment. Figure out what works for you.</p>
<p>Then write it down somewhere so you aren’t making something up again when you run out.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Update</strong></p>
<p>I found the recipe I started with! <a href="https://www.gimmesomeoven.com/diy/diy-sea-salt-texturizing-hair-spray/">Gimme Some Oven</a> has the information you need. Not much different than what you’ll find here, though with less Dr. Strangelove.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p></p>
&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Now on Dreamhost</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/06/now-on-dreamhost/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/06/now-on-dreamhost/</guid>
  <description>The site’s moved from AWS to Dreamhost!
Nothing wrong with AWS S3 for static site hosting, but some of what I want to do is easier to describe in a shell. Also – I don’t mind paying for a service, but I got tired of usage-based billing. I ended up literally paying for typos more than a few times. Give me a predictable bill please.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>site</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The site’s moved from <a href="https://aws.amazon.com">AWS</a> to <a href="https://dreamhost.com">Dreamhost</a>!</p>
<p>Nothing wrong with AWS S3 for static site hosting, but some of what I want to do is easier to describe in a shell. Also – I don’t mind paying for a service, but I got tired of usage-based billing. I ended up literally paying for typos more than a few times. Give me a predictable bill please.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Hopepunk for 2019</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Lots of copying and pasting in this, since getting the words in full is important to me.</p>
<p>Tonight on Facebook, a friend shared a <a href="http://heartlessharless.tumblr.com/post/133490414240/alycs-being-unconditionally-polite-kind-and">Tumblr post</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Being unconditionally polite, kind, and compassionate in a society that values and finds “deeper meaning” in aloofness and cynicism is subversive and thus punk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>hufflepunk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has been my own general philosophy. Best to make it explicit. Values fade if kept in the shadows.</p>
<p>Anyways, &ldquo;hufflepunk&rdquo; sounds an awful lot like <a href="https://ariaste.tumblr.com/post/163500138919/ariaste-the-opposite-of-grimdark-is-hopepunk">hopepunk</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The opposite of grimdark is hopepunk. Pass it on.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>#this is a good post #also I need an example of hopepunk #bc the name #resonates with me #and I need it
#please #if you don’t mind (via @-lavender-starling)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So the essence of grimdark is that everyone’s inherently sort of a bad person and does bad things, and that’s awful and disheartening and cynical. It’s looking at human nature and going, “The glass is half empty.”</p>
<p>Hopepunk says, “No, I don’t accept that. Go fuck yourself: The glass is half-full.”  YEAH, we’re all a messy mix of good and bad, flaws and virtues. We’ve all been mean and petty and cruel, but (and here’s the important part) we’ve also been soft and forgiving and KIND. Hopepunk says that kindness and softness doesn’t equal weakness, and that in this world of brutal cynicism and nihilism, being kind is a <em>political act</em>. An act of <em>rebellion.</em></p>
<p>Hopepunk says that <em>genuinely and sincerely</em> caring about something, anything, requires bravery and strength. Hopepunk isn’t ever about submission or acceptance: It’s about standing up and fighting for what you believe in. It’s about standing up for other people. It’s about DEMANDING a better, kinder world, and truly believing that we can get there if we care about each other as hard as we possibly can, with every drop of power in our little hearts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There&rsquo;s more, but I don&rsquo;t need to paste the <em>entire</em> post.</p>
<p>Looking up Hopepunk led me to <a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/12/27/18137571/what-is-hopepunk-noblebright-grimdark">this Vox article</a>, which does a fine job breaking it down so I don&rsquo;t have to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Through this framing, the idea of choosing hope becomes both an existential act that affirms your humanity, and a form of resistance against cynical worldviews that dismiss hope as a powerful force for change.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see, what other examples can I think of? Oh, I know: <a href="http://www.pbs.org/parents/rogers">Mister Rogers</a>. You could throw a dart at a wall of Fred Rogers quotes and anything it hit would be appropriate for hopepunk. The man fully understood the world he was speaking to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some days, doing &ldquo;the best we can&rdquo; may still fall short of what we would like to be able to do, but life isn&rsquo;t perfect on any front — and doing what we can with what we have is the most we should expect of ourselves or
anyone else. — <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/895495">Fred Rogers</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The thing about all of these is that you don&rsquo;t expect the world to magically become a better place through your efforts. You do them because that&rsquo;s how things should be, and if we see someone stubbornly refusing to submit to cynicism, it might give us a little strength for our own efforts. If nothing else, we can sleep a little more easily with ourselves at night.</p>
<p>So I intend to be more explicitly this in 2019.</p>
<p>And — you know. If you don&rsquo;t like it, fuck off. I love you anyways.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: On Modesty And Imposter Syndrome</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</guid>
  <description>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It’s a rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It’s something I’ll need to read again.
It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I’m glad.
Don’t get in your own way Imposter Syndrome is a thing, yes.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It&rsquo;s a  rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ll need to read again.</p>
<p>It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I&rsquo;m glad.</p>
<h2 id="dont-get-in-your-own-way">Don&rsquo;t get in your own way</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.quickanddirtytips.com/health-fitness/medical-conditions/what-is-impostor-syndrome">Imposter Syndrome</a> is a thing, yes.</p>
<p>Anyone who pays attention and is honest with themselves knows there are things they do not know, and that other people know some of those things.</p>
<p>Some folks who see how much they don&rsquo;t know assume it means they know nothing of value. Massive oversimplification, but work with me here.</p>
<p>This assumes you value knowledge or competence, of course. If you don&rsquo;t, then we won&rsquo;t have much to talk about.</p>
<p>Modesty is good, in moderation. Pretending you know more than you do is at best tasteless, and can be dangerous.</p>
<p>But don&rsquo;t get in your own way.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been programming professionally for twenty years. I&rsquo;ve been knitting for well over ten years. I&rsquo;ve been sketching close to thirty years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m better than most folks at each of these. Granted, I&rsquo;m better partly because most folks don&rsquo;t do any of those things. BUT STILL.</p>
<p>I put in time. I learned things. I know things other practitioners know, and things not every practitioner knows.</p>
<p>I learn new things all the time. I just learned how to look up the spelling of a word with <a href="http://aspell.net/">GNU aspell</a>:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ <span class="nb">echo</span> practicioner <span class="p">|</span> aspell -a
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">@<span class="o">(</span><span class="c1">#) International Ispell Version 3.1.20 (but really Aspell 0.60.7-20110707)</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="p">&amp;</span> practicioner <span class="m">6</span> 0: practitioner, practicing, practice, practiced, practices, practice<span class="err">&#39;</span>s</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>In every one of those domains I&rsquo;m <strong>convinced</strong> I&rsquo;m a raw beginner.</p>
<p>Because there are plenty of things I don&rsquo;t know, and because sometimes I get brain lock.</p>
<h2 id="brain-lock">Brain lock</h2>
<p>I usually only get brain lock when knowing the thing is important to me.</p>
<p>I <em>should</em> know the thing. I should know <em>something</em>. I knew lots of things a second ago. But suddenly I don&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know the answer. I don&rsquo;t know the question. I don&rsquo;t know how to brain. All I know is to be furious at myself.</p>
<p>Is the brain lock just me getting into emotional overload because I didn&rsquo;t <em>immediately</em> have an acceptable answer?</p>
<p>Is that one of those &ldquo;gifted child grows up&rdquo; kind of problems? Yeesh what a depressing thought.</p>
<p>Whatever it is, that brain lock gets in the way.</p>
<p>It gets in the way at work. It gets in the way in relationships. Oh goodness does it get in the way in relationships.</p>
<p>So I think I&rsquo;m a beginner because I&rsquo;m still mad at myself for not knowing everything immediately? Maybe.</p>
<p>Regardless of why I feel this way, I need to get over it.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<h2 id="stack-building">Stack building</h2>
<p>Started focusing on the crisis moments there, when the original thought was about modesty and Imposter Syndrome.</p>
<p>But that&rsquo;s part of the point, isn&rsquo;t it? Taking a specific moment, generalizing it, and then judging yourself based on the generalization?</p>
<p>And then deciding what you are and are not capable of based on that judgment?</p>
<p>And then not doing the thing because you already decided you wouldn&rsquo;t be good at it?</p>
<p>Hey look at me I built a stack of cognitive distortions!</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s pop the stack. How would I look at these if it was someone else?</p>
<p>Avoiding action out of fear is its own entire stack of issues. Let&rsquo;s just set that one to the side for today.</p>
<p>A person&rsquo;s capabilities change. They may do better or even worse than you expected, but there is always the possibility of improvement.</p>
<p>Judging someone based on a general pattern of behavior is generally good but limited. They could surprise you given a new context.</p>
<p>Taking a particular moment and imagining this is how the person will behave in every moment is almost always a bad idea.</p>
<p>Some folks I feel perfectly content building a stack like this, but not many.</p>
<p>Certainly nobody I ever felt close to. I know I&rsquo;ve been fortunate in that regard.</p>
<p>I feel pretty close to myself.</p>
<h2 id="a-better-stack">A better stack</h2>
<p>So. Yeah. Sometimes I get brain lock. That sucks, and it&rsquo;s a thing I can work on.</p>
<p>Most of the time my brain is pretty good.</p>
<p>I know things, and I know how to learn more things.</p>
<p>If anything, my general pattern is wanting to learn more and do better.</p>
<p>You can always do better, but usually you&rsquo;re further along than the last time you tried this.</p>
<p>If it doesn&rsquo;t feel that way, you&rsquo;re in the frustrating part of getting better. But you&rsquo;re still getting better.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pattern I&rsquo;ve applied successfully throughout my life. Programming, knitting, sketching, juggling, being a decent human being.</p>
<p>Heck yeah being a decent human being takes wanting to learn more and do better. I&rsquo;m working on it <em>right now</em>.</p>
<p>There we go. I built a better cognitive stack. I&rsquo;ll keep revisiting it of course.</p>
<p>Getting rid of the old one takes more than just seeing it.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been with me my whole life, so tearing it down will be the work of a lifetime.</p>
<p>But look at how much I&rsquo;ve done even with that stack in place!</p>
<p>I can still be realistically modest. I can also take pride in what I <em>have</em> accomplished, and what I&rsquo;m continuing to accomplish.</p>
<p>Not entirely sure it&rsquo;s still about modesty or Imposter Syndrome, but I&rsquo;ll leave the title. And I&rsquo;ll fight the urge to just stash this file away somewhere, because posting makes it more concrete. I have an easier time holding myself accountable with a post. After all, this isn&rsquo;t the first time I&rsquo;ve seen and worked on bits of my cognitive stack.</p>
<p>Now go knit or something.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<p>PS. Still not smoking. It&rsquo;ll be five months on Saturday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Cougar Mountain</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</guid>
  <description>The park sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.
Be careful Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Last weekend I wandered the trails of Cougar Mountain Regional Wildland Park
</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.kingcounty.gov/services/parks-recreation/parks/parks-and-natural-lands/popular-parks/cougar.aspx">park</a> sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.</p>
<h2 id="be-careful">Be careful</h2>
<p>Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently. Warning signs remind you about the area’s long history as a coal mine. Collapsed mines could collapse further with just a little weight on them. A decades-old underground fire presents ongoing <a href="https://www.heraldnet.com/news/cougar-mountain-mines-still-a-danger/">danger</a> from heat and toxic fumes.</p>
<p>Basically: if a sign tells me to stay back, I stay back.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/warning-sign.jpg" title="Pay attention to the warning signs" alt="sign warning of ground collapse or fatal gases"/><figcaption>Pay attention to the warning signs</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>The trails are well-labeled, perhaps partly due to those hazards. I still managed to get myself turned around, because there were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cougar_Mountain_Regional_Wildland_Park#Official_Trails">so many trails</a>. Somewhere along the way I lost my paper map, but had enough signal to get the Washington Trails Association <a href="https://www.wta.org/our-work/about/trailblazer-mobile-app">Trailblazer</a> app installed on my phone and follow the links to a PDF map.</p>
<h2 id="look-at-the-trees">Look at the trees</h2>
<p>I think I focused a little too much on the hazards. Those are really in specific sections of the park, and are all clearly indicated. The park itself is lovely, green, and very Pacific Northwest.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/mossy.jpg" alt="Mossy"/></figure></p>
<p>We have some lovely woods around here. I started taking that for granted over the years. My assorted <a href="/tags/sauntering">sauntering</a> trips have done a great job reminding me to not do that.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/tall-stump.jpg" alt="Tall stump"/></figure></p>
<p>The trees on Cougar Mountain are young. When the mines started winding down, logging picked up. I saw several thick old stumps near the trail, giving me a hint of what the older growth must have looked like.</p>
<p>Some of those stumps had sprouts on them, while a few had full grown trees.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/old-stump.jpg" alt="Old stump with stump sprouts"/></figure></p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/stump-tree.jpg" alt="Tree growing from stump"/></figure></p>
<p>We got some rain recently. Everything that could be green was very green indeed. Even the rocks. I walked a little out of my way to see Fantastic Erratic, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glacial_erratic">glacial erratic</a> boulder left here by glacier action in some past ice age.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/fantastic-erratic.jpg" title="Fantastic Erratic" alt="Large mossy rock"/><figcaption>Fantastic Erratic</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>My image shows the scale poorly. That single rock is roughly fifteen feet high. I took a rest break sitting on top of it, with room to stretch.</p>
<h2 id="anyways">Anyways</h2>
<p>I spent three hours walking about ten miles of trails around Cougar Mountain, enjoying the scenery and history. It didn’t feel as epic as <a href="/post/2018/09/mount-si/">walking up a mountain</a>, but I want to avoid chasing that &ldquo;epic&rdquo; feeling. I’m not racking up accomplishments. I’m getting out and appreciating more of the world around me. That includes epic moments, little details, and everything in between.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/fungi.jpg" title="Look! Fungus!" alt="clamshell-looking fungi on a tree trunk"/><figcaption>Look! Fungus!</figcaption></figure></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Mount Si</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</guid>
  <description>A rather rocky trail through the trees
Mount Si If Mount Si looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show Twin Peaks. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I sauntered up the main trail of Mount Si this weekend.</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg"/></figure>
A rather rocky trail through the trees</p>
<h2 id="mount-si">Mount Si</h2>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/mt-si.jpg" alt="Mount Si as seen from North Bend"/></figure></p>
<p>If <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/mount-si">Mount Si</a> looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_Peaks">Twin Peaks</a>. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s. It was officially labeled a Natural Resources Conservation Area in 1987.</p>
<p>The Olympic and Cascade mountains defined my landscape growing up in the Puget Sound area, but I never went up any of them. I attribute that to my habit of mentally associating &ldquo;mountain climbing&rdquo; with the major challenge of Mount Rainier. I never thought of smaller mountains such as Mount Si. They challenge desk-bound people like myself but can still be done as a single day trip.</p>
<p>Oh, you pronounce &ldquo;Si&rdquo; as &ldquo;sigh&rdquo; — not &ldquo;see.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="getting-there">Getting there</h2>
<p>The trail is a short drive from Seattle, but Google Maps gave me a hard time. I ask for directions to Mount Si. It sends me to the base of the mountain, in somebody’s driveway and nowhere near a trail. Then I ask for directions to the Mount Si <em>Trail</em> and it tries to put me on a private road. This happens often enough that the owner put up a sign indicating there was no trail access on their property.</p>
<p>I abandoned Google Maps and found the trail proper a little further up the (public) road. You want to keep your eyes peeled. The sign for the trail is easy to miss if you don’t know the area.</p>
<p>Don’t forget about your <a href="http://discoverpass.wa.gov/">Discover Pass</a>! You need one to use the official parking spots, and there’s no public parking anywhere near the trail.</p>
<p>I admit it. I forgot about the pass. Fortunately, you can purchase one at the Ace Hardware in North Bend.</p>
<h2 id="the-trail">The trail</h2>
<p>The thing about sauntering up a mountain is that the trail occupies most of your attention. You might miss interesting stuff as you spend a few hours wondering how much trail you have left. Thankfully, the trail itself is pretty interesting. Some spots soft and flat, some spots packed with rocks, and sometimes both!</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/trail.jpg" alt="a trail section with packed rocks and dirt"/></figure></p>
<p>The trail climbs around 3,000 feet over roughly four miles. A walk like that is easy enough for the experienced, but by the time I was halfway up I needed to rest every few minutes. Thank goodness nobody accompanied me! I bet a veteran walker would have been at best amused, and at worst annoyed, by my pace.</p>
<p>Nobody accompanied me, but I wasn’t alone. This trail gets loads of traffic, and has its own traffic rules.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you bring a dog, keep it on a leash, and clean up after it</li>
<li>People going up get right of way, so people going down need to make   room for them.</li>
<li>Be nice</li>
<li>Stay tidy — don’t be dropping garbage along the way!</li>
</ul>
<p>Everybody I encountered stuck with the rules, which were posted on an information board at the trail head. Well, I met a few off-leash dogs, but they were friendly.</p>
<p>My frequent breaks meant that I saw most sights while leaning or sitting on something, and waiting for my pulse to recover.</p>
<p>For example: my new, attractive, and very comfortable friend Stumpy the Stump.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/stumpy.jpg" alt="Check out this gnarled tree stump"/></figure></p>
<p>I encountered impressive rocks all over the place. That’s not unusual in the Pacific Northwest, but you rarely see anything so <em>large</em> in Seattle.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/rock.jpg" alt="Rock!"/></figure></p>
<p>Of course I looked up the details when I got home. These are <a href="https://www.usgs.gov/faqs/what-are-metamorphic-rocks-0">metamorphic</a> rocks, transformed by intense pressure. Apparently in the distant geological past, there was an oceanic plate volcano. Now, millions of years later, we walk around on it and call it Mount Si.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/more-rock.jpg" alt="These rocks used to be under an ocean?"/></figure></p>
<p>I can’t help but feel very small and brief when I try wrapping my brain around a geological time scale.</p>
<h2 id="lunch">Lunch</h2>
<p>Eventually I ran out of mountain. I paused to have lunch and enjoy the view with half a dozen other like-minded folks.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/lunch.jpg" alt="Eating lunch and looking over Snoqualmie"/></figure></p>
<p>I encountered few local critters on the way up. That’s probably because the ones that tolerate people knew to stick around up here where folks brought out food. Gray jays, chipmunks, and a wandering raven kept us company.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/grayjay.jpg" title="A photogenic gray jay posing — right before stealing my cracker!" alt="gray jay bird"/><figcaption>A photogenic gray jay posing — right before stealing my cracker!</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Keep a tight grip on your meal! One jay grabbed a cracker right out of my hand when a hiker distracted me.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/jay-rocks.jpg" alt="Gray jay against rocks"/></figure></p>
<p>I suppose a bird has to make a living. I can’t be mad when they’re so fearless and just so <em>pretty</em>.</p>
<h2 id="wandering-a-little-further">Wandering a little further</h2>
<p>So many folks came up, ate their lunch, and headed right back down. That confused me, because I was nowhere near done enjoying Mount Si. Maybe this is just a routine weekend thing for them. Me? Even if this becomes routine I’ll find excuses to stick around longer. Maybe I can bring my knitting.</p>
<p>I had read that the trail extended beyond my lunch spot, so I looked around until I saw the Haystack, an additional 200 feet of rock that marks the proper peak of Mount Si.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/haystack.jpg" title="The Haystack, Si&#39;s true summit" alt="rocky peak"/><figcaption>The Haystack, Si&#39;s true summit</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>I decided against climbing the Haystack this time. Almost halfway, I realized going down would be harder than going up. My body still felt the strain from walking up the mountain in the first place. Next trip.</p>
<p>Got some nice shots before I started back down, though.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/lovely.jpg" title="Sure the trees will break my fall eventually" alt="treetops seen from above"/><figcaption>Sure the trees will break my fall eventually</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>I spent the next hour or so lounging in the overlook between the Haystack and the gray jay crime haven, looking at flowers and appreciating the view.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/flowers.jpg" alt="Flower!"/></figure></p>
<p>Surely the view impresses even more on clear days, but clouds are familiar to me. A clear sky would have disoriented me.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/overlook.jpg" alt="View from the overlook"/></figure></p>
<p>A memorial marker placed at the overlook caught my eye.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/brett-marker.jpg" title="Memorial marker for Brett Hall 1962-1981" alt="memorial marker"/><figcaption>Memorial marker for Brett Hall 1962-1981</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Later I looked up the name on the marker, and found this nwhikers forum<a href="http://www.nwhikers.net/forums/viewtopic.php?p=202011&amp;sid=1b5ffb6683037d9488f2bbb5e5f4218b#202011">comment</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Brett Hall was from Lynnwood. His family used to live next door to mine. He disappeared on an intended dayhike on Mt Si with, I think, a group of friends. They searched at the time but didn’t find him; the assumption was that he took a tumble down a hill, or got disoriented, sat down and died of hypothermia. I’m not sure about the January 25th, 1981 date&ndash; or why they were hiking in the winter. (I was away at college at the time, so my info was secondhand.) If I recall, his body was found a year or so later after the snow melted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, yeah. Caution is smart even on small, popular mountains close to urban centers.</p>
<h2 id="heading-back">Heading back</h2>
<p>Once I rested enough — and my phone started running low on charge after so many pics — I headed back down the trail. Going down took less time than going up. Even so I took care, because those rocks in the path feel ever so solid when your feet are landing on them from above.</p>
<p>The sun came out when I was near the bottom of the mountain, and it was so gorgeous I felt the temptation to climb back up.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/sunshine.jpg" alt="Afternoon sun through trees and undergrowth"/></figure></p>
<p>My feet would have hated me. Besides, because of my timing, I got back to Seattle at exactly the right moment to get waved at on West Seattle Bridge by a trolley bus full of furries having their own special day! That was an awesome &ldquo;welcome home!&rdquo; moment.</p>
<h2 id="the-aftermath">The aftermath</h2>
<p>I wore better shoes than at <a href="/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/">Island Center Forest</a>, so my feet feel fine today. My knees got more work than usual, but at least I can walk without major discomfort.</p>
<p>One thing is for sure: next time I go walking up a mountain, I bring my
<em>inbox/Knitting</em>!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Island Center Forest</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/</guid>
  <description>Island Center Forest contains roughly ten miles of trails. I walked about six of them yesterday. Today my feet hurt.
Getting There Island Center Forest is a 363 acre wooded nature preserve in the middle of Vashon Island, which is a short ferry ride from West Seattle. I skipped the car for this trip, looking to save money on ferry fares.
I regretted that plan a little when I reached the island and noticed that route 118 only runs every hour and a half on Saturdays.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/island-center-forest">Island Center Forest</a> contains roughly ten miles of trails. I walked about six of them yesterday. Today my feet hurt.</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-19.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-19.jpg"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="getting-there">Getting There</h2>
<p>Island Center Forest is a 363 acre wooded nature preserve in the middle of <a href="http://www.vashonchamber.com/">Vashon Island</a>, which is a short ferry ride from West Seattle. I skipped the car for this trip, looking to save money on ferry fares.</p>
<p>I regretted that plan a <em>little</em> when I reached the island and noticed that <a href="https://www.kingcounty.gov/depts/transportation/metro/schedules-maps/118-119.aspx">route 118</a> only runs every hour and a half on Saturdays. No problem. I decided to walk until I reached something interesting. Lovely roads to drive on. Walking, maybe not so much. There was no sidewalk until I reached downtown Vashon about an hour after leaving the ferry terminal. Fortunately drivers were considerate as I negotiated the road shoulder on foot.</p>
<p>Found a grocery store in downtown Vashon and recharged with a snack while enjoying local art.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/art-cart.jpg" alt="Cool sketch on a cart. I missed the &lsquo;Trump/Putin 2016&rsquo; stickers until just now"/></figure></p>
<p>The park itself was only about five minutes&rsquo; walk from the store.</p>
<h2 id="my-path">My Path</h2>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/map.jpg" title="The trails I covered, more or less" alt="map"/><figcaption>The trails I covered, more or less</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>The trails have names, but there were fewer signs than I would have liked. Given the large number of trails to choose from, I set my plan as &ldquo;when in doubt, turn right.&rdquo; That kept me on the outer edge of the park. About halfway through I had a better feel for the park layout, and made more deliberate choices about my path.</p>
<h2 id="the-park-itself">The Park Itself</h2>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/mossy-trees.jpg" alt="Mossy trees and undergrowth"/></figure></p>
<p>This is a second-growth forest, moving from single-species tree plantations to a more diverse selection that provides better homes for wildlife and native growth. Trees provide pleasant shade throughout most of the park, which is good news for some of my friends who are sensitive to heat and sunlight.</p>
<p>Watch your step, though. You share these trails with horse riders, and droppings are a minor hazard underfoot.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/mukai-pond.jpg" alt="The southern bit of Mukai Pond"/></figure></p>
<p>I visited in the tail end of summer. As lovely as Mukai and Meadowlake ponds were, you could tell they were ready for rain. Still — there was something in Mukai Pond big enough to make a splash when I got too close.</p>
<p>Folks sometimes accuse me of getting lost in the weeds, getting so wrapped up in details that I miss the big picture. They have a point. I could stand to step back and look at the forest occasionally instead of the trees.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/fungus.jpg" alt="Look! Fungus!"/></figure></p>
<p>That said, these woods offered a wealth of details to keep my attention.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/cobwebs.jpg" alt="A spider neighborhood"/></figure></p>
<p>I picked Meadowlake Pond as the end of my circuit, enjoying the view and the strange calls of the local ravens that were having a grand time in the wetlands. Maybe the calls weren’t strange for ravens. I’m accustomed to crows. These corvids definitely had a range of noises to make, from a &ldquo;Mwa!&rdquo; that sounded like a strange cat to vaguely simian noises to a water drop sound.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/meadowlake-pond.jpg" alt="Meadowlake Pond"/></figure></p>
<h2 id="the-aftermath">The Aftermath</h2>
<p>I timed my return from downtown Vashon a little more carefully, catching the 118 bus to the ferry terminal. Much better.</p>
<p>I put my Fitbit back on for the day — I’ve been taking a little vacation from it the last week or so to minimize distractions — and managed to get myself some new badges:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;Trail Shoe&rdquo; for 30,000 steps in a day</li>
<li>&ldquo;Hiking Boot&rdquo; for 35,000 steps in a day</li>
<li>&ldquo;Skyscraper&rdquo; for 100 floors in a day</li>
</ul>
<p>16,000 or so of those steps were in the park itself, and pretty much all of those &ldquo;floors.&rdquo; It’s hardly mountain climbing, but there plenty of hills to cover. Anyways, back to my Fitbit vacation. My feet hurt and I won’t walk more than I must for the next couple days.</p>
<p>I enjoyed Island Center Forest, and particularly enjoyed getting out of Seattle for a day. I’m already deciding which park to make a day trip out of next time I feel the need to go sauntering.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Pearl Jam Tag</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/pearl-jam-tag/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/08/pearl-jam-tag/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Dog and I saw a &lt;a href=&#34;https://pearljam.com&#34;&gt;Pearl Jam&lt;/a&gt; logo tag while walking near &lt;a href=&#34;https://easystreetonline.com&#34;&gt;Easy Street Records&lt;/a&gt; this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-07.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-07.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>music</category>  <category>seen</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Dog and I saw a <a href="https://pearljam.com">Pearl Jam</a> logo tag while walking near <a href="https://easystreetonline.com">Easy Street Records</a> this morning.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-07.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-08-07.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Probably something to do with this sign right next to the tag.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/announce.jpg" title="Easy Street announcement for &#39;Pearl Jam Home Shows Aug 8 & 10&#39;" alt="Easy Street reader board"/><figcaption>Easy Street announcement for &#39;Pearl Jam Home Shows Aug 8 &amp; 10&#39;</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>All right, so what does the sign mean by &ldquo;Home Shows?&rdquo; At first I thought it described some special in-store event, since Easy Street has associated with Pearl Jam for a while. Last year the business marked the band’s induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame by putting up a <a href="https://www.easystreetonline.com/NewsItem/6863">pop-up store</a> – a corner dedicated to the band’s music and so on.</p>
<p>Oh good. I found <a href="https://pearljam.com/thehomeshows/seattle-wa">an explanation</a> on the band’s site:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of us grew up here. Over the past 28 years, the City of Seattle’s population has grown by 40%. The region’s homelessness population is now the third largest in the country, with over 12,000 people living without shelter on any one night. This is not a number to be proud of.</p>
<p>As part of The Home Shows Initiative, more than 140 businesses, individuals, government agencies, and foundations are banding together to fight homelessness in King County. Join us. Take action and learn more about this crisis.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Nice. I knew Pearl Jam involved themselves in local homelessness issues — they <a href="http://www.marysplaceseattle.org/blog/thank-you-pearl-jam/">gave a donation</a> to <a href="http://www.marysplaceseattle.org">Mary’s Place</a> a few years back — but I forgot the name of their project.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;Home Shows&rdquo; that Easy Street Records is promoting are at Safeco Field, and unfortunately the venue sold out. I guess not &ldquo;unfortunately&rdquo; since some of that money goes to support homeless people.</p>
<p>If you want to contribute to the Home Fund, you can always <a href="https://www.uwkc.org/home-show/">donate</a>, or make a special day of it by going out for food or beverages at a partner restaurant on Wednesday August 8, <a href="https://pearljam.com/acts/news/the-home-shows-restaurant-partners">Home Shows Restaurant Night</a>. As of the moment I write these words, that is tomorrow.</p>
<p>Anyways, yeah. I liked the tag. Dog had no opinion on the matter.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/tag.jpg" alt="close up of Pearl Jam logo tag"/></figure></p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Fauntleroy Park</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/fauntleroy-park/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/07/fauntleroy-park/</guid>
  <description>Today I explored Fauntleroy Park, a 28 acre park in West Seattle with some nice trails.
Years ago, I had a regular habit of exploring local parks and trails. Not hiking, mind you. Ugh. That sounds too purposeful for a person like me. No, sauntering. I just wanted to wander around, seeing what interests me, and enjoying the little differences each park offered.
You know what? It’s past time to start that habit back up.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>sauntering</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I explored <a href="http://fauntleroywatershed.org/">Fauntleroy Park</a>, a 28 acre park in West Seattle with some nice trails.</p>
<!-- more -->
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-08.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-07-08.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>Years ago, I had a regular habit of exploring local parks and trails. Not <em>hiking</em>, mind you. Ugh. That sounds too purposeful for a person like me. No, <a href="/tags/sauntering">sauntering</a>. I just wanted to wander around, seeing what interests me, and enjoying the little differences each park offered.</p>
<p>You know what? It’s past time to start that habit back up.</p>
<p>Fauntleroy Park is smaller than nearby <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/lincoln-park">Lincoln Park</a>, but I wanted someplace new to me.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/stairs.jpg" alt="stairs leading uphill"/></figure></p>
<p>I enjoyed following the park’s trails. Green, lush, and very local. <a href="http://www.nwplants.com/business/catalog/pol_mun.html">Sword ferns</a> everywhere! It left me feeling a bit nostalgic for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Green_belt">green belts</a> that have been steadily disappearing from the Pacific Northwest as we make room for more people.</p>
<p>The city is unavoidable. I could hear traffic at every point in the park. I found myself accidentally outside the park a few times in my brief visit. If you’re not careful some of the smaller trails will lead you to someone’s back yard. That makes me even more impressed by how much work has gone into maintaining the watershed in the middle of a busy city’s residential neighborhoods. Volunteers and students maintain the space, keeping it safe for salmon spawning, barred owls, and other critters.</p>
<p>And if you give nature half a chance, things start growing absolutely any place they can.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2018/tree-roots.jpg" alt="trees growing from a decaying collapsed tree trunk"/></figure></p>
<p>Still – I think next time I may want to venture a little further out. Seattle has many parks and trails, but I have visited the longer trails within the city many times over the years. The <a href="https://www.wta.org/">Washington Trails Association</a> provides resources for the aspiring saunterer, including an <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-outside/map">interactive map</a> of trails across Washington State.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
