<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>rustonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/rust/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinrust on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 22:40:56 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/rust/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: From Perl to Rust</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/10/from-perl-to-rust/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 22:40:56 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2022/10/from-perl-to-rust/</guid>
  <description>In Tim Heaney’s introduction to From Perl to Rust:
Having to know everything at once makes it hard to teach Rust as well. It seems like no matter where we start, we are always touching on concepts that we haven’t covered yet. This is quite the opposite of Perl, where it’s fairly easy to learn as we go. But perhaps making this one assumption— that we all know Perl— will help us navigate the complexities of Rust.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>rust</category>  <category>perl</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In Tim Heaney&rsquo;s introduction to <a href="https://oylenshpeegul.gitlab.io/from-perl-to-rust/introduction.html">From Perl to Rust</a>:</p>
<figure class="border-primary border-left pl-9 container-9 centered">
  <blockquote
    >
<p>Having to know everything at once makes it hard to teach Rust as well. It seems like no matter where we start, we are always touching on concepts that we haven&rsquo;t covered yet. This is quite the opposite of Perl, where it&rsquo;s fairly easy to learn as we go. But perhaps making this one assumption&mdash; that we all know Perl&mdash; will help us navigate the complexities of Rust. I don&rsquo;t know if this is going to work, but I thought I&rsquo;d try it.</p>
  </blockquote></figure>
<p>Not everybody knows <a href="/card/perl/">Perl</a>, but I do. I am very much the target audience for this title. We&rsquo;ll just throw it on the TOREAD stack with the others. But maybe I might read it before some of those others?</p>
<p>I <em>really</em> want to get a better grasp on <a href="/card/rust/">Rust</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
