<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>cultureonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/culture/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinculture on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Cory Doctorow on the split appeal of tech</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/cory-doctorow-on-the-split-appeal-of-tech/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/cory-doctorow-on-the-split-appeal-of-tech/</guid>
  <description>For many technologists, the allure of digital tools is the possibility of emancipation, a world where we can collaborate to make things without bosses or masters. But for the bosses and masters, automation’s allure is the possibility of getting rid of workers, shattering their power, and replacing them with meeker, cheaper, more easily replaced labor.
— Cory Doctorow, Pluralistic: Mass tech worker layoffs and the soft landing (21 Mar 2023) That is one depressing truth.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>quotes</category>  <category>culture</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<figure class="border-primary border-left pl-9 container-9 centered">
  <blockquote
    cite="#ZgotmplZ">
<p>For many technologists, the allure of digital tools is the possibility of emancipation, a world where we can collaborate to make things without bosses or masters. But for the bosses and masters, automation&rsquo;s allure is the possibility of getting rid of workers, shattering their power, and replacing them with meeker, cheaper, more easily replaced labor.</p>
  </blockquote><figcaption class="align-right">
    &mdash;
    Cory Doctorow, <a href="#ZgotmplZ">Pluralistic: Mass tech worker layoffs and the soft landing (21 Mar 2023)</a>
  </figcaption></figure>
<p>That is one depressing truth. This split has had a dampening effect on the enthusiasm of my latest job hunt. But on the bright side:</p>
<figure class="border-primary border-left pl-9 container-9 centered">
  <blockquote
    >
<p>That means that workers who go from tech firms to firms in the real economy might be getting lucky – escaping the grasp of bosses who dream of a world where technology lets them pit workers against each other in a race to the bottom on wages, benefits and working conditions, to employers who are glad to have them as partners in their drive to escape Big Tech&rsquo;s grasp.</p>
  </blockquote></figure>
<p>That also matches up to what I&rsquo;m seeing. The more interesting &ldquo;tech&rdquo; jobs for the last few years have been in automating and empowering <em>other</em> domains. Tech itself has been ever more obsessed with eliminating workers and making whoever&rsquo;s left dependent on them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
