<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>socksonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/socks/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinsocks on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/socks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Deidre&#39;s Double Moss Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/deidres-double-moss-socks/</guid>
  <description>blocked and ready to wear
Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!
The pattern Using Sensational Knitted Socks by Charlene Schurch, as usual. Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe moss stitch fallback.
The yarn brand Think Bamboo style B917 color 992 composition 45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon site https://thinkbamboo.com; doesn’t work for me at the moment The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I'm just glad I finished them</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-01.jpg"/></figure>
blocked and ready to wear</p>
<p>Took me six months to make these. It’s a good thing she likes them!</p>
<h2 id="the-pattern">The pattern</h2>
<p>Using <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/399836.Sensational_Knitted_Socks">Sensational Knitted Socks</a> by Charlene Schurch, as usual.
Been a while since I knitted any socks, so I went with a safe <a href="https://www.gathered.how/knitting-and-crochet/knitting/moss-stitch/">moss
stitch</a> fallback.</p>
<h2 id="the-yarn">The yarn</h2>
<dl>
<dt>brand</dt>
<dd>Think Bamboo</dd>
<dt>style</dt>
<dd>B917</dd>
<dt>color</dt>
<dd>992</dd>
<dt>composition</dt>
<dd>45% bamboo, 40% wool, 15% nylon</dd>
<dt>site</dt>
<dd><a href="https://thinkbamboo.com">https://thinkbamboo.com</a>; doesn&rsquo;t work for me at the moment</dd>
</dl>
<p>The yarn is pretty, and works nice once you get going.  It is beyond a hassle
to wind up, though.</p>
<h2 id="the-review">The review</h2>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Omg my beautiful handmade socks are so soft and a thing of BEAUTY <a href="https://t.co/cXmYHyI1CC">pic.twitter.com/cXmYHyI1CC</a></p>&mdash; Deidre Wisti (@IamMrsGeek) <a href="https://twitter.com/IamMrsGeek/status/1341594975629283328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 23, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Rainy&#39;s Mish-Mash Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/04/rainys-mish-mash-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/04/rainys-mish-mash-socks/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Some socks to go with &lt;a href=&#34;https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves/&#34;&gt;the gloves&lt;/a&gt; I made a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Some socks to go with <a href="/post/2016/03/rainys-mish-mash-gloves/">the gloves</a> I made a few weeks ago.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-04-14.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-04-14.jpg"/></figure></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong></p>
<p>I know I know I&rsquo;ve been quiet. I haven&rsquo;t been lazy, though. Mostly work and knitting. Tonight I posted the three knit projects finished since the last time I updated the site in January.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still have loads of yarn after making a pair of fingerless gloves for my friend. Asked if she wanted some long socks to match, and of course she said yes.</p>
<p>These go over the knee. I couldn&rsquo;t find any patterns I liked, so I improvised. They are regular toe-up socks until about four inches up, then I added two stitches  very
half inch until I had added an inch and a half, and knit straight from there. I used the next size smaller needle for the cuff to get a snug fit at the top. I have a tight gauge. You might add more stitches per increase or have more increases overall. If I can repeat this experiment I&rsquo;ll turn it into an actual pattern.</p>
<p>The patterns I found had one of two problems. Some were simply straight tubes, which would have been too tight around the calves. Others started adding stitches immediately after the heel, which results in what I consider a sloppy look between ankle and calf. I have no pictures for you yet, but that experiment worked out perfectly.</p>
<p>The only part that I wasn&rsquo;t fully satisfied with is that I bound off one sock just a little too tightly. Didn&rsquo;t realize it until she tried them on. However, it wasn&rsquo;t bound tight enough that I could convince her to relinquish the socks for me to fix it. Just something to remember next time.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Mom&#39;s Stansfield 12 Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/02/moms-stansfield-12-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/02/moms-stansfield-12-socks/</guid>
  <description>After more than ten years knitting, I finally had enough confidence in my ability to make something for Mom.
This time I blocked the socks flat, and I think that helped them look better when I wrapped them up for shipping.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-02-07.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-02-07.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>After more than ten years knitting, I finally had enough confidence in my ability to make something for Mom.</p>
<p>This time I blocked the socks flat, and I think that helped them look better when I wrapped them up for shipping.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2016/moms-stansfield-socks-flat.jpg" alt="Socks flat blocked"/></figure></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: My Twin Rib Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/01/my-twin-rib-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2016/01/my-twin-rib-socks/</guid>
  <description>This is from Charlene Schurch’s book Sensational Knitted Socks. Nearly every sock I make is, to be honest. Great book. The yarn is Cascade Yarns Heritage Silk 5608 “Pine”. A single 100 gram hank served almost perfectly for my US size 10.5 feet. The amount of yarn left over (5 grams) is so small that it’s nearly a choking hazard.
I blocked these on sock hangers, but that made them look more lumpy.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Took me a couple months because I started a pair for my mom in the middle of making this pair.
</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-01-30.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2016/cover-2016-01-30.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>This is from Charlene Schurch’s book <em>Sensational Knitted Socks</em>. Nearly every sock I make is, to be honest. Great book. The yarn is <a href="http://www.cascadeyarns.com/cascade-HeritageSilk.htm">Cascade Yarns Heritage Silk</a> 5608 &ldquo;Pine&rdquo;. A single 100 gram hank served almost perfectly for my US size 10.5 feet. The amount of yarn left over (5 grams) is so small that it’s nearly a choking hazard.</p>
<p>I blocked these on sock hangers, but that made them look <em>more</em> lumpy. The socks are a little larger than the hangers. You can see where the corner of the hanger deformed them a bit at the top of the heel. I assume that will bounce back after wearing and washing. Still - future pairs will likely get blocked flat.</p>
<p>They look and feel great on my feet. For the first time I understand why my ex was always requesting more socks.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: My First Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/11/my-first-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/11/my-first-socks/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Not my first socks ever, of course. But there are many firsts in these socks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Not my first socks ever, of course. But there are many firsts in these socks.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2015/cover-2015-11-25.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2015/cover-2015-11-25.jpg"/></figure></p>
<ul>
<li>They&rsquo;re mine! The rest have been for other people.</li>
<li>toe-up</li>
<li><a href="http://www.doctorwhoscarf.com/s12.html">Judy&rsquo;s Magic cast-on</a></li>
<li>short-row heels</li>
<li>two different yarns (a black yarn and a self-striping brown, both 4-ply wool/poly by Regia)</li>
</ul>
<p>Mistakes were made. I&rsquo;m not sure whether it was due to gauge issues or bad math, but toe and heel ended up pointy. So these socks feel a little long when I wear them. Still nice if I don&rsquo;t wear them jogging. Lessons learned.</p>
<p>These semed to go faster than top-down socks with heel flaps.</p>
<p>I think my second pair will be simpler. Maybe just one type of yarn.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Amicable Socks</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/05/amicable-socks/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/05/amicable-socks/</guid>
  <description>They follow directions from Charlene Schurch’s Sensational Knitted Socks with “Woven Stitch” as the repeating pattern. I used Shoalwater Bay Bamboo/Merino yarn, which I purchased a couple years ago at the Seattle University District Street Fair.
That takes care of the technical details, more or less. What made this project interesting enough to blog about?
I Kept a Journal inbox/Knitting is detail work. You need to remember how many stitches you knitted, how many more you need to knit, and how far along the increases or decreases you are.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Because I made them for my ex, and we split on friendly terms</h2><p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2015/cover-2015-05-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2015/cover-2015-05-20.jpg"/></figure></p>
<p>They follow directions from Charlene Schurch’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/399836.Sensational_Knitted_Socks">Sensational Knitted Socks</a> with &ldquo;Woven Stitch&rdquo; as the repeating pattern. I used <a href="http://shoalwaterbayyarn.com/bamboo.html">Shoalwater Bay Bamboo/Merino yarn</a>, which I purchased a couple years ago at the Seattle University District Street Fair.</p>
<p>That takes care of the technical details, more or less. What made this project interesting enough to blog about?</p>
<h2 id="i-kept-a-journal">I Kept a Journal</h2>
<p><em>inbox/Knitting</em> is detail work. You need to remember how many stitches you knitted, how many more you need to knit, and how far along the increases or decreases you are. I usually handle this by counting stitches constantly, getting bored, and loathing the fact that people have two feet because it means I need to knit a <em>second</em> sock. I often take months to finish a single pair of socks. Knitting two at the same time just confused me more — though I plan to tackle that eventually.</p>
<p>I decided to log my work with the Amicable Socks. Part of that involved breaking down the generalized instructions into something specific for my chosen pattern.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2015/amicable-socks-logged.jpg" title="I knew I&#39;d find a use for my Moleskine eventually" alt="in-progress socks laid out on project page"/><figcaption>I knew I&#39;d find a use for my Moleskine eventually</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>I also marked off rows as I finished them. I pondered tracking individual stitches, but realized that would result in too much detail to be useful.</p>
<p>These socks took me six weeks to finish, significantly beating my previous record of 3 months. And that was with a week and a half of idle time while I worried about whether I had enough yarn to finish the pair.</p>
<p>Oh, about that.</p>
<h2 id="i-weighed-my-yarn">I Weighed My Yarn</h2>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/vmbrasseur">@vmbrasseur</a> suggested that I weigh my in-progress sock and the amount of remaining yarn, then compare the two weights.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2015/amicable-socks-weighed.jpg" title="The sock weighed 1.3 ounces" alt="sock laid flat, with remaining yarn on scale"/><figcaption>The sock weighed 1.3 ounces</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>It turns out I had plenty of yarn to finish the project. This knowledge kept me moving at a steady pace even when the yarn ball got alarmingly small.</p>
<h2 id="i-blocked-them-when-i-was-done">I Blocked Them When I Was Done</h2>
<p>Every knitting book I read tells me to block my projects, but I never did. These socks were special, though. I decided to block them.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/attachments/img/2015/amicable-socks-blocked.jpg" title="The important thing is the blocking, not me going crazy with filters." alt="finished socks on sock hangers"/><figcaption>The important thing is the blocking, not me going crazy with filters.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>The result amazed me. The stitch pattern pops out. The yarn feels soft and luxurious to the touch. The socks lay flat. I plan to block all of my future projects.</p>
<h2 id="what-next">What Next?</h2>
<p>Next I’m going to try something else new to me. I will make socks for myself. Never did that before. I’ll log. I’ll block. If I get nervous, I’ll weigh.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Brooke&#39;s Garter Rib Sock</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2010/01/brookes-garter-rib-sock/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2010 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2010/01/brookes-garter-rib-sock/</guid>
  <description>Accidentally made one foot a little pointy. Rather than frog and fix, I just matched the error on the other side. Now instead of making a mistake, I added character.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Accidentally made one foot a little pointy. Rather than frog and fix, I just matched the error on the other side. Now instead of making a mistake, I added character.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2010/cover-2010-01-03.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2010/cover-2010-01-03.jpg"/></figure></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Brooke&#39;s Socks - Not Sarah&#39;s</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2009/02/brookes-socks-not-sarahs/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2009 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2009/02/brookes-socks-not-sarahs/</guid>
  <description>Made scads of mistakes, so I gave them to Brooke. She loved them.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>socks</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Made scads of mistakes, so I gave them to Brooke. She loved them.</p>
<p><figure>
    <img src="/../../../attachments/img/2009/cover-2009-02-13.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2009/cover-2009-02-13.jpg"/></figure></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
