<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>groomingonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/grooming/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentingrooming on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/grooming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Basic DIY Sea Salt Spray</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/10/basic-diy-sea-salt-spray/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2019/10/basic-diy-sea-salt-spray/</guid>
  <description>Sea salt, argan oil, and a spray bottle. You need water too.
tl;dr:
Heat a cup of water. Mix in 2 teaspoons argan oil, 1 tablespoon sea salt, and a few drops of something pretty. Let it cool. Shake before each use.
The recipe Get ingredients at your favorite local market or evil online megacorporation!
Ingredients Sea salt 1 Argan oil 2 Spray bottle 3 Funnel Maybe a whisk Kettle or other means of making cold water hot Extras That’s pretty much all you need.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>diy</category>  <category>recipe</category>  <category>grooming</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>In which I write a hair spray recipe and *then* share the story</h2><p><img src="/post/2019/10/../../../attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-10-21.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2019/cover-2019-10-21.jpg"/>
Sea salt, argan oil, and a spray bottle. You need water too.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>tl;dr:</strong></p>
<p>Heat a cup of water. Mix in 2 teaspoons argan oil, 1 tablespoon sea salt, and a few drops of something pretty. Let it cool. Shake before each use.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="the-recipe">The recipe</h2>
<p>Get ingredients at your favorite local market or evil online megacorporation!</p>
<h3 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h3>
<ul>
<li>Sea salt <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></li>
<li>Argan oil <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></li>
<li>Spray bottle <sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup></li>
<li>Funnel</li>
<li>Maybe a whisk</li>
<li>Kettle or other means of making cold water hot</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="extras">Extras</h3>
<p>That’s pretty much all you <em>need</em>. You’re free to add more!</p>
<ul>
<li>tea tree, sandalwood, or some other essential oil with a smell that pleases you</li>
<li>hair gel or coconut oil — for additional hold</li>
<li>epsom salt — for magnesium, I guess?</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="instructions">Instructions</h3>
<ol>
<li>Heat some water in the kettle. If it boils, let it cool a moment. You don’t want your first hairspray story to involve burn treatment.</li>
<li>Measure out one cup (roughly 250 ml) of hot water</li>
<li>Whisk in 2 teaspoons of oil. You can vary this a bit more or less depending on how dry your hair gets.</li>
<li>Whisk in a tablespoon of sea salt. A little more gives more hold, but careful to avoid crusty hair!</li>
<li>If you want your hair to smell nice, whisk in a few drops of essential oil.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup></li>
<li>Pour your mix into the spray bottle with a funnel, unless you have very steady hands!</li>
<li>Let it cool to room temperature or at least until there’s no risk of burns.</li>
<li>Shake vigorously before each use!</li>
</ol>
<p>One batch lasts me over a month of daily use, but I intentionally go for a lighter hold. Out of my face and roughly pointed in the right direction is all I care about.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2019/10/attachments/img/2019/me.jpg" alt="Still roughly pointed in the right direction halfway through the day"/></p>
<h2 id="the-story">The story</h2>
<p>Now that the recipe is out of the way — I thought cookbooks were bad about forcing you to read a long story before giving you their instructions. Cookbooks are nothing. Those self-care blogs are <em>awful</em>. An evening searching and I couldn’t find the source for the basic recipe I’ve been using over the last year or so because I couldn’t get through all the <em>stories</em>.</p>
<p>I had this big story in mind about how I was watching a beard care video one night and they said &ldquo;use sea salt spray! It’s good on your hair!&rdquo; and I said &ldquo;okay!&rdquo; and they said &ldquo;use <em>our</em> sea salt spray!&rdquo; and I said &ldquo;at that price? H*ck no!&rdquo; I was even going to work in some <a href="/card/perl/">card/Perl</a> references. Talk about how making your own hair spray is another application of <a href="http://threevirtues.com/">The Three Virtues</a>.</p>
<p>But I got bored just writing the outline for that particular story. Now it’s a year later, and I’m writing down the recipe somewhere permanent to avoid losing it again.</p>
<p>Look around for ideas from other recipes, but take what you read with a grain of sea salt. We’re here for mad science and saving money, not Clean Living or Purity Of Essence.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iyj_D2ivwS4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>This recipe is what I came up with last night after giving up on my search. You can find many recipes with varying ingredients and proportions. Experiment. Figure out what works for you.</p>
<p>Then write it down somewhere so you aren’t making something up again when you run out.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Update</strong></p>
<p>I found the recipe I started with! <a href="https://www.gimmesomeoven.com/diy/diy-sea-salt-texturizing-hair-spray/">Gimme Some Oven</a> has the information you need. Not much different than what you’ll find here, though with less Dr. Strangelove.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p></p>
&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
