<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>quotesonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/quotes/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentinquotes on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/quotes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Cory Doctorow on the split appeal of tech</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/cory-doctorow-on-the-split-appeal-of-tech/</link>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/cory-doctorow-on-the-split-appeal-of-tech/</guid>
  <description>{% quote( from=“Cory Doctorow” cite=&#34;https://pluralistic.net/2023/03/21/tech-workers/#sharpen-your-blades-boys&#34; title=“Pluralistic: Mass tech worker layoffs and the soft landing (21 Mar 2023)” ) %}
For many technologists, the allure of digital tools is the possibility of emancipation, a world where we can collaborate to make things without bosses or masters. But for the bosses and masters, automation’s allure is the possibility of getting rid of workers, shattering their power, and replacing them with meeker, cheaper, more easily replaced labor.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>quotes</category>  <category>culture</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>{% quote(
from=&ldquo;Cory Doctorow&rdquo;
cite=&quot;<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2023/03/21/tech-workers/#sharpen-your-blades-boys">https://pluralistic.net/2023/03/21/tech-workers/#sharpen-your-blades-boys</a>&quot;
title=&ldquo;Pluralistic: Mass tech worker layoffs and the soft landing (21 Mar 2023)&rdquo;
) %}</p>
<p>For many technologists, the allure of digital tools is the possibility of emancipation, a world where we can collaborate to make things without bosses or masters. But for the bosses and masters, automation&rsquo;s allure is the possibility of getting rid of workers, shattering their power, and replacing them with meeker, cheaper, more easily replaced labor.</p>
<p>{% end %}</p>
<p>That is one depressing truth. This split has had a dampening effect on the enthusiasm of my latest job hunt. But on the bright side:</p>
<p>{% quote() %}
That means that workers who go from tech firms to firms in the real economy might be getting lucky – escaping the grasp of bosses who dream of a world where technology lets them pit workers against each other in a race to the bottom on wages, benefits and working conditions, to employers who are glad to have them as partners in their drive to escape Big Tech&rsquo;s grasp.
{% end %}</p>
<p>That also matches up to what I&rsquo;m seeing. The more interesting &ldquo;tech&rdquo; jobs for
the last few years have been in automating and empowering <em>other</em> domains. Tech
itself has been ever more obsessed with eliminating workers and making whoever&rsquo;s left dependent on them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Elf Sternberg on how SSG is not a reaction</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/elf-sternberg-on-how-ssg-is-not-a-reaction/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2023/03/elf-sternberg-on-how-ssg-is-not-a-reaction/</guid>
  <description>{% quote( cite=&#34;https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/&#34; from=“Elf Sternberg” title=“Static site generation is not a ‘reaction’ to client-site rendering” ) %} It was literally the first thing we did. {% end %}
Strong agree. I’ve heard variations on static site generators being something invented after SPAs turned out to be a less than universal solution. Sounds like Elf’s start was with Muse — an Emacs tool that I heard of but never played with.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>quotes</category>  <category>ssg</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>{% quote(
cite=&quot;<a href="https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/">https://elfsternberg.com/blog/static-site-generation/</a>&quot;
from=&ldquo;Elf Sternberg&rdquo;
title=&ldquo;Static site generation is not a &lsquo;reaction&rsquo; to client-site rendering&rdquo;
) %}
It was literally the first thing we did.
{% end %}</p>
<p>Strong agree. I&rsquo;ve heard variations on static site generators being something invented after SPAs turned out to be a less than universal solution. Sounds like Elf&rsquo;s start was with <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs-muse/index.html">Muse</a> — an Emacs tool that I heard of but never played with.</p>
<p>I showed up onto the Internet a few years later, so I had a few site-generating frameworks to choose from. <a href="http://webmake.taint.org">WebMake</a> built my site for a couple years. What was that other one? Oh that&rsquo;s right! Engelschall&rsquo;s <a href="https://thewml.github.io/about/">WML</a>! That was fun too.</p>
<p>Oh, and my first interesting project was converting Vim&rsquo;s text documentation to usable HTML. I had a better version at some point, but <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20020422015833/http://www.coolnamehere.com/vim/vimdoc/help.html">this</a> was what I found with the Wayback Machine.</p>
<p>Anyways, there&rsquo;s also some good points in there about &ldquo;the eternal amnesia.&rdquo; That&rsquo;s one name for — basically, when folks have no foundational context. They think they&rsquo;re the first ones to think about some issue that was addressed in 1999, or 1968, or ~260 BCE.</p>
<p>{% quote() %}
The Eternal Amnesia is a consequence of how programming works&hellip; it encourages programmers to fill their brains with the sort of intellectual puzzle solving that used to be left to the rare professional mathematician, but without giving us the time to write it all down and explain how it works to other people.
{% end %}</p>
<p>No time to write it and not much time to read it, either. The kind of thoughtful effort it takes to build your context runs counter to the whole &ldquo;if you got time to lean, you got time to clean&rdquo; rut we call a work ethic.</p>
<p>Except we don&rsquo;t really clean either. You know — technical debt? That tag for 90% of the items in your ticket backlog? The backlog that&rsquo;ll last longer than your job?</p>
<p>Anyways. Yeah. Static site generation has been around for a bit.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Fred Brooks was right</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/07/fred-brooks-was-right/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 08:30:19 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/07/fred-brooks-was-right/</guid>
  <description>Fred Brooks, The Mythical Man-Month
Show me your flowcharts and conceal your tables, and I shall continue to be mystified. Show me your tables, and I won’t usually need your flowcharts; they’ll be obvious.
That line’s been in my head since yesterday for boring work reasons. The important part is thank goodness for SQL files. The ones I can understand, anyways.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>quotes</category>  <category>software-architecture</category>  <category>show-me-the-tables</category>  <category>old-reference-is-old</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Fred Brooks, <a href="https://archive.org/details/MythicalManMonth">The Mythical Man-Month</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Show me your flowcharts and conceal your tables, and I shall continue to be mystified. Show me your tables, and I won&rsquo;t usually need your flowcharts; they&rsquo;ll be obvious.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That line&rsquo;s been in my head since yesterday for boring work reasons. The important part is thank goodness for SQL files. The ones I can understand, anyways.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
