<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>editorsonRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/tags/editors/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentineditors on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 08:55:27 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/tags/editors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Looks like Sublime Text is shifting to a subscription plan</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/looks-like-sublime-text-is-shifting-to-a-subscription-plan/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 08:55:27 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2021/01/looks-like-sublime-text-is-shifting-to-a-subscription-plan/</guid>
  <description>Yesterday’s dev build plus A File Icon
Terence Martin posted a couple helpful videos explaining version licensing and the impending changes to the Sublime Text text editor, along with some tips on getting started with “version 4.” So nice I watched them twice.
A real subscription, where you get to keep the builds you paid for. I like this.
Okay, sure. Sublime Text isn’t open source. Version releases are few and far between.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>editors</category>  <category>sublime-text</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Found via my quarterly "Sublime Text 4" web search</h2><p><img src="/post/2021/01/../../../attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-30.png" alt="attachments/img/2021/cover-2021-01-30.png"/>
Yesterday&rsquo;s dev build plus <a href="https://packagecontrol.io/packages/A%20File%20Icon">A File Icon</a></p>
<p><a href="https://odatnurd.net">Terence Martin</a> posted a couple helpful videos <a href="https://youtu.be/P52ZBQvAAsU">explaining</a> version licensing and the impending changes to the <a href="https://www.sublimetext.com">Sublime Text</a> text editor, along with some tips on <a href="https://youtu.be/_HoltQwvF2o">getting started</a> with &ldquo;version 4.&rdquo; So nice I watched them twice.</p>
<p>A real subscription, where you get to keep the builds you paid for.  I like this.</p>
<p>Okay, sure.  Sublime Text isn’t open source.  Version releases are few and far between. But it’s <em>good</em> — the only graphical text editor I’ve used that feels as responsive as <a href="/card/vim/">card/Vim</a>.</p>
<p>I love supporting independent development when I can.  A subscription approach is more sustainable for developers and more satisfying for users than the (extremely) intermittent bursts of version-based licensing.  There’s nothing official, so I don’t know what’s really happening.  The <a href="https://discord.gg/HcmwdVK">Sublime Discord</a> &ldquo;announcements&rdquo; channel holds the details.</p>
<p>Python 3.8.6. Good stuff!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Found the micro editor</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/11/found-the-micro-editor/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 20:41:49 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/11/found-the-micro-editor/</guid>
  <description>micro — apparently it’s like nano but bigger.
OMG I hit C-v and it pasted the link. Just like that. Then I dragged that filemanager divider over with my mouse and it worked.
A shell text editor? With key bindings that make sense to people who haven’t had their brains warped by Unix? With window splitting and tabs and JSON configuration and Lua plugins? I’m so confused.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>editors</category>  <category>shell</category>  <category>life-doesn-t-have-to-be-hard</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2020/11/../../../attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-11-30.png" alt="attachments/img/2020/cover-2020-11-30.png"/></p>
<p><a href="https://micro-editor.github.io/">micro</a> — apparently it&rsquo;s like <code>nano</code> but bigger.</p>
<p>OMG I hit <code>C-v</code> and it pasted the link. Just like that. Then I dragged that <a href="https://github.com/NicolaiSoeborg/filemanager-plugin">filemanager</a> divider over with my <em>mouse</em> and it worked.</p>
<p>A shell text editor? With key bindings that make sense to people who haven&rsquo;t had their brains warped by Unix? With window splitting and tabs and JSON configuration and Lua plugins? I&rsquo;m so confused.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: VS Code pylint needs pylintrc</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/vs-code-pylint-needs-pylintrc/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 10:15:30 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2020/03/vs-code-pylint-needs-pylintrc/</guid>
  <description>Visual Studio Code doesn’t seem to pick up my environment’s PYTHONPATH when running pylint. Makes project-local modules a headache. The solution: put it in your pylint config.
${workspaceFolder}/.pylintrc
[MASTER] init-hook=&#39;import sys; sys.path.append(&#34;pylib&#34;)&#39; Okay, I got more planned for today than messing with code. Back to that other stuff.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>note</category> 
   <category>python</category>  <category>vscode</category>  <category>editors</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/">Visual Studio Code</a> doesn’t seem to pick up my environment’s <a href="https://docs.python.org/3.8/using/cmdline.html#envvar-PYTHONPATH">PYTHONPATH</a> when running <a href="https://www.pylint.org/">pylint</a>. Makes project-local modules a headache. The solution: put it in your pylint config.</p>
<p><strong><code>${workspaceFolder}/.pylintrc</code></strong></p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-ini" data-lang="ini"><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="k">[MASTER]</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="na">init-hook</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">&#39;import sys; sys.path.append(&#34;pylib&#34;)&#39;</span></span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>Okay, I got more planned for today than messing with code. Back to that other stuff.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Remote Editing In Atom</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/07/remote-editing-in-atom/</link>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2015/07/remote-editing-in-atom/</guid>
  <description>I am slowly learning more about how to use Atom for real work. First requirement: my “real work” almost exclusively takes place on a virtual machine. Atom alone cannot handle editing those files. remote-atom to the rescue!
Well, sort of. It’s not as reflexive as bouncing around in a Vim session, but some of that must be due to lack of familiarity.
It works, though.
You can install the remote-atom package from Atom’s Settings View.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>atom-editor</category>  <category>editors</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I am slowly learning more about how to use Atom for real work.</h2><p>I am slowly learning more about how to use <a href="https://atom.io">Atom</a> for real work. First requirement: my &ldquo;real work&rdquo; almost exclusively takes place on a virtual machine. Atom alone cannot handle editing those files. <a href="https://atom.io/packages/remote-atom">remote-atom</a> to the rescue!</p>
<p>Well, sort of. It’s not as reflexive as bouncing around in a <a href="/card/vim/">Vim</a> session, but some of that must be due to lack of familiarity.</p>
<p>It works, though.</p>
<p>You can install the remote-atom package from Atom’s <a href="https://atom.io/packages/settings-view">Settings View</a>. Follow the directions on the <a href="https://atom.io/packages/remote-atom">remote-atom</a> package page! You’ll end up with an <code>rmate</code> executable on your virtual machine, corresponding to a <a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/aurora/rmate/master/rmate">master copy</a> in the remote-atom git repo.</p>
<p><code>rmate</code> communicates with the Remote Atom service, which you need to manage yourself. You can do this from the <em>Packages</em> menu, but I want to get comfortable with the <a href="https://atom.io/packages/command-palette">Command Palette</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2015/07/attachments/img/2015/remote-atom-start-server.png" alt="Start Remote Atom Server from Command Palette"/></p>
<p>Once the server is available, you can <code>rmate</code> files to your heart’s content.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ rmate lib/secret-work-stuff
$ rmate test/secret-work-tests</code></pre>
</figure><p>No point showing a screenshot of <code>lib/secret-work-stuff</code>. It’s just another tab as far as the Atom user interface is concerned. Saving correctly updated the file on my virtual machine. Simple and straightforward.</p>
<p>Eventually you may want to stop the server. Again, from the Command Palette.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2015/07/attachments/img/2015/remote-atom-stop-server.png" alt="Stop Server from the Command Palette"/></p>
<p>I’m still not ready to use Atom as my primary or even secondary editor. However, it’s starting to feel useful — thanks to packages like remote-atom.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Sticking with Vim</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2006/02/sticking-with-vim/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2006/02/sticking-with-vim/</guid>
  <description>I’ve been experimenting with several excellent editors for Windows, including UltraEdit and Crimson Editor. The experiments will continue, but for now I am going to stick to a Windows install of Vim. Becoming familiar with Windows doesn’t mean I have to drop everything I already know in the dust!</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>43-things</category>  <category>vim</category>  <category>editors</category>  <category>blogspot</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been experimenting with several excellent editors for Windows, including <a href="http://www.ultraedit.com">UltraEdit</a> and <a href="http://www.crimsoneditor.com">Crimson Editor</a>. The experiments will continue, but for now I am going to stick to a Windows install of <a href="/card/vim/">Vim</a>. Becoming familiar with Windows doesn&rsquo;t mean I have to drop everything I already know in the dust!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Editors</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2001/07/editors/</link>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jul 2001 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2001/07/editors/</guid>
  <description>Choose your weapon As a geek, your text editor is your most important tool. Pick one or two, and really get to know it. I don’t care if you choose Emacs, vi, SciTE, or whatever else. Pick it and learn how to use it. I want you to really get the hang of your editing environment. Being more skilled with your tools will make it easier for you to get work done.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>editors</category>  <category>coolnamehere</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="choose-your-weapon">Choose your weapon</h2>
<p>As a geek, your text editor is your most important tool. Pick one or two, and really get to know it. I don’t care if you choose Emacs, vi, SciTE, or whatever else. Pick it and learn how to use it. I want you to <em>really</em> get the hang of your editing environment. Being more skilled with your tools will make it easier for you to get work done. And geek play, of course.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
