<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>2018onRandom Geekery</title>
    <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/</link>
    <description>
      Recent contentin2018 on Random Geekery
    </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      
      <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 22:42:33 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
  <title>Post: Hopepunk for 2019</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</link>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/hopepunk-for-2019/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Writing these late night thoughts is as close as I get to making resolutions.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/12/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-31.jpg"/></p>
<p>Lots of copying and pasting in this, since getting the words in full is important to me.</p>
<p>Tonight on Facebook, a friend shared a <a href="http://heartlessharless.tumblr.com/post/133490414240/alycs-being-unconditionally-polite-kind-and">Tumblr post</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Being unconditionally polite, kind, and compassionate in a society that values and finds “deeper meaning” in aloofness and cynicism is subversive and thus punk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>hufflepunk</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has been my own general philosophy. Best to make it explicit. Values fade if kept in the shadows.</p>
<p>Anyways, &ldquo;hufflepunk&rdquo; sounds an awful lot like <a href="https://ariaste.tumblr.com/post/163500138919/ariaste-the-opposite-of-grimdark-is-hopepunk">hopepunk</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The opposite of grimdark is hopepunk. Pass it on.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>#this is a good post #also I need an example of hopepunk #bc the name #resonates with me #and I need it
#please #if you don’t mind (via @-lavender-starling)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So the essence of grimdark is that everyone’s inherently sort of a bad person and does bad things, and that’s awful and disheartening and cynical. It’s looking at human nature and going, “The glass is half empty.”</p>
<p>Hopepunk says, “No, I don’t accept that. Go fuck yourself: The glass is half-full.”  YEAH, we’re all a messy mix of good and bad, flaws and virtues. We’ve all been mean and petty and cruel, but (and here’s the important part) we’ve also been soft and forgiving and KIND. Hopepunk says that kindness and softness doesn’t equal weakness, and that in this world of brutal cynicism and nihilism, being kind is a <em>political act</em>. An act of <em>rebellion.</em></p>
<p>Hopepunk says that <em>genuinely and sincerely</em> caring about something, anything, requires bravery and strength. Hopepunk isn’t ever about submission or acceptance: It’s about standing up and fighting for what you believe in. It’s about standing up for other people. It’s about DEMANDING a better, kinder world, and truly believing that we can get there if we care about each other as hard as we possibly can, with every drop of power in our little hearts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There&rsquo;s more, but I don&rsquo;t need to paste the <em>entire</em> post.</p>
<p>Looking up Hopepunk led me to <a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/12/27/18137571/what-is-hopepunk-noblebright-grimdark">this Vox article</a>, which does a fine job breaking it down so I don&rsquo;t have to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Through this framing, the idea of choosing hope becomes both an existential act that affirms your humanity, and a form of resistance against cynical worldviews that dismiss hope as a powerful force for change.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see, what other examples can I think of? Oh, I know: <a href="http://www.pbs.org/parents/rogers">Mister Rogers</a>. You could throw a dart at a wall of Fred Rogers quotes and anything it hit would be appropriate for hopepunk. The man fully understood the world he was speaking to.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some days, doing &ldquo;the best we can&rdquo; may still fall short of what we would like to be able to do, but life isn&rsquo;t perfect on any front — and doing what we can with what we have is the most we should expect of ourselves or
anyone else. — <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/895495">Fred Rogers</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The thing about all of these is that you don&rsquo;t expect the world to magically become a better place through your efforts. You do them because that&rsquo;s how things should be, and if we see someone stubbornly refusing to submit to cynicism, it might give us a little strength for our own efforts. If nothing else, we can sleep a little more easily with ourselves at night.</p>
<p>So I intend to be more explicitly this in 2019.</p>
<p>And — you know. If you don&rsquo;t like it, fuck off. I love you anyways.</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Active Tasks in Taskwarrior</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/active-tasks-in-taskwarrior/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/12/active-tasks-in-taskwarrior/</guid>
  <description>card/tldr
Use the start, stop, and active Taskwarrior commands to manage what you’re doing right now.
I use Taskwarrior’s priority system to show what I want to be working on now. What if there are several things I want to be working on right now? Even with my priority rules, I still find myself drawn to the lower priority tasks that are more interesting. Realistically, I can only do one thing at a time.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>taskwarrior</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/post/2018/12/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-01.png" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-12-01.png"/></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="/card/tldr/">card/tldr</a></strong></p>
<p>Use the <code>start</code>, <code>stop</code>, and <code>active</code> <a href="/card/taskwarrior/">Taskwarrior</a> commands to manage what you’re doing right now.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I use Taskwarrior’s <a href="/post/2017/12/taskwarrior-priorities/">priority</a> system to show what I want to be working on now. What if there are several things I want to be working on right now? Even with my priority rules, I still find myself drawn to the lower priority tasks that are more interesting. Realistically, I can only do one thing at a time. How do I remind myself which task should have my active attention?</p>
<h2 id="task-start"><code>task start</code></h2>
<p>Easy! Use the <code>start</code> command.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task 72 start</code></pre>
</figure><p>This assigns the virtual tag <code>+ACTIVE</code> to the task. The regular task report highlights active tasks, as well as showing a new &ldquo;Active&rdquo; column indicating how long the task has been active.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task

ID Active Age  P Project Tag              Description                       Urg
72 12min  1h   H         blog taskwarrior start, stop, and active           10.9
61        7d   H         crochet gift     crochet crown for mom             6.94
47        3mo  M         art              upload felix to dbh               5.35
35        6mo  L site    layout           add Year link to content headers  4.75
⋮</code></pre>
</figure><p>Being active increases the urgency of a task, bubbling it up to the top in this report. I can also request to see <em>only</em> the active tasks.</p>
<h2 id="task-active"><code>task active</code></h2>
<p>The <code>active</code> report shows me only those tasks that have been assigned the <code>+ACTIVE</code> virtual tag. Very handy in my blog <a href="/post/2018/02/taskwarrior-contexts/">context</a>, when many curious ideas are tugging at my easily distracted brain and I need to see just what I’m doing.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task active

ID Started    Active Age P Project Tag              Description                      Urg
72 2018-12-01 14min  1h  H         blog taskwarrior start, stop, and active          10.9</code></pre>
</figure><p>You can start as many tasks as you like. I find that distracting. Taskwarrior helps me focus, and starting a dozen different tasks feels like the opposite of focusing. I’ll limit <code>+ACTIVE</code> for <em>one</em> task that I intend to be working on <em>at this moment</em>.</p>
<h2 id="task-stop"><code>task stop</code></h2>
<p>I’m still writing this post, but I need to do something else real quick. I could just <code>start</code> that other task, but that blows a hole in my “one active task at a time” personal rule. Instead I’ll show that my attention is elsewhere with <code>stop</code>.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task 72 stop
Stopping task 72 &#39;start, stop, and active&#39;.
Stopped 1 task.</code></pre>
</figure><p>Okay excuse me for a few minutes.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task 73 start
Starting task 73 &#39;walk the dog&#39;.
Started 1 task.
⋮
$ task 73 done
Completed task 73 &#39;walk the dog&#39;.
Completed 1 task.
You have more urgent tasks.</code></pre>
</figure><p><em>You have more urgent tasks.</em> — Yeah, tell that to the dog.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task 72 start
Starting task 72 &#39;start, stop, and active&#39;.
Started 1 task.</code></pre>
</figure><p>Now where was I? Oh yeah. I wanted to mention time tracking.</p>
<h2 id="taskwarrior-is-not-for-time-tracking">Taskwarrior is not for time tracking</h2>
<p>Those <code>start</code> and <code>stop</code> commands show up in the task’s modification history, including timestamps and information about duration of active status.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ task 72
No command specified - assuming &#39;information&#39;.

Name          Value
ID            72
Description   start, stop, and active
Status        Pending
Entered       2018-12-01 12:27:44 (2h)
Start         2018-12-01 14:43:08
Last modified 2018-12-01 14:43:08 (17min)
Tags          blog taskwarrior
Virtual tags  ACTIVE PENDING READY TAGGED UDA UNBLOCKED PRIORITY
UUID          f5f87929-a4e8-4af4-bb38-cf142235f693
Urgency       10.9
Priority      H

    active              1 *    4 =      4
    tags              0.9 *    1 =    0.9
    UDA priority.H      1 *    6 =      6
                                   ------
                                     10.9

Date                Modification
2018-12-01 13:25:51 Priority changed from &#39;L&#39; to &#39;M&#39;.
2018-12-01 13:41:53 Priority changed from &#39;M&#39; to &#39;H&#39;.
2018-12-01 13:42:01 Start set to &#39;2018-12-01 13:42:01&#39;.
2018-12-01 13:59:06 Start deleted (duration: PT17M5S).
2018-12-01 14:43:08 Start set to &#39;2018-12-01 14:43:08&#39;.</code></pre>
</figure><p>Even though there are timestamps in the task info, this is clumsy for time tracking. The Taskwarrior team also wrote <a href="https://taskwarrior.org/docs/timewarrior">Timewarrior</a>, a command line tool dedicated to tracking and reporting time. It even hooks into Taskwarrior’s <code>start</code> and <code>stop</code> commands, giving you time management with your task management.</p>
<p>I may explore Timewarrior eventually, but for now I am content using Taskwarrior alone to show what I’ve done with <code>completed</code>, what I’m doing right now with today’s new commands, and what I want to do (with everything else).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Picot Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-picot-edge/</guid>
  <description>This hat is another round of the “basic hat” from Ann Budd’s The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from last time.
The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from A Treasury of Knitting Patterns. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I continue building my hat knitting knowledge!</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-20.jpg"/></p>
<p>This hat is another round of the &ldquo;basic hat&rdquo; from Ann Budd’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a>. This time I used a picot edge, which adds texture to the hemmed edge from <a href="/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/">last time</a>.</p>
<p>The picot edge was so satisfying that I decided to add a couple more new techniques. First was the Roman stitch on the hat body, which came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/129506.A_Treasury_of_Knitting_Patterns">A Treasury of Knitting Patterns</a>. The pattern instructions from the book are for knitting flat. I adapted them for knitting in the round.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Rows 1-4</dt>
<dd><code>K</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 5</dt>
<dd><code>K1,P1</code> to end</dd>
<dt>Row 6</dt>
<dd><code>P1,K1</code> to end</dd>
</dl>
<p>I wasn’t done with new stuff, though. I decided it was time for my first pom pom. Wandered off to YouTube to see the process in action.</p>
<p>I needed to see someone making a pom pom.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8ilFeg7dPIU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Finally, I realized I also needed to see someone attach a pom pom to a hat. The hat in the video is crochet, but the principle is the same.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/aiRQb5JkjzE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>After all that, the hat came out quite nice. It fit my head comfortably. The pom pom stays securely attached. The Roman Stitch feels nice when I rub my hands on the hat.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/modeling.jpg" alt="A much better fit"/></p>
<p>So naturally I’m taking the hat down to the post office tomorrow to ship off for a friend. Their head has the same circumference as mine. At this point, I worry less about the fate of my projects. I can make more.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Basic Hat With Hemmed Edge</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/basic-hat-with-hemmed-edge/</guid>
  <description>Ann Budd’s book The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her “Basic hat” template. The black wool hat I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.
What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a ribbed edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I made another hat! This time I learned how to make a hemmed edge.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/11/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-11-11.jpg"/></p>
<p>Ann Budd’s book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter’s Handy Book of Patterns</a> continues to teach me new techniques. This project is my second iteration of her &ldquo;Basic hat&rdquo; template. The black <a href="/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/">wool hat</a> I made a couple of weeks ago was the first.</p>
<p>What’s the difference? The wool hat — and most of the hats I have knitted until now — had a <a href="https://www.dummies.com/crafts/knitting/knitting-stitches/how-to-rib-stitch/">ribbed</a> edge. Alternating knit and purl stitches create a section more elastic than the body of the hat, so it hugs a bit closer to your head.</p>
<p>This hat uses a <a href="http://www.vogueknitting.com/pattern_help/how-to/beyond_the_basics/hems">hemmed</a> edge. Stockinette rows get folded over and stitched into the body of the hat. I like the smooth look a hemmed edge produces. The extra volume of the hem provides the snugness needed to keep your hat on your head.</p>
<p>Oh! This was also the first time I used my copy of <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13167139-the-handknitter-s-yarn-guide">The Handknitter’s Yarn Guide</a>! See, I had this mystery yarn in my stash. It was thick and self-striping, but that’s all I knew. No idea about the material, or what size needles I should be using. And let’s be honest, &ldquo;thick yarn&rdquo; is more than a little subjective. Some people <a href="https://youtu.be/FKw-pjwaXz8">knit with rope</a>, after all.</p>
<p>The Yarn Guide provides a reference of yarn textures and varieties, focused on details that are important for hand knitters. Machine knitters track somewhat different details. It includes nifty details like how a particular yarn material feels, or how it should burn — wool burns slow, acrylic goes up quick. It also describes <a href="https://www.craftyarncouncil.com/standards/how-measure-wraps-inch-wpi">wraps per inch</a> for establishing the weight of your yarn. &ldquo;Weight&rdquo; here is not about mass and gravity, but about expected gauge and needle size.</p>
<p>My 200 gram chunk of mystery self-striping yarn yielded eight and a half wraps per inch. A snip burned <em>quick</em>. This suggested I had a bulky acrylic, and should use size 13-15 (9-10mm) knitting needles.</p>
<p>Except I misread those numbers — three cheers for minor cognitive issues! — and ended up using size 9 (5.5mm) needles. Combine that with the fact that my flat knitting — such as what I used for the gauge swatch — produces a wildly different gauge from my knitting in the round, and. Well.</p>
<p>I made a <em>lovely</em> hat. A hat that was maybe a little too snug for a comfortable fit on my head.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/wearing-hat.jpg" title="The hat looks nice, but after a minute starts pinching my forehead" alt="me wearing the hat"/></p>
<p>That’s okay though. The hat fits a friend perfectly, and it’s heading home with them as I type.</p>
<p>For future projects, I will make my flat stockinette stitch match my round knitting gauge more closely. The main difference is in my purl stitch, which is looser than my knit stitch unless I pay close attention. When you knit in the round, purl stitches occur less often than when flat. That’s why those projects have a tighter gauge and tighter fit.</p>
<p>So far the hat I am knitting now has only a somewhat tighter gauge than the flat swatch. I <em>could</em> — maybe &ldquo;should?&rdquo; — also knit my gauge swatch in the round, but I’m not entirely confident that a gauge tube is what I need. We’ll see. But so far the current hat is the size I expected. That’s good enough for me.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Using Hugo Data Templates</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/using-hugo-data-templates/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/11/using-hugo-data-templates/</guid>
  <description>I put my frequently used links in a card/Hugo data template to cut down on copying and pasting between posts.
Motive I often create several inbox/Knitting or inbox/Crochet projects from the same book, or reference the same tutorial for a technique that I find tricky. Today, linking to those references in a post involves copying and pasting the URL from somewhere else – usually the blog post for a previous project.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>hugo</category>  <category>site</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I put my frequently used links in a <a href="/card/hugo/">card/Hugo</a> data template to cut down on copying and pasting between posts.</p>
<h2 id="motive">Motive</h2>
<p>I often create several <em>inbox/Knitting</em> or <em>inbox/Crochet</em> projects from the same book, or reference the same tutorial for a technique that I find tricky. Today, linking to
those references in a post involves copying and pasting the URL from
somewhere else – usually the blog post for a previous project. This is
tedious at best, and becomes downright troublesome if and when the link
for that reference changes.</p>
<p>Hugo <a href="https://gohugo.io/templates/data-templates/">data templates</a> could fix all that.</p>
<p>Data templates are written in <a href="/card/yaml/">card/YAML</a>, <a href="/card/toml/">card/TOML</a>, or <em>inbox/JSON</em> format and saved to your site’s <code>data</code> folder. Your data templates and their contents become available to Hugo via the <code>$.Site.Data</code> variable. Organize your data templates however you like, and make them as complex as you want.</p>
<h2 id="my-data-template-for-links">My data template for links</h2>
<p>Before getting carried away with visions of complex structures to meet my every desire, what do I need <em>right now</em>?</p>
<p>I need a glossary of links I can reference at any time. Its entries must provide what I consider the canonical resource URL for a book or topic. That’s it. I can revisit the glossary idea if my needs change later. So let’s start with the links I just used. I like to talk about YAML, TOML, and JSON sometimes, after all.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <figcaption><tt>data/links.toml</tt></figcaption>
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-toml" data-lang="toml"><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="c"># Frequently used URLs</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="nx">JSON</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">&#34;https://json.org/&#34;</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="nx">TOML</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">&#34;https://github.com/toml-lang/toml&#34;</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="nx">YAML</span> <span class="p">=</span> <span class="s2">&#34;http://yaml.org/&#34;</span></span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>The filename provides part of the data structure for Hugo. For example, the &ldquo;TOML&rdquo; entry in <code>data/links.toml</code> becomes <code>$.Site.Data.links.JSON</code>.</p>
<p>Nobody but me sees these keys – except right now, while I am telling <em>you</em> about them. Since they’re for me, it’s most important that I pick keys I can remember easily within the limitations of the data format. &ldquo;JSON&rdquo; works. &ldquo;TheJsonSpecificationSite&rdquo; probably would not. &ldquo;The JSON Site&rdquo; is a legal key in TOML, but in this case not a helpful one.</p>
<h2 id="getting-the-data-from-my-template">Getting the data from my template</h2>
<p>How do I <em>use</em> these URLs? With a <a href="https://gohugo.io/templates/shortcode-templates/">shortcode</a>! Again, focusing on exactly what I need right now: the URL in <code>$.Site.Data.links</code> corresponding to a key.</p>
<p><code>layouts/shortcodes/linkFor.html</code> provides just that. It uses its first positional argument as a key, returning the value at that <a href="https://gohugo.io/functions/index-function/">index</a> in the glossary.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-html" data-lang="html"><span class="line"><span class="cl">{{- with .Get 0 -}}{{ index $.Site.Data.links . }}{{- end -}}</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>Then in my content Markdown:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-md" data-lang="md"><span class="line"><span class="cl">[<span class="nt">TOML</span>](<span class="na">{{&lt; linkFor &#34;TOML&#34; &gt;}}</span>)</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>That’s <em>almost</em> everything I need. I should throw in error checking for inevitable typos such as the one I made a couple minutes ago.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-md" data-lang="md"><span class="line"><span class="cl">[<span class="nt">TOML</span>](<span class="na">{{&lt; linkFor &#34;YOML&#34; &gt;}}</span>)</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>I don’t need anything fancy, but I do need something to tell me if there’s a problem. The system quietly returns nothing if there is no entry for the key. I would hate to have empty links all over my site due to a lazily written shortcode.</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >{{- with .Get 0 -}}
   {{- $url := index $.Site.Data.links . -}}
   {{- if $url -}}
       {{- $url -}}
   {{- else -}}
       {{- errorf &#34;No link for key %s&#34; . -}}
   {{- end -}}
{{- end -}}</code></pre>
</figure><p>Now I get an error both on the console and in the browser:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0"
    ><code class="language-" data-lang=""
      >$ hugo server -D
Building sites … ERROR 2018/11/10 15:53:14 No link for key YOML
Total in 1389 ms
Error: Error building site: logged 1 error(s)</code></pre>
</figure><p><img src="/post/2018/11/attachments/img/2018/error-screenshot.png" alt="Hugo shows the error in-browser"/></p>
<p>This provides what I need for today.</p>
<h2 id="other-thoughts">Other thoughts?</h2>
<ul>
<li>When do I put a link in the data template? Like so many things in life, it depends. Sometimes I’ll want to add it immediately. Other times I have the URL practically memorized.</li>
<li>I’ll probably need to keep that <code>data/links.toml</code> handy when writing a post, since the keys will get harder to remember.</li>
<li>I could have used a Params entry in the site’s <code>config.toml</code>, but keeping the glossary in its own file keeps the configuration from getting cluttered.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Winter Hat and Gloves</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</link>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/winter-hat-and-gloves/</guid>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>knitting</category>  <category>hat</category>  <category>gloves</category>  <category>craft</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I made  myself a hat and gloves in matching colors for winter.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-27.jpg"/></p>
<p>The gloves use the same <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/170305.Son_of_Stitch_n_Bitch">Son of Stitch &rsquo;n Bitch</a> pattern as the <a href="/post/2018/08/beer-gloves/">purple beer gloves</a> I knitted this summer. This pair turned out much better. Learning through repetition! However, that Loops &amp; Threads &ldquo;Impeccable&rdquo; yarn is far too stiff for gloves. I would prefer a sportweight blend to this worsted weight acrylic for things that need to move with my hands.</p>
<p>I lost the label for the hat yarn but it&rsquo;s probably Patons North America Classic Wool Worsted. So soft and cozy on my head. I accidentally changed tension once I picked up speed, resulting in an interesting gauge effect along the bottom ribbing, but that is already becoming less pronounced with wear. You can also see twisted stiches where I recovered a row but mounted those stitches incorrectly. This happened plenty of times in the past, but I wanted to remember these little mistakes for future projects.</p>
<p>This isn&rsquo;t me being overly fussy. It&rsquo;s just me moving past the beginner mode of &ldquo;Yay I finished something!&rdquo; to hopefully more intermediate habits that ask &ldquo;how will I do better next time?&rdquo;</p>
<p>The hat pattern came from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/85015.Knitters_Handy_Book_Of_Patterns">The Knitter&rsquo;s Handy Book of Patterns</a> by Ann Budd. As I get more comfortable with knitting, my interests move from specific patterns to templates and techniques. This book seems a good step in that direction so far. Quite a few tables and charts, which calls out to old memories of gaming books. The tables are just math helpers though. I can see not needing them after a certain point. That&rsquo;s the day I&rsquo;ll be able to knit custom fit stuff from memory. Something to look forward to!</p>]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: On Modesty And Imposter Syndrome</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/on-modesty-and-imposter-syndrome/</guid>
  <description>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It’s a rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It’s something I’ll need to read again.
It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I’m glad.
Don’t get in your own way Imposter Syndrome is a thing, yes.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>personal</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/10/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-21.jpg"/></p>
<p>Articulating and addressing a chain of thought that kept me up last night. It&rsquo;s a  rain dump instead of a crafted essay, because the point was to get it down rather than to get it pretty. It&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ll need to read again.</p>
<p>It might not apply to you, but if some of it does I&rsquo;m glad.</p>
<h2 id="dont-get-in-your-own-way">Don&rsquo;t get in your own way</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.quickanddirtytips.com/health-fitness/medical-conditions/what-is-impostor-syndrome">Imposter Syndrome</a> is a thing, yes.</p>
<p>Anyone who pays attention and is honest with themselves knows there are things they do not know, and that other people know some of those things.</p>
<p>Some folks who see how much they don&rsquo;t know assume it means they know nothing of value. Massive oversimplification, but work with me here.</p>
<p>This assumes you value knowledge or competence, of course. If you don&rsquo;t, then we won&rsquo;t have much to talk about.</p>
<p>Modesty is good, in moderation. Pretending you know more than you do is at best tasteless, and can be dangerous.</p>
<p>But don&rsquo;t get in your own way.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been programming professionally for twenty years. I&rsquo;ve been knitting for well over ten years. I&rsquo;ve been sketching close to thirty years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m better than most folks at each of these. Granted, I&rsquo;m better partly because most folks don&rsquo;t do any of those things. BUT STILL.</p>
<p>I put in time. I learned things. I know things other practitioners know, and things not every practitioner knows.</p>
<p>I learn new things all the time. I just learned how to look up the spelling of a word with <a href="http://aspell.net/">GNU aspell</a>:</p>
<figure class="highlight">
  <pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"
    ><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span class="line"><span class="cl">$ <span class="nb">echo</span> practicioner <span class="p">|</span> aspell -a
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl">@<span class="o">(</span><span class="c1">#) International Ispell Version 3.1.20 (but really Aspell 0.60.7-20110707)</span>
</span></span><span class="line"><span class="cl"><span class="p">&amp;</span> practicioner <span class="m">6</span> 0: practitioner, practicing, practice, practiced, practices, practice<span class="err">&#39;</span>s</span></span></code></pre>
</figure><p>In every one of those domains I&rsquo;m <strong>convinced</strong> I&rsquo;m a raw beginner.</p>
<p>Because there are plenty of things I don&rsquo;t know, and because sometimes I get brain lock.</p>
<h2 id="brain-lock">Brain lock</h2>
<p>I usually only get brain lock when knowing the thing is important to me.</p>
<p>I <em>should</em> know the thing. I should know <em>something</em>. I knew lots of things a second ago. But suddenly I don&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know the answer. I don&rsquo;t know the question. I don&rsquo;t know how to brain. All I know is to be furious at myself.</p>
<p>Is the brain lock just me getting into emotional overload because I didn&rsquo;t <em>immediately</em> have an acceptable answer?</p>
<p>Is that one of those &ldquo;gifted child grows up&rdquo; kind of problems? Yeesh what a depressing thought.</p>
<p>Whatever it is, that brain lock gets in the way.</p>
<p>It gets in the way at work. It gets in the way in relationships. Oh goodness does it get in the way in relationships.</p>
<p>So I think I&rsquo;m a beginner because I&rsquo;m still mad at myself for not knowing everything immediately? Maybe.</p>
<p>Regardless of why I feel this way, I need to get over it.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<h2 id="stack-building">Stack building</h2>
<p>Started focusing on the crisis moments there, when the original thought was about modesty and Imposter Syndrome.</p>
<p>But that&rsquo;s part of the point, isn&rsquo;t it? Taking a specific moment, generalizing it, and then judging yourself based on the generalization?</p>
<p>And then deciding what you are and are not capable of based on that judgment?</p>
<p>And then not doing the thing because you already decided you wouldn&rsquo;t be good at it?</p>
<p>Hey look at me I built a stack of cognitive distortions!</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s pop the stack. How would I look at these if it was someone else?</p>
<p>Avoiding action out of fear is its own entire stack of issues. Let&rsquo;s just set that one to the side for today.</p>
<p>A person&rsquo;s capabilities change. They may do better or even worse than you expected, but there is always the possibility of improvement.</p>
<p>Judging someone based on a general pattern of behavior is generally good but limited. They could surprise you given a new context.</p>
<p>Taking a particular moment and imagining this is how the person will behave in every moment is almost always a bad idea.</p>
<p>Some folks I feel perfectly content building a stack like this, but not many.</p>
<p>Certainly nobody I ever felt close to. I know I&rsquo;ve been fortunate in that regard.</p>
<p>I feel pretty close to myself.</p>
<h2 id="a-better-stack">A better stack</h2>
<p>So. Yeah. Sometimes I get brain lock. That sucks, and it&rsquo;s a thing I can work on.</p>
<p>Most of the time my brain is pretty good.</p>
<p>I know things, and I know how to learn more things.</p>
<p>If anything, my general pattern is wanting to learn more and do better.</p>
<p>You can always do better, but usually you&rsquo;re further along than the last time you tried this.</p>
<p>If it doesn&rsquo;t feel that way, you&rsquo;re in the frustrating part of getting better. But you&rsquo;re still getting better.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pattern I&rsquo;ve applied successfully throughout my life. Programming, knitting, sketching, juggling, being a decent human being.</p>
<p>Heck yeah being a decent human being takes wanting to learn more and do better. I&rsquo;m working on it <em>right now</em>.</p>
<p>There we go. I built a better cognitive stack. I&rsquo;ll keep revisiting it of course.</p>
<p>Getting rid of the old one takes more than just seeing it.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been with me my whole life, so tearing it down will be the work of a lifetime.</p>
<p>But look at how much I&rsquo;ve done even with that stack in place!</p>
<p>I can still be realistically modest. I can also take pride in what I <em>have</em> accomplished, and what I&rsquo;m continuing to accomplish.</p>
<p>Not entirely sure it&rsquo;s still about modesty or Imposter Syndrome, but I&rsquo;ll leave the title. And I&rsquo;ll fight the urge to just stash this file away somewhere, because posting makes it more concrete. I have an easier time holding myself accountable with a post. After all, this isn&rsquo;t the first time I&rsquo;ve seen and worked on bits of my cognitive stack.</p>
<p>Now go knit or something.</p>
<p><em>Take a deep breath. Relax. You got this.</em></p>
<p>PS. Still not smoking. It&rsquo;ll be five months on Saturday.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Trying Beorg</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/trying-beorg/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/10/trying-beorg/</guid>
  <description>This is not a review. This is me, excitedly sharing screenshots of the shiny thing I am playing with.
NOTE
My beorg screenshots are in the Dark theme, which is currently the only paid add-on for the app. All functionality I look at today is part of the free core. I’m perfectly happy putting out 99 cents if it helps development a little bit.
You can also contribute directly to feature development by making a contribution in Settings.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>orgconfig</category>  <category>tools</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>The beorg iOS app has me playing with Org mode again</h2><p>This is not a review. This is me, excitedly sharing screenshots of the shiny thing I am playing with.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-14.png" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-10-14.png"/></p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>NOTE</strong></p>
<p>My beorg screenshots are in the Dark theme, which is currently the only paid add-on for the app. All functionality I look at today is part of the free core. I’m perfectly happy putting out 99 cents if it helps development a little bit.</p>
<p>You can also contribute directly to feature development by making a contribution in Settings.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Does <a href="https://beorgapp.com/">beorg</a> support your favorite <a href="/card/org/">card/Org</a> feature? I have no idea. But I can add,
schedule, edit, and save tasks.</p>
<p>You <em>could</em> manage everything on your phone, but synchronization is an important feature for me. Synchronizing org files via <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a> – or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebDAV">WebDAV</a> if that’s more your thing – works in both directions. I prefer <a href="https://syncthing.net/">Syncthing</a> but I’ll take what I can get. Who knows? Maybe I’ll figure out WebDAV later.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/attachments/img/2018/emacs-synced.png" alt="Emacs showing task added in beorg"/></p>
<h2 id="todo-view">TODO view</h2>
<p>The TODO view lists tasks, including clear indications of scheduled completion – assuming you understand the notation.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/attachments/img/2018/agenda-view.png" alt="TODO view"/></p>
<p>The Rainer König Org <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sQS06Qjnkcc&amp;list=PLVtKhBrRV_ZkPnBtt_TD1Cs9PJlU0IIdE">tutorials</a> on YouTube are great stuff. I’m going through them again myself for a refresher, and I highly recommend them if you want to learn Emacs Org mode.</p>
<p>The TODO view supports multiple filters.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/attachments/img/2018/agenda-filtered.png" alt="Filtered TODO view"/></p>
<h2 id="notifications">Notifications</h2>
<p>The app icon badge shows the count of overdue tasks.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/attachments/img/2018/notifications.jpg" alt="Overdue count shown on app icon"/></p>
<p>Alarms pop up for deadlines.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/10/attachments/img/2018/alarm.png" alt="Task notification"/></p>
<p>I better wrap it up.</p>
<h2 id="also">Also</h2>
<p>beorg includes other features I don’t feel like looking at today.</p>
<p>The Agenda view integrates with your calendar events, which is both very handy and not something I feel comfortable sharing with the entire world :smile:</p>
<p>The Files view gives you something closer to a raw edit of your Org files, but honestly that’s pretty darned clunky on a phone for me. For the moment I’ll stick with high level task management on the phone, and Emacs org mode if I need anything more involved.</p>
<h2 id="anyways">Anyways</h2>
<p>Try out <a href="https://beorgapp.com/">beorg</a> if you’re on iOS. Read the <a href="https://beorgapp.com/manual/">manual</a> for a more in-depth look at features and usage. I’m going to go reschedule that art project. I have other things that are higher priority.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Cougar Mountain</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/cougar-mountain/</guid>
  <description>The park sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.
Be careful Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Last weekend I wandered the trails of Cougar Mountain Regional Wildland Park
</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/09/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-30.jpg"/></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.kingcounty.gov/services/parks-recreation/parks/parks-and-natural-lands/popular-parks/cougar.aspx">park</a> sits just outside Bellevue, Washington. There’s been a lot of construction in the area thanks to the steady influx of tech workers and others. Passing housing development after housing development along the way gave me low expectations for the park itself. Suddenly there were more trees than houses, and moments later there was a 3,100 acre woodland park.</p>
<h2 id="be-careful">Be careful</h2>
<p>Cougar Mountain only became a park relatively recently. Warning signs remind you about the area’s long history as a coal mine. Collapsed mines could collapse further with just a little weight on them. A decades-old underground fire presents ongoing <a href="https://www.heraldnet.com/news/cougar-mountain-mines-still-a-danger/">danger</a> from heat and toxic fumes.</p>
<p>Basically: if a sign tells me to stay back, I stay back.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/warning-sign.jpg" title="Pay attention to the warning signs" alt="sign warning of ground collapse or fatal gases"/></p>
<p>The trails are well-labeled, perhaps partly due to those hazards. I still managed to get myself turned around, because there were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cougar_Mountain_Regional_Wildland_Park#Official_Trails">so many trails</a>. Somewhere along the way I lost my paper map, but had enough signal to get the Washington Trails Association <a href="https://www.wta.org/our-work/about/trailblazer-mobile-app">Trailblazer</a> app installed on my phone and follow the links to a PDF map.</p>
<h2 id="look-at-the-trees">Look at the trees</h2>
<p>I think I focused a little too much on the hazards. Those are really in specific sections of the park, and are all clearly indicated. The park itself is lovely, green, and very Pacific Northwest.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/mossy.jpg" alt="Mossy"/></p>
<p>We have some lovely woods around here. I started taking that for granted over the years. My assorted <a href="/tags/sauntering">sauntering</a> trips have done a great job reminding me to not do that.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/tall-stump.jpg" alt="Tall stump"/></p>
<p>The trees on Cougar Mountain are young. When the mines started winding down, logging picked up. I saw several thick old stumps near the trail, giving me a hint of what the older growth must have looked like.</p>
<p>Some of those stumps had sprouts on them, while a few had full grown trees.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/old-stump.jpg" alt="Old stump with stump sprouts"/></p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/stump-tree.jpg" alt="Tree growing from stump"/></p>
<p>We got some rain recently. Everything that could be green was very green indeed. Even the rocks. I walked a little out of my way to see Fantastic Erratic, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glacial_erratic">glacial erratic</a> boulder left here by glacier action in some past ice age.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/fantastic-erratic.jpg" title="Fantastic Erratic" alt="Large mossy rock"/></p>
<p>My image shows the scale poorly. That single rock is roughly fifteen feet high. I took a rest break sitting on top of it, with room to stretch.</p>
<h2 id="anyways">Anyways</h2>
<p>I spent three hours walking about ten miles of trails around Cougar Mountain, enjoying the scenery and history. It didn’t feel as epic as <a href="/post/2018/09/mount-si/">walking up a mountain</a>, but I want to avoid chasing that &ldquo;epic&rdquo; feeling. I’m not racking up accomplishments. I’m getting out and appreciating more of the world around me. That includes epic moments, little details, and everything in between.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/fungi.jpg" title="Look! Fungus!" alt="clamshell-looking fungi on a tree trunk"/></p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post: Mount Si</title>
  <link>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</link>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
  
  <guid>https://randomgeekery.org/post/2018/09/mount-si/</guid>
  <description>A rather rocky trail through the trees
Mount Si If Mount Si looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show Twin Peaks. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s.</description>
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>post</category> 
   <category>exploring</category>  <category>marginalia</category> 
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>I sauntered up the main trail of Mount Si this weekend.</h2><p><img src="/post/2018/09/../../../attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg" alt="attachments/img/2018/cover-2018-09-09.jpg"/>
A rather rocky trail through the trees</p>
<h2 id="mount-si">Mount Si</h2>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/mt-si.jpg" alt="Mount Si as seen from North Bend"/></p>
<p>If <a href="https://www.wta.org/go-hiking/hikes/mount-si">Mount Si</a> looks familiar to you even though you don’t live near it, maybe you saw it as part of the scenery of the television show <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twin_Peaks">Twin Peaks</a>. It sits right next to the town of North Bend, about 30 miles east of Seattle. Formerly a site for logging and quarrying, the beauty of the mountain was preserved through the efforts of state legislator Frances North in the 1970s. It was officially labeled a Natural Resources Conservation Area in 1987.</p>
<p>The Olympic and Cascade mountains defined my landscape growing up in the Puget Sound area, but I never went up any of them. I attribute that to my habit of mentally associating &ldquo;mountain climbing&rdquo; with the major challenge of Mount Rainier. I never thought of smaller mountains such as Mount Si. They challenge desk-bound people like myself but can still be done as a single day trip.</p>
<p>Oh, you pronounce &ldquo;Si&rdquo; as &ldquo;sigh&rdquo; — not &ldquo;see.&rdquo;</p>
<h2 id="getting-there">Getting there</h2>
<p>The trail is a short drive from Seattle, but Google Maps gave me a hard time. I ask for directions to Mount Si. It sends me to the base of the mountain, in somebody’s driveway and nowhere near a trail. Then I ask for directions to the Mount Si <em>Trail</em> and it tries to put me on a private road. This happens often enough that the owner put up a sign indicating there was no trail access on their property.</p>
<p>I abandoned Google Maps and found the trail proper a little further up the (public) road. You want to keep your eyes peeled. The sign for the trail is easy to miss if you don’t know the area.</p>
<p>Don’t forget about your <a href="http://discoverpass.wa.gov/">Discover Pass</a>! You need one to use the official parking spots, and there’s no public parking anywhere near the trail.</p>
<p>I admit it. I forgot about the pass. Fortunately, you can purchase one at the Ace Hardware in North Bend.</p>
<h2 id="the-trail">The trail</h2>
<p>The thing about sauntering up a mountain is that the trail occupies most of your attention. You might miss interesting stuff as you spend a few hours wondering how much trail you have left. Thankfully, the trail itself is pretty interesting. Some spots soft and flat, some spots packed with rocks, and sometimes both!</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/trail.jpg" alt="a trail section with packed rocks and dirt"/></p>
<p>The trail climbs around 3,000 feet over roughly four miles. A walk like that is easy enough for the experienced, but by the time I was halfway up I needed to rest every few minutes. Thank goodness nobody accompanied me! I bet a veteran walker would have been at best amused, and at worst annoyed, by my pace.</p>
<p>Nobody accompanied me, but I wasn’t alone. This trail gets loads of traffic, and has its own traffic rules.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you bring a dog, keep it on a leash, and clean up after it</li>
<li>People going up get right of way, so people going down need to make   room for them.</li>
<li>Be nice</li>
<li>Stay tidy — don’t be dropping garbage along the way!</li>
</ul>
<p>Everybody I encountered stuck with the rules, which were posted on an information board at the trail head. Well, I met a few off-leash dogs, but they were friendly.</p>
<p>My frequent breaks meant that I saw most sights while leaning or sitting on something, and waiting for my pulse to recover.</p>
<p>For example: my new, attractive, and very comfortable friend Stumpy the Stump.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/stumpy.jpg" alt="Check out this gnarled tree stump"/></p>
<p>I encountered impressive rocks all over the place. That’s not unusual in the Pacific Northwest, but you rarely see anything so <em>large</em> in Seattle.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/rock.jpg" alt="Rock!"/></p>
<p>Of course I looked up the details when I got home. These are <a href="https://www.usgs.gov/faqs/what-are-metamorphic-rocks-0">metamorphic</a> rocks, transformed by intense pressure. Apparently in the distant geological past, there was an oceanic plate volcano. Now, millions of years later, we walk around on it and call it Mount Si.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/more-rock.jpg" alt="These rocks used to be under an ocean?"/></p>
<p>I can’t help but feel very small and brief when I try wrapping my brain around a geological time scale.</p>
<h2 id="lunch">Lunch</h2>
<p>Eventually I ran out of mountain. I paused to have lunch and enjoy the view with half a dozen other like-minded folks.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/lunch.jpg" alt="Eating lunch and looking over Snoqualmie"/></p>
<p>I encountered few local critters on the way up. That’s probably because the ones that tolerate people knew to stick around up here where folks brought out food. Gray jays, chipmunks, and a wandering raven kept us company.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/grayjay.jpg" title="A photogenic gray jay posing — right before stealing my cracker!" alt="gray jay bird"/></p>
<p>Keep a tight grip on your meal! One jay grabbed a cracker right out of my hand when a hiker distracted me.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/jay-rocks.jpg" alt="Gray jay against rocks"/></p>
<p>I suppose a bird has to make a living. I can’t be mad when they’re so fearless and just so <em>pretty</em>.</p>
<h2 id="wandering-a-little-further">Wandering a little further</h2>
<p>So many folks came up, ate their lunch, and headed right back down. That confused me, because I was nowhere near done enjoying Mount Si. Maybe this is just a routine weekend thing for them. Me? Even if this becomes routine I’ll find excuses to stick around longer. Maybe I can bring my knitting.</p>
<p>I had read that the trail extended beyond my lunch spot, so I looked around until I saw the Haystack, an additional 200 feet of rock that marks the proper peak of Mount Si.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/haystack.jpg" title="The Haystack, Si&#39;s true summit" alt="rocky peak"/></p>
<p>I decided against climbing the Haystack this time. Almost halfway, I realized going down would be harder than going up. My body still felt the strain from walking up the mountain in the first place. Next trip.</p>
<p>Got some nice shots before I started back down, though.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/lovely.jpg" title="Sure the trees will break my fall eventually" alt="treetops seen from above"/></p>
<p>I spent the next hour or so lounging in the overlook between the Haystack and the gray jay crime haven, looking at flowers and appreciating the view.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/flowers.jpg" alt="Flower!"/></p>
<p>Surely the view impresses even more on clear days, but clouds are familiar to me. A clear sky would have disoriented me.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/overlook.jpg" alt="View from the overlook"/></p>
<p>A memorial marker placed at the overlook caught my eye.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/brett-marker.jpg" title="Memorial marker for Brett Hall 1962-1981" alt="memorial marker"/></p>
<p>Later I looked up the name on the marker, and found this nwhikers forum<a href="http://www.nwhikers.net/forums/viewtopic.php?p=202011&amp;sid=1b5ffb6683037d9488f2bbb5e5f4218b#202011">comment</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Brett Hall was from Lynnwood. His family used to live next door to mine. He disappeared on an intended dayhike on Mt Si with, I think, a group of friends. They searched at the time but didn’t find him; the assumption was that he took a tumble down a hill, or got disoriented, sat down and died of hypothermia. I’m not sure about the January 25th, 1981 date&ndash; or why they were hiking in the winter. (I was away at college at the time, so my info was secondhand.) If I recall, his body was found a year or so later after the snow melted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So, yeah. Caution is smart even on small, popular mountains close to urban centers.</p>
<h2 id="heading-back">Heading back</h2>
<p>Once I rested enough — and my phone started running low on charge after so many pics — I headed back down the trail. Going down took less time than going up. Even so I took care, because those rocks in the path feel ever so solid when your feet are landing on them from above.</p>
<p>The sun came out when I was near the bottom of the mountain, and it was so gorgeous I felt the temptation to climb back up.</p>
<p><img src="/post/2018/09/attachments/img/2018/sunshine.jpg" alt="Afternoon sun through trees and undergrowth"/></p>
<p>My feet would have hated me. Besides, because of my timing, I got back to Seattle at exactly the right moment to get waved at on West Seattle Bridge by a trolley bus full of furries having their own special day! That was an awesome &ldquo;welcome home!&rdquo; moment.</p>
<h2 id="the-aftermath">The aftermath</h2>
<p>I wore better shoes than at <a href="/post/2018/08/island-center-forest/">Island Center Forest</a>, so my feet feel fine today. My knees got more work than usual, but at least I can walk without major discomfort.</p>
<p>One thing is for sure: next time I go walking up a mountain, I bring my
<em>inbox/Knitting</em>!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
